<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Medicina magica tamen physica: magical, but natural physick. Or A methodical tractate of diastatical physick. Containing the general cures of all infirmities: and of the most radical, fixed, and malignant diseases belonging, not only to the body of man, but to all other animal and domestick creatures whatsoever, and that by way of transplantation. With a description of a most excellent cordial out of gold, much to be estimated. / Published by Samuel Boulton, Salop.</title>
            <author>Boulton, Samuel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 231 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 106 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77127</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3833A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1678_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209147</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868037</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868037</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170252</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77127)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170252)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 210:E1678[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Medicina magica tamen physica: magical, but natural physick. Or A methodical tractate of diastatical physick. Containing the general cures of all infirmities: and of the most radical, fixed, and malignant diseases belonging, not only to the body of man, but to all other animal and domestick creatures whatsoever, and that by way of transplantation. With a description of a most excellent cordial out of gold, much to be estimated. / Published by Samuel Boulton, Salop.</title>
                  <author>Boulton, Samuel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 192, 191-195, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.C. for N. Brook, at the Angel in Cornhil,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a final advertisement leaf.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June: 21.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Diseases --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Medicine --  Formulae, receipts, prescriptions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Veterinary medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quacks and quackery --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170252:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MEDICINA MAGICA <hi>TAMEN PHYSICA:</hi> Magical, but Natural Phyſick. OR A Methodical Tractate of <hi>Diaſtatical Phyſick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Containing the general Cures of all infirmities: And of the moſt radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, fixed, and malignant Diſeaſes belonging, not only to the Body of Man, but to all other Animal and Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick creatures whatſoever, and that by way of <hi>TRANSPLANTATION.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With a Deſcription of a moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Cordial out of Gold, much to be eſtimated.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by <hi>Samuel Boulton, Salop,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ars non habet inimicum niſi ignorantem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. C.</hi> for <hi>N. Brook,</hi> at the Angel in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> 1656</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170252:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170252:2"/>
            <head>TO The Right Honourable The Marqueſs of DORCHESTER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Candor of your affections to theſe <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſculapian</hi> Myſteries, by divers of my acquaintance frequently related unto me, together with the prompti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of your Genius to thoſe ſublime and ineſtimable trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures occulted in Spagirical o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations, Hermetically per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, have preſſed on my
<pb facs="tcp:170252:3"/>preſumption to this Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Epiſtle, without your Honors conſent or licence firſt obtained. <hi>Horace</hi> had his <hi>Maecenas,</hi> and <hi>Virgil</hi> his <hi>Auguſtus;</hi> and it is the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed manner of our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Writers, alwaies to pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liate themſelves under the Protection of ſome worthy Patron. I queſtion not but that harmonious temper of your well-diſpoſed nature will accept in good part the raſh attempt of your well-meaning, and yet unknown ſervant. I confeſs it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs to ſtamp the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of your Honours Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb facs="tcp:170252:3"/>upon ſuch an abortive; and could I imagine the child in the future would become the leaſt diſparagement to the dignity of the Godfather, I would even now ſtrangle it in the Cradle. Vouchſafe then (moſt gracious Lord) one ſmile from your ſerene coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance upon this tender In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant, caſt out into the wilde world, ready to be devoured with the dupilicated teeth of <hi>Zoilian</hi> Sharks. The ſhadow of your Honours wings is the only Solace it can expect, to whoſe tuition I only com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it for protection, humbly imploring your Lordſhips fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable
<pb facs="tcp:170252:4"/>conſtruction of this my incivility, I take leave, and reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours truly devoted though moſt ignoted ſervant <hi>SAM. BOLTON.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Pridie nonas</hi> Maii 1646.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170252:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is an Engliſh Proverb, that <hi>Good Wine needs no buſh;</hi> and the Latines ſay, <hi>Veritas non quaerit angulos:</hi> And it is my opinion, that Books that are true in their Theorick, and beneficial in their Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctick, can want no buyers. The truth in this ſmall Tractate I conceive undeniable, and the benefit ineſtimable. Truly I have locked it up faſt for this ten years ſpace in the moſt ſecret corners of my Cloſet, ever jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous leſt any of the deareſt of my acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance ſhould have caſt their eyes upon it, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring it as an unvaluable Jewel, that was too precious for the worlds acquaintance and publick Surveigh. The reaſon of my Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation now, I aſsure thee, is not for oſtentation ſake, nor the ambitious thought of vain-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or ſelf-end: But God having lately viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me with, though a ſhort, yet violent fit of ſickneſſe, conſidering upon my recovery that this was the greateſt talent that I eſtimated amongſt the treaſures of this life, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving written a great part of it in looſe pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers in quarto, and ſome of that in Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cterical figures, only for occultneſse ſake, and the reſidue I had tranſcribed into ſeveral
<pb facs="tcp:170252:5"/>places of a ſmall Manuſcript in octavo; with other matters (for the cauſe aforeſaid) interpoſed and inſerted; ſo that I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, had I then died, it had been either ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly loſt, or by the confuſed and occult wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting never been digeſted into any methodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal order. This (I confeſſe) was the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and moſt materiall cauſe that indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced me to this Publication. I ingeniouſly confeſs it is not all from mine own <hi>Minerva,</hi> I was beholding for ſome part thereof (which occaſioned the whole) to a worthy Gentleman of <hi>Kent,</hi> one Mr. <hi>M. B.</hi> a dear friend of mine, who had ſome looſe papers of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Mr. but by us ſuppoſed to proceed from that late worthy and Reverend Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt Dr. <hi>Everard.</hi> If a friendly and cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous acceptation hereof be perceived, it may in a ſhort time occaſion an addition of ſome more of the very depth of this Art to enſue this Tractate. In the interim I ſhall bid thee farewel with this advice, <hi>Lege fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenter, &amp; relege diligenter;</hi> and ſo thoſe things that at firſt ſeem difficult and intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, will become facile and manifeſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>London <date>pridie nonas <hi>Maij.</hi> 1656.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Vale </salute>
               <signed>S. BOULTON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170252:5"/>
            <head>MEDICINA MAGICA <hi>Tamen Phyſica.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore I come to treat of the Practical part of this Art, it is very requiſite ſomething ſhould be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken concerning the The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orical grounds thereof: and that for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers cauſes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it will be an occaſion to clear the Title of this Book, and manifeſtly declare, that as it is really <hi>Magica,</hi> ſo is it truly <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: though ſome obſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous Ignorants, and other pragmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Opinioniſts, through the little know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the Principles of true Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, and leſſe judgement in the grounds of occult Phyſick have, and ſtill (I queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not) but will bend all the ſtrength of their wilful miſty knowledge againſt the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170252:6"/>truth hereof: inconſiderately crying out, <hi>Away with it, it is Diabolical: Away with it, it is ſuperſtitious:</hi> when as if theſe and the like <hi>Ignoramus'es</hi> will but with the eye of Modeſty weigh the enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing concluſions, they cannot in truth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the original of this Art to be groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of nothing but true (yet ſublime) natural cauſes, and therefore all the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and operations thereof to be tyed and depend upon no other but the ſame cauſes; requiring not ſo much of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite faith from any party, in any of the Cures, as <hi>Hippocrates</hi> himſelf requires in a Patient, concerning a meer <hi>Galeniſt</hi> or any other though but an Empirical Profeſſor. And that is, that the Patient ought to have a good conceit, both of the Phyſician and the Medicine, the which will greatly further the Cure, as he ſaith.</p>
            <p>This is now an abſolute binding of an implicite faith, and the force of imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will work wonders, as is wel under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of all thoſe that know how right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to uſe and make application thereof; but of this we ſhall have occaſion to ſpeak more hereafter.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as the ſaid Theorical Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170252:6"/>will vindicate and cleare the Title of this Book from ſuſpition of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abolical Magick, ſo in the next place it will open a fair and large gap to many rare and ſingular Experiments, which the true Sons of Art will in time bring to light, having no ſmall taſte but very great encouragement from theſe funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Principles: indeed they are Pearls, and therefore ought not to be caſt to ſwine, for truly the world is ſcarce worthy of them, (for next the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine truth which concernes our ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) there is no truth more ineſtimable, nor no ſecrets more ſublime in all the Treaſury of Nature. A taſte of three of theſe unvaluable Experiments you ſhall finde in the concluſion enſuing, in very ſhort but ſignificant words.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, as the aforeſaid Theorical concluſions will not onely clear the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of this Book, but alſo open a gap to many ſingular ſecrets; ſo in the laſt place it will be the main guide and light of the practical part, by profound con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration whereof the Practice will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear very eaſie and manifeſt. I deny not but divers Authors have heretofore written of the ſame ſubject, and under
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170252:7"/>the name of <hi>Medicina Diaſtatica:</hi> as <hi>Paracelſus</hi> ſomething, but very occultly, and <hi>Tenzelius</hi> likewiſe, but very obſcure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: So Dr. <hi>Floyd,</hi> and ſome other late Writers; but all that I have ſeen have ſo wrapped up the quinteſſence of the Art in ſuch <hi>Aenigma's</hi> and clouds of obſcuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that little or nothing can be gained from them, rather diſcourſing thereof, and declaring there is ſuch an Art in <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura rerum,</hi> then teaching any thing. Only I confeſſe the Weapon-ſalve hath been the moſt ſecret in this Art divul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: and that hath been publiſhed by <hi>Oſwaldus Croilius</hi> in his <hi>Baſilica Chymica,</hi> under the Title of his <hi>Vulneraria:</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Sympathetick powder made from the body of <hi>Vitriol,</hi> and alſo the water hath been known to ſome few, the reſidue of this famous Art hath been cloſely concealed from the vulgar: and ſo I conceive it ſtill fit to be, for <hi>ne ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor ultra crepidam,</hi> and truly I confeſſe I have not ſo clearly drawn the curtains that all may apparently be diſcerned: But what I have wrote I writ to the Sons of Art, and ingeniouſly confeſſe it is the plaineſt and moſt methodical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt diſcourſe of this Art, that hitherto
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170252:7"/>is extant. But to returne <hi>ad Propoſitum,</hi> our firſt Concluſion ſhall be this <hi>Exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="conclusion">
               <head>CONCLUSION I. <hi>That the Soule works without or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond his proper body ſo called.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NO true Philoſopher will diſſent from this Tenet. The <hi>Peripatetticks</hi> themſelves, together with <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> doe confeſſe that the ſoule executes ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions without the body: neither hath there been wanting ſome Divines which have attributed a certain kind of ubiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the ſoules affirming to be preſent where it worketh: Certainly that the imagination worketh without and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond his own being, I take it to be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, and Experience will convince any one doubting thereof, for it works on the <hi>Embryon,</hi> otherwiſe how could faſcinations be performed? and what is imagination but the handmaid of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170252:8"/>ſoule, by which it works without the body? But to come neerer to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>I</hi> muſt tell you that the ſoul muſt neceſſarily be whereſoever the vital ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is found, for this ſpirit is the <hi>medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> or bond by which the ſoule is tyed to the body, or rather is the undivided companion thereof, and here it is never extended further then the ſoule it ſelfe, without which the ſpirit cannot ſubſiſt: then if a mans body work ſomething with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it ſelf, ſurely it works as informed by the ſoul: And ſhall it not then work vitally, and produce vital actions? but how ſhall it produce them? without doubt in and by the vertue and power of the forme, which is the ſoule; but except I be deceived, there can nothing work in the power of another, and not be partaker of it; therefore the active beames that produce ſuch effects without the body, muſt needs be partakers of the ſoule by which they work; and I think no man can be ſo ſenſeleſſe to deny acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons extrinſecal, or without the body, to man, the moſt noble compound, and yet grant them to plants and ſtones: for from whence proceeds their vertues but from their ſpecifick formes? or how
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170252:8"/>came their vertues to be diſcovered but by their ſignatures? <hi>Vide Oſwaldum Crollium in lib. de ſignat. rerum:</hi> but that operations depend upon formes, it hath alwayes ſeemed true to the moſt Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Some alſo are of opinion that the Seed doth beget the <hi>Embrion</hi> in the vertue of the Father, which it could not doe, were it not upholden and furniſhed with the preſence of the fathers ſoule: But I hear ſome whiſper this objection; that this opinion can no way be conſonant to truth, becauſe that then if the Father ſhould dye aſſoon as he had begotten a child, his ſoule, being freed from the bonds of the body, goeth to his appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted place; how then can it work in the <hi>Embrion?</hi> But to him that judiciouſly contemplates this matter, it will appear no great difficulty whether it be ſaid that the ſoul is not utterly &amp; abſolutely free ſo long as any vital ſpirit remaines ſafe and unaltered, for there it ſticks &amp; abides as long, and until its ſubject be quite converted into another thing: And then becauſe it wants organical inſtruments (as in an Appoplexy is very apparent) it cannot performe any ſenſible action; or elſe whether it may be ſaid rather that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170252:9"/>ſoule is neceſſarily preſent at thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations by a certain preſence, and yet not hindered but that in another place it may performe other works; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the ſoule doth by wonderful and ſtrange meanes produce divers things in the body, and is after divers manners in divers places; why ſhall it not when it is free from the body doe the ſame things, or the like? for it wants not its inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of its proper natural heat, which is onely fit to produce an effect. Now out of what hath been ſaid the cauſe is evident, why about the graves of them that die a violent death, there appeare often <hi>Spectra's,</hi> and many times Appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are viſible: for the ſpirit and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural moiſture being not quite diſſolved, the ſoule ſticks and gives ſometimes the exhalations impregnated with this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, the forme of a man, and ſometimes in Church-yards the like are ſeen: And from the ſame reaſon a corps ſlain blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth at the touch or preſence of the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer, for the ſage and vital ſpirits, or both, muſt needs produce theſe effects. Now if the ſoule doe and can (without the body) act; (for the ſoule in its eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence includes act) and therefore cannot
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170252:9"/>but act, it operates therefore according to the organs informed, or according to the manner of information, ſeeing it communicates a forme to the ſubject: and peradventure it may be eſteemed more agreeable to naked and pure truth to call the ſoule not the forme, but the giver of forme. Hereupon it ſeems that <hi>Plato</hi> placed in man a threefold diſtinct forme, yet depending upon the common ſoule: It is true, that to theſe inferiour formes the name of ſoule is ſometimes given, but how truly and properly, let them anſwer, who onely accuſtomed to ſpeculation, have learned to ſeparate the vital actions from the ſoule, which only proceed from it; but omitting all theſe difficulties, we will be content to uſe the common names, which will ſerve our occaſions ſufficiently.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But here ſome may take an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to make this Objection, That if the ſoule be and work without the body, or beſides it, by informing the natural heat, and that proceeds without it, and is inherent in his beams, then thoſe beams muſt needs be living creatures conſiſting of a ſoul &amp; a body, and ſo conſequently men; &amp; this Objection may ſeem of ſome
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170252:10"/>moment to thoſe who are but little perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacious or be but <hi>Infantulae in natura re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> as I may ſo term them. But now I anſwer,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, that it is as abſurd, for ought that I have ſaid, to call theſe beames creatures, and ſo by conſequence men, as to call the feet and hands men. Secondly, Every bare information doth not make a man; for it is requiſite that a reaſonable ſoule doe informe an orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical body, and that by meanes of the forme it be made fit for organical ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations; for if the ſoule informe any compound onely vegetable, or ſome other inferiour thing by another way to us not known, it cannot therefore be called a man; for the ſoul informs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the merit of the matter, as the <hi>Platoniſts</hi> hold: or more clearly it informes according to the portion of the vital ſpirits that is preſent; for every portion of this is not fit for operation: And hence it appeareth, that though the ſoule doe for ſome time inform a corps with a certain form (as we ſee in dead carcaſſes, the vegetative faculty doth after death for a time exerciſe his power, which cannot be done without the ſoul)
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170252:10"/>yet that corps cannot be called a man; for being deprived of ſenſe and reaſon, it hath loſt that dignity; but it is moſt certain, that the ſoul being preſent on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly according to the vegetable power, may work elſewhere: for when it was tyed to the body according to all the wayes of vicallity, it did perform many other operations: Why then when it is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther free from theſe bonds, or leaſt tyed with them, ſhould it not work things proper to it ſelfe? there is no reaſon known to the contrary: It may therefore according to the will of the Creator en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy pleaſure, or be tormented with pain, (although it be as yet tyed to the dead corps in the manner aforeſaid, ſeeing that in the vegetative faculty it ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer nothing till it be again united to an organical body: But after what manner the ſoul doth ſuffer, when it is freed from the organical body, we ſhall leave to Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, for it is moſt proper to leave ſuch Theological diſcourſes to them which it moſt appertains to, deſiring only leave to diſpute natural things naturally. But it is now full time we proceed to our ſecond Concluſion, which we will ſtate as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:170252:11"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. CONCLUS. II. <hi>From every body floweth corporal beames, which the Soule makes by its preſence, and diſtributeth to them Energie and power of work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and theſe beames are not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly corporeal, but alſo of divers parts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe firſt part of this Concluſion will eaſily appear to them that conſider the operations of natural things, and the impediment of thoſe ſaid operations; for what reaſon can there be demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, why bodies more ſolid then the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of things doe require, work not ſo freely as bodies leſſe compact? Is it not becauſe the pores of thoſe bodies being ſhut and more cloſely conjuncted, the corporeal beames cannot finde a due egreſſe. And now unleſſe they were cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal, no affection that is meerly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170252:11"/>could hinder them: And nothing but the change of the forme could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoy the faculties of things; but we ſee, that though the forme remain, the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations are hindered. Moreover, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe theſe beames were corporeal, their operations would proceed to any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and not be hindered by any bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. If you anſwer, it is by an accident by which things work at a diſtance; why then that accident muſt needs be in a ſubject, and muſt needs work by the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of that ſubject in which it is: for I take it to be certain, that no accident, barely conſidered in it ſelfe, can have activity; and therefore except ſuch beams be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, nothing can work at diſtance by any meanes, therefore thoſe accidents muſt be placed in corporeal beams, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing all manner of vertues of that bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy from whence they proceed: But I would not any one ſhould ſuppoſe I am a maintainer of accidents, who could never as yet diſcern any thing in nature but ſubſtance; unleſſe any man will goe about to conſtitute the poſitions and manners of things ſomething really diſtinct from the bodies; but here I ſpeak out of ſuppoſition, granting
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170252:12"/>ſomething that peradventure ſome would gladly ask at my hand. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides what hath been ſaid for our beams, we may adde, that adventitious heat doth promote and adjuvate the operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of things; and how could it do this but by ſtirring up more plentiful beams to iſſue forth? for example ſake we may perceive in <hi>Amber,</hi> how being heated by rubbing, attracts the chaff to it more forcibly, and many other the like things, that will not operate ſo ſtrongly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out they be heated, which heat doth more plenteouſly exhale thoſe corporeal beames, and addeth a dexterity to their operations: Moroever, ſolidity and cloſeneſſe would not keep the power of things unhurt, but that it hinders the diſſipation and ſpending of the beames: Again, unleſſe the beames were corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real, they would pierce and work through the moſt compacted bodies, the contrary whereof experience manifeſtly teſtifies; though in truth ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded bodies ſend out ſo thin &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle beams, that may pierce through the the pores of all bodies. But to what end do we conceive Nature did ordaine pores in bodies, but that they might be
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170252:12"/>the doors by which theſe beams might iſſue in and out: Alſo the ſenſes could never perceive things ſenſible, but that there proceeds beams from the bodies affecting the ſenſes, as appeares in ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, for odour periſheth with age, and that for no other cauſe then that the beams periſh which conveyeth the odour to our noſtrils; ſo from all bodies there iſſues ſubtil thin rayes, carrying with them the ſhapes of things, which is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to be perceptible to the eyes in a dark place by the help of a tranſlucid connex glaſſe: Againe, unleſſe theſe beames were corporeal, let any man tell me how they could affect the ſenſes; but I have rather wondred, how being mingled with ſo great a confuſion in paſſing though the glaſſe, they can ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally explicate themſelves. But let us proceed yet to another ſtrong argument, and more agreeing to our purpoſe, to prove what we principally intend, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that ſuch beams or rays do in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued motion iſſue out of the bodies of all wights; which we ſhall eaſily perform, if we conſider the common natures of all wights; for every creature or wight, that it may live any ſpace, muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170252:13"/>be nouriſhed with food, neither can it live long without it, becauſe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual iſſuing out of the beames would otherwiſe too much alter the body from its natural diſpoſition, and induce more vacuity and emptineſſe then nature hath appointed for ſuch a body: Now that which in food is dry, reſtoreth the ſolid parts of the body, that which is moiſt, the humours; and why hath Nature need of this reſtauration? becauſe eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day, nay every moment, theſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proeal beames doe plenteouſly iſſue out from the body, yea and from every part thereof; for if this were not ſo, then living creatures would grow to an enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and monſtrous greatneſſe: And this is alſo the cauſe why creatures decay and fall to deſtruction, and are not ſo long lived as ſtones or trees, or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the more compacter and more ſolid ſort of bodies; for the vital ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and natural heat being in creatures free and more at liberty, operate more powerfully, and produce more plenteous exhalations; whence it comes to paſſe that they are propagated to the greateſt diſtance, the ſoule all the while conne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting together, leſt they ſhould be utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170252:13"/>diſſipated; for otherwiſe they coul by no means hold the ſpecifick vertue of the body, neither could they work, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the ſoule informed them; for in it lies the natural heat, as hereafter ſhall be ſhewed, which produceth a ſufficient diſpoſition to receive information from the ſoule. But here ſome may ſay, we have ſpoken all this while much, and many things concerning the ſoule, but have not declared what it is, or ſo much as given a bare definition thereof; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for their ſatisfaction, and to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate the enſuing Diſcourſe, we will in the next Chapter ſpeak ſomething thereof before we proceed any further.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:170252:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. CONCLUS. III. <hi>Firſt what the Soul of man is: Next what the ſoules of beaſts and other living creatures are. Laſtly of the powers and properties which the Soul of man hath common with the ſouls of beaſts and plants, which is onely proper and peculiar to our Diſcourſe, and this enſuing Art.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ANd firſt we will declare the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Galen, Plato, Ariſtotle,</hi> with ſome other of the moſt Learned Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers of the Ancients; who ſpeaking of Man, have often called him a Great Miracle; and ſo indeed truly contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plated, he will appear; eſpecially in the particular contemplation of the Soule, which is truly Man: But to return to our purpoſe; <hi>Galen,</hi> a great adorer and profound ſearcher of Nature, durſt not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170252:14"/>peremptorily determine what the reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſoule was; yet for that which is commonly called the vegetative or nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing, and the ſenſitive or ſenſual ſoule, he boldly affirmd it to be no other thing then either the natural and vital ſpirits, or the temperament: But as for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſoule, he leaveth it in doubt whether it be of a corporeal nature, or ſome other which is not corporeal, and which ſubſiſteth by it ſelfe, being ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the body; neither doth he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude any thing otherwiſe, but that it is either a ſhining ſubſtance and an Aethere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al body, that is to ſay, of a more pure and celeſtial nature then any of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; or elſe that it is of a nature that is not corporeal, but yet hath this body (by which he meaneth the animal ſpirit) to be as a chariot to carry it. Thus much for <hi>Galens</hi> opinion.</p>
               <p>Next for <hi>Plato,</hi> who thus defines it; or rather indeed <hi>Alcinous ex ipſius Plato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ſententia,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>quae omnia hoc ſonant: Nam cum ſingula anima diſcernamus, meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to omnium rerum principium hanc appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit, ut quicquid unquam occurreret ex cogna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170252:15"/>quadam recognoſcentes rebus conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam illius eſsentiam adhiberemus, Ergo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co eſsequandam intelligibilem ſubſt untiam &amp; indiviſilem, &amp;c. Voluit igitur animam eſſe eſsentiam quandam quae ſe moveret.</hi> Thus much for <hi>Plato.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Next, <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> he comes, and he calls the ſoul by a new Greek name <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>id eſt, actus,</hi> which is as much as to ſay, a perpetual motion, and ſaith that it proceedeth from a fifth nature and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, which he calleth Heaven; yet he delivereth not himſelf ſo plainly, that a man might judge his opinion, what he thinketh of the reaſonable ſoul in man, whether it be mortal or immortal; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe hee confeſſeth that there is a great difference betweene that power of the ſoule which we call more ſpecially by the name of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and between the other twain, which he calleth the nutritive and ſenſitive powers: for he uſeth this word pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and affirmeth that theſe two firſt proceed onely from the body, and are bred there; and that the vegetative ſoul and power is more in the ſeed and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, then the ſenſitive. But as for the third, he ſaith plainly, that it only com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170252:15"/>from without elſewhere, and that onely this is divine. And thus for <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle.</hi> For the reſt of the Ancient Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, in brief, <hi>Pythagoras</hi> called the Soule <hi>Harmoniam.</hi> Hippocrates, <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum tenuem per corpus omne diſperſum.</hi> Poſſidonius, <hi>Ideam.</hi> Aſclepiades, <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſenſuum exercitium ſibi conſonum.</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raclitus Ponticus, <hi>Lucem.</hi> Heraclitus Phyſicus, <hi>Scintillam ſtellaris eſſentiae.</hi> Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, <hi>Concretum corpori ſpiritum.</hi> Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critus, <hi>Spiritum inſertum atomis.</hi> Crito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus <hi>Peripateticus, conſtare eam ex quinta eſſentia dixit.</hi> Hypparchus, <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</hi> Anaximenes, <hi>Aerem.</hi> Empedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, <hi>Sanguinem;</hi> with whom agrees <hi>Critias.</hi> Parmenides, <hi>Ex terra &amp; igne conflatum quid.</hi> Xenophontes, <hi>Ex igne, aere, &amp; ſpiritu miſtam ſpeciem.</hi> Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus accorded with <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> calling it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: of which ſee more <hi>in Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophiae naturalis Epitom. ex univerſis Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Ariſtot. decerptum, Simone Broſerio Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thore, Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>de anima.</hi> The ſame <hi>Broſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerius</hi> in the beginning of the ſame ſaid 7th. Book defines the ſoule thus: <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma eſt principium quo vivimus, ſentimus at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> movemur.</hi> This definition doth appeare to be taken from her proper paſſions of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170252:16"/>living, perceiving, and moving. But there is another definition more eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, taken from the ſubſtance of the thing, that is, as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> alſo hath it; <hi>Animus eſt primus actus perfectio<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> corporis potentia vitam habentis.</hi> Where by the word <hi>actum, intelligit ſubſtantiam eſſe:</hi> Alſo whereas he ſayes, <hi>Corporis potentiae vitam habentis, intelligit omnia corporis munia ita dependere à forma, ut niſi per eam nihil facere poſſit.</hi> Thus you ſee the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and definitions of the Wiſe and Ancient Philoſophers, who by the light of nature only, aſcribed great faculties and power to the ſoule, thinking high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thereof, though plainly they could not conclude any certainty, nor truly ſearch into the depth thereof, not any mentioning the immortality thereof: Let us therefore ſee whether we can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a true and real definition thereof according to our promiſe in the Title of this Concluſion: Then take it thus. The ſoule of man is a ſpiritual, inviſible, and immortal ſubſtance, endued with power to underſtand and will; but the power thereof it not of and from it ſelf; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it muſt needs proceed from another cauſe, which is from power, wiſedome,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170252:16"/>and underſtanding it ſelfe, and that is God. Yea, it <hi>tota in toto corpore, &amp; tota in ſingulis partibus:</hi> And as the before cited <hi>Broſserius</hi> hath it; <hi>Eſt<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> anima ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis eadem &amp; vegetativa, ab officio vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandi, &amp; ſenſitiva ab officio ſentiendi, &amp; rationabilis ab officio rationandi.</hi> And thus far for the ſoule of Man. Now let us proceed and clear the other part of this third Concluſion, and ſhew what the Soule of beaſts and other living crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures is: And this point the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers agree very well amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſay that it is of the ſame mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that their bodies are compounded of. Whether it be derived and taken from the ſame, or whether it be the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety of the matter; and therefore they underſtand it to be the vital ſpirit only therein that giveth life unto them, which is of a corporal matter and ſubſtance; or elſe they conceive it to be the tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or temperament of the whole body generally, which is the propriety of the matter; And ſo the ſoule in beaſts ſhall be the life it ſelf, of which the vital ſpirits, or the temperament, are the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments thereof: which ſeemeth to accord with <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaying, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.4. and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170252:17"/>
                  <hi>Lev.</hi> 17.14. That the ſoule of the fleſh is in the blood thereof <hi>(id eſt)</hi> the life. And although we ſee not with the eye how theſe vital ſpirits, or the tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all the parts of the body doe give unto it that life which it hath, yet we may judge, and have ſome know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thereof by things we ſee in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which have ſome agreement and reſemblance therewith: For we may well conceive how the flame of a Lamp is nouriſhed by the oyl and wick: where we ſee two ſorts of matter different one from another joyned both together. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, we may perceive how that by the means of this conjunction, &amp; of the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature and agreement that theſe two things have each with other, the flame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once kindled in them, is nouriſhed &amp; preſerved by them. So likewiſe we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the vital ſpirit in the bodies of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving creatures, as a thin flame engendred of the blood, by vertue of the heart, which diſtributeth it ſelf throughout all the parts of the body, giving unto it vital heat, which quickeneth it, and endueth it with that virtue by which it hath motion &amp; ſenſe, and exerciſeth all its actions ſo that every member doth its office: Now
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170252:17"/>we ſee well in this compariſon the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that is in the Lamp, and the tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and agreement that is between the parts of it, and how the flame is fed and maintained after it is lighted; we may underſtand alſo from whence this flame is brought to the lamp, &amp; how this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is lighted, and that neither the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, nor the agreement and temperature bred this flame of themſelves, but that it is brought from elſewhere. In the ſame manner we may conceive of that which hath been ſpoken of the vital ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and of the blood whereof it is bred, and of the vertue and power of the heart in the generation of it. But here it may be ſaid, that there is a great difference between the compariſon of a Lamp and his flame, and between that which we have ſpoken of the generation of the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſpirit, becauſe this flame, which we call the vital ſpirit, ſpringeth of the ſelf ſame matter by which it is nouriſhed and preſerved, and is kindled there. And therefore it is requiſite that we ſhould further know what is the cauſe of this, as alſo why the life and moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that are therein, are enflamed by this vital ſpirit, and not by any other means
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170252:18"/>whatſoever, whether it be the blood, or the fleſh: And yet this ſpirit is as well of a corporal and bodily matter, as all the reſt of which the body is compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; ſo that it hath his original of the ſelf-ſame Elements from whence that matter is derived, out of which it ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth. But of ſuch Inquiſitors I may likewiſe demand from whence the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, the Sun, Moon, and Stars, have their motion, light, and properties? It is certain, they can yield me no other true cauſe, but that God hath created them of that nature, and that he hath ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted them, and that he alwayes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth them by the divine vertue and power of his providence. And this ſhall ſuffice for the nature &amp; matter of the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive &amp; ſenſual ſoul, which we attribute to beaſts. Now for the laſt part of this Concluſion, of the powers and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that the ſoul of man hath common with the ſoule of beaſts and plants, it hath been, in ſhort, but ſignificant words, declared above, where it was ſaid out of <hi>Broſſerius, Eadem eſt anima hominis &amp; vegetativa ab officio vegetandi, &amp; ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiva ab officio ſentiendi, &amp;c.</hi> So that here it is plaine that it hath the vegeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170252:18"/>quality, which is common with Plants <hi>ab officio vegetandi:</hi> and alſo its ſenſitive power and quality <hi>ab officio ſentiendi:</hi> And hereupon they that ſay every living creature hath but one ſoul, ſay well; but there are divers powers thereof in certaine creatures, in ſome more, in ſome leſſe; therefore we call that of Plants by a more ſpecial name (Vegetative) becauſe it hath no more but this bare office and vertue of vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, from whence proceeds the name. And albeit the ſoule of beaſts hath the ſame vertue alſo, yet we call it not by the ſame name, but only ſenſitive, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which we comprehend alſo the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getative ſoul that is in Plants, as a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and property thereof: So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, although the ſoul of man hath both theſe faculties together, yet we call it not either vegetative or ſenſitive, but onely reaſonable, and that, as afore is ſaid, <hi>ab officio ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandi;</hi> under which we alſo doe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the vegetative ſoule in Plants, and the ſenſitive ſoul of Beaſts, which is ſufficient for clearing this Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And this vegetative and ſenſitive power and properties will peculiarly
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170252:19"/>ſit and ſerve our occaſions in the enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcourſe, and the manifeſtation of the whole Art we treat of.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. CONCLUS. IV. <hi>Every compound conſiſting of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and forme, hath in it its own proper natural heat, which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived and propagated (not from the Elements, but) from Heaven and the influence thereof.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FRom this Concluſion, it is apparent that nothing can ſubſiſt without ſome manner of heat; for heat is the bond whereby the forme is tyed to the matter, which lying hid in a viſcous Mercurial moiſture brought with it from Heaven, giveth increaſe and ſeeds to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry body: It is alſo the inſtrument which the forme doth uſe to produce actions, and it is the immediate cauſe of the aforeſaid beams, ſpoken of in Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170252:19"/>the ſecond; which beams it never forſaketh, but accompanieth in their motions perpetually. Now this ſaid heat, if it decreaſe, the body tends to deſtruction, the beams being fewer and weaker; and though the forme be not united to the matter, but by a certaine manner of heat, which is ſo required, as proper to all things, that it yet varies in every ſpecies of things, yet it hath in every ſpecies ſome latitude; ſo that you ſhall ſcarce finde amongſt the individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als that which is altogether one and the ſame thing, becauſe the heat is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more, and ſometimes leſſe, which may be the cauſe of the variety of ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, not onely of things of the ſame ſpecies, but even in the ſame individual it is often changed, till at laſt by corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption it ends in that which is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther another latitude; for the matter being not ſufficiently tenacious, holds not this heat faſt enough, but lets it (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing volatil) wander abroad, which, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the impreſſions of Heaven, applyes it ſelfe variouſly to the matter, whence depends the whole variety and change of ſublunary things. But now it is time to come to the body of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170252:20"/>Man, the proper ſubject of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and enſuing Art.</p>
               <p>And in the firſt place, it ſhall not be amiſſe to explain our ſelves, what we here mean by heat; to which end, let us conſider, the concordance and mutual relation which the heart of man hath with the Heavens: For as the <hi>Primum mobile,</hi> or firſt motion of the whole world beginneth by the Heavens, of which all the other motions that are in nature doe depend; ſo the heart is that member in the body of man which firſt receiveth life and motion, and which is the well-ſpring and fountain thereof; whereupon it is ſaid to be <hi>Primum vivens &amp; ultimum moriens,</hi> and is continually in motion, without any intermiſſion of ceaſing: And therefore ſome Authors are of opinion, that the <hi>Pericardium,</hi> which is called the little cloſet of the heart, is of ſuch a capacity, that it is ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the ſame on every ſide as much as is requiſite, that its motion might not any wiſe be impeded. And ſome think that there is ſome water within this veſſel, or ſome moiſture like a dew, to the intent it ſhould water the heart, that it ſhould not conſume or dry it ſelf
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170252:20"/>up by its perpetual moving. Now the heart is the root and fountain of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral heat, diſperſing abroad by the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries over the whole body, and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtreth the life to every part thereof: For although the inſtrumenes of reſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſerve the voice, yet they were principally created for the hearts ſake, that the natural heat which is in it might be refreſhed, increaſed and fed by them; and for this cauſe the Divine Providence hath made the lungs to be as it were the ſhop of reſpiration, to the end that the aire without be ſent even to the heart, for the reaſons aforeſaid; for the aire that is to be brought to the heart, is firſt prepared in the lungs, to the end it might moderate the heat of the heart and ſpirits, and that it ſhould not enter in either too hot, or too cold, or in too great abundance, whereby it might be damnified, or quite choaked up.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and his followers, make heat the cauſe of the hearts pulſifick motion; others will have the ſoul, and others the vegetative faculty; but I encline to <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> opinion; for the ſoul works by its faculties, and theſe by heat; ſo that heat is the immediate cauſe of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170252:21"/>this motion, and the ſoules inſtrument, yet not ſuch an inſtrument as worketh nothing, but by the force of the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Agent; for the heat worketh by its own natural force, though it be direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and regulated by the ſoule; the heat then of the heart rarifying the blood in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vapours, which require more room, dilates the heart; but by diſpelling ſome of theſe vapours into the Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and receiving alſo ſome cold aire by the lungs, the heart is contracted, and this is called <hi>Syſtole,</hi> the other <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtole.</hi> And as heat is the efficient cauſe, ſo alſo it is the end of this motion; and therefore doth heat move the heart, that it by this motion might impart heat to the body: But I underſtand not heat here for a bare quality, but that which is called <hi>calidum innatum;</hi> the heart being, as appeares, the fountain of heat, whoſe action is the firſt, and the moſt common of all the actions in the body; for without the action of heat there can be no nutrition, motion, ſenſation, nor underſtanding, as it works by the fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſie.</p>
               <p>And becauſe in this Treatiſe we have, and often ſhall have occaſion to ſpeak of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170252:21"/>the vital ſpirit, we will now declare what we mean in this Art thereby: And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther after the manner of the <hi>Galeniſts</hi> and Phyſitians, we mean that which the Schools call by that name, or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing of another nature: Truly, we ſuppoſe not the common and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved opinion of ſpirits, animal, vital, and natural, to be diſconſonant to truth; yet being not ſo material for our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, we meddle not with them; and therefore here we ſpeak of another man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſpirit. Here ſome may object, and ask, what new ſpirit then is this brought into Phyſick, or by what Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority was it introduced? Surely for anſwer, I am not ſo ſupercillious, as to affirm it done by my Authority, I am indifferent, let it not be brought in at all, I onely deſire that I may be ſpared the uſe of that name, whereby to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe natural heat and radical moiſture both together; and my reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are never actually ſeparated: And ſo I call them ſpirits, becauſe of all corporal things, they come neereſt the nature of a ſpirit, both in original and power: And I call it alſo vital, becauſe by mediation of it, life flowes, and is
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170252:22"/>propagated into the body; and therefore here I thought it convenient to declare, that whereſoever in this Treatiſe you finde the name of vital ſpirit, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it there as it is before nominated. Now this aforeſaid ſpirit flouriſheth in the aforementioned beames; and this ſpirit alſo floweth from the body, and this cannot be denied by any wiſe man; for if it flowed not from the body, then the body would laſt for ever; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the things that have moſt pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to fix this ſpirit, have moſt power to prolong the life of man; for it is vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, and every moment ſome part and portion of it goeth forth; and certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is moſt likely, that it goeth out with the parts of the body reſolved into beames; for to what end ſhould it leave the beams going out, and inſinuate it ſelf into bodies indiſpoſed? there can be no reaſon given, nay it ſeemes utterly impoſſible: And that the beames have a diſpoſition to hold it; for that it goeth out with them, it is plain, becauſe the beams, as is aforeſaid, retain the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the body from whence they goe out; and by this reaſon I take it, that dogs, and other creatures of prey, in their
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170252:22"/>hunting, when they have loſt the ſcent of the footing on the ground, peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by other creatures, in treading in, or croſſing the ſame footſteps, doe then hold up their noſes in the air, ſearching after theſe beames, to recover the loſt ſcent, theſe beames flowing and reflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to and from the wight, as Atomes in the Sun; nay, if this ſpirit were not there, the beams could not do as they do, nor work in the power of the ſoule; for of it this ſpirit is an inſtrument: And either therefore the body of men ſhall work at no diſtance at all, or to that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, whatſoever it be, this ſpirit muſt needs reach and proceed, and by vertue of a more potent ſoul, in the very begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and <hi>principium</hi> of life, the body of man (as of all wights) is ordained to natural actions, as other natural bodies are, by the ſeminary vertues which are in the forms. This ſpirit then accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies the beames, diſperſeth their actions which are propagated; and when they grow faint, as rivers from their heads, they are ſupplyed by and from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. And this ſhall be ſufficient for to terminate this Fourth Concluſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:170252:23"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. CONCLUS. V. <hi>That the Excrements of the bodies of living creatures retain a portion of the vital ſpirit; and therefore we cannot deny them life, and this life is of the ſame ſpecies that the life of the creature is of, and propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated from the ſame ſoule.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Concluſion will manifeſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, if we conſider that theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements, having lurked long in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, they imbibe this ſpirit, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn it to themſelves, intercepting the beames iſſuing from the nobleſt parts of the body, yea, having gotten at the leaſt ſome digeſtion, they are made liker the bodies in which they were concocted, and therefore doe greedily attract the beames with the ſpirits, and the ſpirits do more willingly inſinuate themſelves
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170252:23"/>into them, then into any body not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of the ſame. And this may be convinced by common experience; for you may eaſily perceive, that the too much flowing of any excrement, brings and begets grievous Symptomes, weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and in the end death it ſelfe, and that not ſo much by expelling the nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment, as by exhauſting the ſpirits; otherwiſe in them that have the Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, how could the too much flowing of water out at the Orifice of the part in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected cauſe death, but that the water being impregnated with theſe ſpirits, carries more of them with it then the body can bear in ſo ſhort time? and ſo in all inward abſceſſes, when great ſtore of purulent matter hath filled the breaſt, if by the negligence or ignorance of the Chyrurgeon the matter flow all at once, it is, for the ſame reaſon, followed with death, or dangerous debilities and ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptomes; for unleſſe the body be every where (according to the proportion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite) ſtored with theſe ſpirits, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not long ſubſiſt: And this ſpirit, as long as the body conſiſts in his due ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry, is nouriſhed from heaven by the mediation of the ayre, and by the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170252:24"/>ſpirit of the aliment; therefore all things that proceed from the bodies of men men or beaſts, after what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſoever, whether naturally, or by force of diſeaſes are impregnated with the ſame vital ſpirit that the body hath; and therefore becauſe they are liker the bodies whence they came, then thoſe things that never were in the body, they quickly imprint the qualities drawn from the body, upon another like body; which ought to occaſion great care, that neither excrements, matter, corruption, or any of thoſe things which came from infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted perſons, be left unburied, for the great miſchief that may come by them, either naturally, or by Art, if they ſhould happen to come into the hands of skilful, but indiſpoſed perſons: And hereupon a wiſe man will be cautious of converſing and comming too neer ſick and infected perſons; the rather, if he feel himſelfe diſpoſed to the like diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe; for a body ſo diſpoſed, doth more vehemently attract to himſelfe thoſe beams, and is ſooner changed; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo bodies between whom there is a ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude in complexion, and an affinity in nature, doe ſooner ſympathize one
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170252:24"/>with another, as Brothers, Siſters, and Couſins, doe ſooner take diſeaſes one from another, becauſe of their radical likeneſſe inherent in their bodies, by which likeneſſe the infected beames are drawn, and the body more ſpeedily changed: And though the burning of dead carkaſſes, after the ancient accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed manner, be not now in uſe, or permitted; yet great care ought to be had and taken, that all dead carkaſſes be ſpeedily and very deep buried, and that, if conveniently, in moiſt places, and farre remote from the feeding of cattell; for, from ſhallow and ſuperfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial graves, ariſeth often unſpeakable miſchiefes: And, I ſuppoſe, this hath been one of the greateſt naturalleſt cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes why the Plague hath ſo furiouſly ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in <hi>London,</hi> and many great Cities in times paſt: For I fear, they to whom the care and charge of burial was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, were then, as they are ſtill, too negligent and careleſſe. Truly the fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral fires of the Ancients (in this regard) was much to be commended; but ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cuſtome having now prevailed, it were but little to our purpoſe any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to make mention thereof: onely I
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170252:25"/>conceive it fit to advertiſe Magiſtrates of populous places to be very careful in a matter of ſo great concernment. It is alſo more obſervable, that Witches, and thoſe that deale with diabolical Arts, cannot prejudice any thing at all, without the parts of dead bodies, and the excrements of him whom they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to miſchief: Of which, read <hi>Wyerus de preſtigiis Daemonum,</hi> and <hi>Cardamus de ſubtilitate.</hi> And as the Magiſtrate ought to take good care of burials; ſo every man, eſpecially if he have enemies, I would adviſe to have a great care of his excrement. But to returne to our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, which affirmeth theſe excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to live alſo: which at firſt ſight appears a little harſh, yet to him that well contemplates the matter, it is ſo far from being unreaſonable, that it is impoſſible it ſhould be otherwiſe: Nay, what if it be ſaid that the haire and nailes doe live a certain life propagated from the ſoule? It may be anſwered, that is, becauſe they are as certain parts of the body; but if I ſay, when they are ſeparated from the body, they live with the ſame ſoule they did before, this would be thought more ſtrange: Well,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170252:25"/>this I will onely ſay of the life of the Excrements, that unleſſe they lived with the ſame life that the wights doe in a certain manner, certainly they would want the vital ſpirit, of which, we have ſpoken of before. Moreover, who can deny that the nailes and haire have life, that hath obſerved in them the augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative or aſſimulative faculty? at leaſt who can deny it unto them, ſo long as they remain faſtened unto the body, though they want ſenſe, as the bones, and ſome other parts of the organical body doth? Now if they live while they are joyned to the body, though ſenſe be wanting; they ſhall live like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, being ſeparated from the body, as long as they are hairs and nails, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame forme they had before, and until they be converted into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpecies; witneſſe the accidents, or ſubſtantial moods, which abiding ſtill the ſame, depend upon the ſame foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine from whence they flowed; and no man can deny, but that the very forme or figure flowed from the ſoule, draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thence its life, which is propagated by the preſence of the ſoule, by mediation of the vital ſpirit: And a
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170252:26"/>man alſo may thus argue for any excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. All excrements in the body, by means of ſome manner of digeſtion, have changed the form they had before that digeſtion, and put on another; as may be known by their operations and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, which are altogether changed, as for example: The excrements of a dog heal the diſeaſes appertaining to the palat and throat, which fleſh and bones, his natural food and nouriſhment, in their own ſubſtance before their conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, by what manner of way ſoever you prepare them, cannot doe; nay, though they have been ſtinking and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt; which comes neereſt to the nature and condition of excrements: And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, this curative faculty from whence &amp; by which they effect this healing, they obtained no where elſe but from the ſoule of the dog; and therefore being introduced and brought in by that, it it wholly depends of the ſoul, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently cannot be void of vitality or livelineſſe, which ſeems obſcure and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perceptible to ſuch as are ignorant in the Centers of things; which will be more expedient to a Philoſopher to ſearch after, then to ſuffer himſelfe to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170252:26"/>be tranſported with the ſpirit of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, which is nothing profitable to any ingenious Art. And thus we will paſs our fifth Concluſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. CONCLUS. VI. <hi>Between the body and the ſpirits there is a certain concatenation of ſpirits or beams, though they be never ſo far at diſtance: The like is alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the blood and other parts of the body, though ſeparated from the body at any diſtance.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF we conſirm and demonſtrate this Concluſion, the greateſt difficulty in this Art is cleared: For herein lies the very quinteſſence of all our Secrets; the which being eſtabliſhed, there is laid a foundation whereupon all the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of this Art are built: And indeed, if what already hath been propounded, abide ſure and unſhaken, the enſuing
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170252:27"/>difficulty will not much trouble us.</p>
               <p>But here it may be enquired of us what concatenation here we intend?</p>
               <p>For anſwer, when we affirme a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catenation of ſpirits or beames between the body and the excrements there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, we underſtand thereby a perpetual flux of beames, proceeding after a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar manner from the body, and termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated as in a body, after a ſort of kin and like unto it; as alſo very procally flowing from the excrements to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: That there are ſuch reciprocal E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manations, is eaſily ſhewed; for the flux of beames being granted, and the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnation of excrements by the vital ſpirit, for the reaſons before mentioned, it muſt neceſſarily follow that both the beames, that is, both of the body and the excrements, are as not differing in nature and quality; ſo terminated upon one another, by the aforeſaid meanes, rather then by any other: yea, if the forme both of the body and excrements depend upon the ſame ſoule, as afore is proved, it will not be abſurd to call the excrements (until they have utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loſt the forme they have got in the body) either a part of that body, or
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170252:27"/>ſomething ſubordinate to the body; and therefore the vital ſpirit being affected in the excrements, is alſo affected in the body, which cannot be performed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch a concatenation. But here this general note is to be obſerved, namely, that the excrements of any part are pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly allyed, and tyed to that part whoſe excrements they are; and that the beames that flow interchangeably from theſe, doe by a peculiar love em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace thoſe that flow from the excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the part whoſe it is <hi>&amp; via ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa;</hi> for out of that part it hath drawn more plenteous ſpirits, and therefore hath greater affinity with it, which may be proved by experience: for if thou put exulcerating materials prepared ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificially into the ordure of the prodex, it will be affected with extreme paine: It is not therefore to be doubted, but that the excrements are by reciprocal beams concatenated with the body, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially with thoſe parts out of which they laſt proceeded: And upon this concate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation depends all magnetical Phyſick, which being well conſidered, there will be no great obſcurity in the practical part; it further concluded, that the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170252:28"/>fartheſt diſtance doth not break this concatenation, which is ſo true, as it is that the vertue of the ſoule extends it ſelfe moſt largely, ſo that it is ſcarce contained in the place; for this conca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenation depending upon the ſoul, muſt needs be extended according to the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the ſoul, beſides the other reaſon of this extenſion, where it was ſaid, that there do moſt plentiful ſpirits flow from bodies, becauſe of the great plenty of vital ſpirits which appeare, in regard they need ſo great ſtore of ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to the end, that what was ſpent in propagating beams, may, by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of the diſpenſing ſpirit, be renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the body, the fountain of them: There is therefore no ſmall ſtore of theſe beames, becauſe being thin, ſubtle, and eaſily diſſipated, they need ſuch ſtore of food to the continual reparation of them. They extend themſelves like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe very far, and work diverſly (we not perceiving or knowing of it) and diverſly are we affected in the hurting of them, being full ignorant of the cauſes of our diſeaſes: And therefore in all ſickneſſes, the ſame ſpirit is to be rectifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, comforted, and multiplied; and ſo
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170252:28"/>may all diſeaſes be eaſily cured, which we propound eſpecially for Phyſicians to note and conſider. And now there is no man will deny, but that what we have ſaid of the excrements, doth alſo agree to the parts ſeparated from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as alſo to the blood; for there is the ſame reaſon in all, unleſſe peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the blood it appeares more evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, becauſe it is called in holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture the ſeat of the ſoule or life, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving greateſt ſtore of vital ſpirits, and hurting moſt eaſily by the much flux of it. Amongſt all other things that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm this concatenation, that famous ſympathetical unguent, commonly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Weapon-ſalve,</hi> and alſo the Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathetical water, doth by manifeſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience clearly prove it; in deſpite of the vain and obſtreperous Divines, that proclame it diabolical and ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, whom both many others, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the learned <hi>Helmuntius</hi> hath put to everlaſting ſilence. Nor did the wran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling <hi>Libanius,</hi> though he proudly rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after his manner, write any better a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this, then he did of and for the <hi>Philoſophical Stone;</hi> how ignorantly and audaciouſly he carried himſelfe in both,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170252:29"/>to the infinite prejudice of the Herme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Commonwealth, none know ſo well as they, that have learned the true knowledge of things from the things themſelves; but of this enough.</p>
               <p>Now of the parts of the body ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he that doubteth may read in the ſame <hi>Helmuntius</hi> a ſtrange ſtory; I will give you his words. A certain man of <hi>Bruxels</hi> ſaith he) being at <hi>Bolognia,</hi> did in a fray loſe his noſe; and going to <hi>Tayliacoza,</hi> a Chyrurgeon living there, to conſult how to have a new noſe; and fearing the cutting a piece out of his own arm, he hired a Porter for a good ſumme of money to have one cut out of his arm; which being done, and the cure performed, the man of <hi>Bruxels</hi> returned home: About 13. moneths after, he felt his noſe ſuddenly grow cold, and within a few dayes after, it rotted, and fell quite off: And he, with many others, wondring at the ſtrange chance, enquiring of the cauſe, it was found, that juſt at the ſame inſtant that the noſe grew cold, the Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at <hi>Bolognia</hi> died; the truth whereof, as <hi>Helmont</hi> writes, many at <hi>Bruxels</hi> will teſtifie. Thus far he. The like ſtory I
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170252:29"/>have heard from a Doctor of Phyſick, a friend of mine, who proteſted deeply he was an eye-witneſſe thereof. Is not all our Doctrine here then confirmed clear as the light? was not that infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious noſe as animated at firſt, ſo ſtill informed with the ſoule of the Porter? neither had it any thing from that man whoſe noſe it was now made, but nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment; the power of aſſimilation which it had from its own proper form, it took not from the ſoule of him, but from the ſoule of the Porter, of whom it was yet truly a part, and who dying, the noſe became immediately a dead noſe, and began to tend to corruption. But who doth not ſee here moſt evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our concatenation? Our Aſſertion therefore is concluded true by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted experience; from whence, as from a plenteous Spring, divers faire Rivulets doe flow. Hence aroſe that glorious miracle of Nature, whereby a man may in an inſtant open his mind to his friend, though they be ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand miles diſtant, by meanes of a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle blood, ſpirit, and fleſh, a ſecret no wayes to be divulged to the multitude: Hence aroſe that lamp of life, which at
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170252:30"/>any diſtance ſhewes by its light the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the body; and its volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry going out, the death of the body, whence it was taken: Hence alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded that ſalt of blood, by its colour ſhewing the ſame thing that the lamp did by its light: And hence alſo aroſe all natural philtres by meanes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the affections are moved, and after a certain manner tyed, meerly and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly natural. But of this enough.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. CONCLUS. VII. <hi>This vitality, or livelineſs, laſts until the Excrements, Blood, or ſeparated parts be changed into another thing of a divers ſpecies.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALl things which have their origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal from the Elements, after they are come to their perfection, do ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way goe back again to the principles from whence they took their beginning;
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170252:30"/>for it is eſtabliſhed by the Providence, that what is begun by motion, ſhall never be partaker of ſtate or reſt: Yet doth not the thing immediately ceaſe to be in that ſpecies wherein it is, until another forme be introduced into the matter, which alſo brings with it new moods, and new operations. I ſpeak not here of ſubordinate forms, which are known to be common to any ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es; the change whereof is not alwayes required in natural changes or corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Of the abſence, or preſence of formes, we can no way judge, but by the moods and faculties of the ſubject; we ſay therefore, that vitality doth ſo long laſt in the excrements, blood, and ſeparated parts, as they are not chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into other things of a divers ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; which being clear of it ſelfe, and by that which is aboveſaid, needs no proof: yet this is to be noted, Firſt, that things have more vertue and energy in their ſtate, then in their declination; and the neerer they are to their abſolute change, the leſſe they work. Secondly, that every change of the ſubſtance doth not change the formes in things, where onely the ſuperfluities are taken away,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170252:31"/>leaving the eſſences (that I may ſo ſay) which lurk in a ſufficient matter, well diſpoſed and digeſted, and are full of the vital ſpirits of things; there the form is not only changed, but alſo more free then it was, and worketh more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</p>
               <p>Moreover, we ſee that ſome corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is neceſſary to the furtherance of ſome operations; though this kind of corruption, if we will give it the true name, is rather to be called fermentation, for that by it the ſpirits are ſtirred up, and made more able to ſhew their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: But <hi>[eſt modus in rebus ſunt certi de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nique fines, Quos ultra citra<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> nequit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtere virtus.]</hi> There is a mean in things, and certain bounds, beyond which truth cannot conſiſt; therefore we muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed very warily, while we labour to ſtir up the ſpirits; for while we digeſt them, and labour to make them more ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, we may utterly put the ſpirit to flight, which I have ſeen often happen in this Art, and in Alchymy. And then men, when they have erred through their own ignorance, they blame and calumniate the Art, making the ſaying true, <hi>Ars non habet inimicum niſi ignorantem.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:170252:31"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. CONCLUS. VIII. <hi>One part of the body being affected, or ill-diſpoſed by hurting the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, all the other parts doe ſuffer with it.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Conceive this is a common and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived opinion, by all Phyſitians al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed and confeſſed to be true; and therefore needs little proof: ſo that we ſhall onely ſay thus much of it, That the cauſe of this compaſſion flowes nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the body, nor from the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular form of the part, nor from the likeneſſe (unleſſe likeneſſe be ſo far forth conſidered which flowes from the ſame or the like proportion of the ſpirit) but from the vital ſpirit, which goeth through the whole body, and is reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in every part thereof: For a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe terminatively is not of the body, but of the ſpirit; for there is no diſeaſe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170252:32"/>of the body, howſoever it comes, which happens not by the weaknes of this ſpirit; neither can any diſtemper of the body laſt long where this ſpirit (by which all evils of the body are amended) flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth &amp; is ſtrong. This ſpirit is that nature whereof Phyſitians ought to be helpers, and upon which ground the Univerſal Medicine is built: And unhappy are thoſe Phyſicians, and unhappily ſpeed, who either neglecting or wronging this ſpirit, deſtroy all things by their vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, while they think to cure diſeaſes, and which by opening a veine exhauſt this ſpirit, and by purging the body from hurtful humours by rank poyſons (which kill this ſpirit) thruſt with thoſe humours the ſoule many times out of the body. And there are they, that by their villany and ignorance, have dim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the glory of Phyſick, which being given over to vain, contentious and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable diſputes, have erred from the ſimplicity of nature; which though they be honoured of the giddy-headed multitude, becauſe of their rich cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and popular applauſe; yet by the ſons of Art (which by great labour, with prying into the Centers of things,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170252:32"/>have found that nothing is to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted againſt natures will) they are eſteemed no better then as the excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Phyſick, and ſo to be caſt into the vault of perpetual infamy; but <hi>ſtul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum plena ſunt omnia.</hi> But we turning to our purpoſe, ſay, that not only the other parts ſuffer with the parts diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; but that if any diſeaſe, of what part ſoever, doe laſt long, the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy will be at length affected; elſe how could death follow upon a particular diſeaſe? The vital ſpirit is but one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuate through the whole body, and propagated through every part of it, that if it be hurt in one part thereof, it is hurt in the whole, as it followes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:170252:33"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX. CONCLUS. IX. <hi>If the vital ſpirit be fortified in any one part, it is fortified by that very action in the whole body.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat which in the foregoing Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we ſaid of diſeaſes, we ſay here of Cures; for there is the like reaſon of both; and this Concluſion put for no other purpoſe, then to ſhew <hi>caeteris pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus,</hi> that there is no odds whether thou apply the medicine to the part af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, or to another, provided by thy medicaments thy intent be to fortifie the vital ſpirit: For if this ſpirit be fortified in any one part, the whole is fortified; becauſe being of a fiery and heavenlye natur, that ſtrengthening is quickly found in the whole latitude thereof; for it is impoſſible that ſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, active, ſpiritual, clear, and aethereal a thing, ſhould ſuffer any thing in any
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170252:33"/>part, which it ſhall not very ſpeedily ſuffer in the whole: The experiment whereof we ſee in outward poyſons, which infecting the neereſt ſpirits, ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, unleſſe the ſpirit be fortified, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteth the whole ſpirit in the body; for it is impoſſible, that by the ſting of a Scorpion in the foot, the ſubſtance of the venome ſhould (as ſome dream) come to the heart; but becauſe one part of the ſpirit being powerfully infected, the infection of the whole muſt needs ſpeedily follow: So by the inflammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any part, immediately followes a Feaver, though the part inflamed be never ſo far from the heart. And as of Diſeaſes, ſo we may conclude of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies: But that remedies applyed to the part affected, doe more good, and more ſpeedily help, it is long of frequent egreſſion of ſpirits in that part, the cauſe whereof look for in the following Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion. It is very neceſſary therefore that thou chooſe a part fit for thy purpoſe; for except thou do ſo, thou wilt be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved &amp; aſhamed; for thou ſhalt not work everywhere alike: And therefore pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der well the following Concluſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:170252:34"/>
               <head>CHAP. X. CONCLUS. X. <hi>Where the Spirit is more bare or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, there it is ſooneſt affected.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Concluſion being moſt neceſſary for Practice, is of it ſelfe mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, and followeth upon the Premiſſes; for doubtleſſe the more intimately any Agent is joyned with the Patient, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration is more ſpeedy and better; for what can hinder action, but undue ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proximation? which impediment we here muſt ſtudy to avoid, ſeeking the vital ſpirit in his nakedneſſe, that it may be the ſooner affected by a due and convenient application, and may the more ſpeedily be freed from things hurtful and extraneous, and ſo quickly change and rectifie the whole body ſlipt into diſtemper: For, if where it is moſt naked, it be then freed from extraneous things, becauſe it is not ſo fettered and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170252:34"/>clogged with evils, then certainly there (if one know the right ſubject) and uſe the right inſtruments, may it be made ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to free the whole body from diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers: For, being fortified in one place, it will ſtraitway be fortified through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out: For, as a diſeaſe is never truly, but when the whole ſpirit is affected with a ſickly diſpoſition (for till then it is but ſome ſpark in <hi>fier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> in the making or breeding) which diſpoſition, at the beginning, affected but one part, and that affection not hindered, corrupted the whole; ſo muſt we alſo Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phize concerning the recovery of health. But here are two things requiſite; Firſt, that thou ceaſe not the application, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the diſeaſe be fully cured: For, if thou leave off before that time, the part that is yet infected (if the infection be ſtrong) will again infect and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the parts thou hadſt made whole, and ſo leave thee to begin the ſame la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. Secondly, that one part anſwer another; for he that will happily cure diſeaſes, muſt begin at the root: And if the root of the diſeaſe be in the head, then cure the vital ſpirit proper to the head; if in the ſtomach, to the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170252:35"/>&amp;c. For although the vital ſpirit confidered in it ſelf, have no heterogeneal parts, but be every<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, and whole, like the light, like it ſelf; yet as it is in the body, it is varied according to the parts of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy by certain adjuncts which are very conſiderable: And therefore the rayes or beames proceeding from the head, do in that diſpoſition contain the ſpirit, as the head doth, as by the things already ſaid may be gathered: The naked ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit therefore, affected with the diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the head (if the root of this diſeaſe be in the head) is to be taken, and remedies applyed to that. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we proceed to other things, it will not be amiſſe to confirm the truth of this Concluſion by experience. There's no man doubts but that in the blood the ſpirit is moſt naked; therefore the Phyſicians know that the naked ſpirit in blood is ſooner infected with poyſon then the ſpirit of any other part; for venome being put into a vein, doth ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner diſſolve and looſen the whole frame of the body, then twice ſo much taken in meat and drink inwardly; yea, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be taken faſting, and without
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170252:35"/>any <hi>vehiculum,</hi> which confirmes the truth of our Concluſion. I ſhall ſpeak little more hereof, leſt evil ſhould enſue by thoſe who are wickedly and malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly inclined; only give thee this cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that God is the revenger of all ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret and wilfull veneficiators.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI. CONCLUS. XI. <hi>In the Excrements, Blood, &amp;c. the Spirit is not ſo deeply drowned, as in the body; and therefore in them it is ſooner affected.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>UPon this Concluſion the whole Art is grounded; and this being falſe, all fails; therefore remember well what hath been ſaid: For he that well underſtands this Concluſion, will finde no difficulty in the whole Art; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it had need to be confirmed with ſome reaſons; whereof the firſt is this: The ſpirit is not ſo deeply drowned in
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170252:36"/>the excrements, blood, and ſeparated parts, as it is in the body, becauſe in them it ranges abroad, as more at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in that it doth not ſo much intend organical operations; for theſe orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical operations doe violently ſnatch the ſpirit inward, that being congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, it may work more powerfully in <hi>ſeceſsu.</hi> But all organical operation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing far from the excrements, blood, &amp;c. there is no need that the ſpirit ſhould drown it ſelfe ſo far, and ſo inwardly: Moreover the beames comming from the body in excrements, blood out of the veines and parts ſeparated, ſtick about the ſuperficies, ſurface, and outſide, and are not allured and drawn internally, becauſe that, as tending to deſtruction, the ſpirits addreſſe themſelves, and make ſome ſtay in the ſuperficies, where alſo the beams joyn themſelves to their fellow-beams, and there reſt, until at laſt the excrements, blood, &amp;c. becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming clean another thing, are apt, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to receive thoſe beams and the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that accompanies them, or to retain them when they have received them: Again, the ſpirits are more naked in theſe, eſpecially in the blood, becauſe
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170252:36"/>when it was in the body, it had the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits more naked, and ſcarce tyed to the body, as appeares evidently in blood. But ſome may ask how this reaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees to parts cut off? for what privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge have they above other parts of the ſame kind? I anſwer: It is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered that now the door is opened, by which a more free egreſſe is granted to the ſpirits, which now having bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken their fetters, begin to wander abroad more at liberty: Again, ſome may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, that if this were true, then by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying things to a wound, we may cure internal diſeaſes? To ſatisfie this, we muſt conſider three things: Firſt, that in every wound there is not only <hi>ſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio continui,</hi> but alſo in the part woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded is an exotick and ſtrange quality introduced, by meanes whereof the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſpirit is hurt. Secondly, thoſe things that are applyed to the wound, have no power to change the vital ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, labouring of another evil diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; yea, the Phyſicians expectation is ſatisfied, if one thing doe performe one defired operation, and therefore they are content with the cure of the wound. Thirdly, if a thing good for another
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170252:37"/>diſeaſe, whereof the Patient peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is ſick, ſhould be applyed to the wound, it might perhaps hurt this more then it would help that; now reaſon perſwades that we ſhould firſt ſuccour that which more urgeth. From theſe things the anſwer to the objection is manifeſt; for the ſpirit then labouring of a double diſtemper, Art commands firſt to cure that which moſt urgeth; therefore we principally attend the wound, leſt Sideration ſhould follow, or ſomewhat elſe bringing aſſured de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; and for the ſame reaſon we apply not unto it things good for the other diſeaſe; yet I will adde this, that it is manifeſt by experience, that many men by wounds have been freed from great diſeaſes, and ſo that they never relapſed; namely, when the part affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted being wounded, the things proper for the diſeaſe could alſo performe the cure of the wound: As if the head la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring of a Chronical diſeaſe, ſhould be wounded, and the wound could be cured by <hi>Betony</hi> and <hi>Sage,</hi> there is no doubt but the ſpirit now naked, being cheriſhed and refreſhed with theſe reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, would perfectly heal both the head
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170252:37"/>and the whole body. Here alſo is to be noted, that they who dig the body with Cauteries, and keep the wound o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen a long time for the purulent matter to run, are ill adviſed that they do not apply unto the wound remedies proper for that diſeaſe for which they made the iſſues; for this being done, the Patients would without doubt in ſhort time feele great eaſe, if the wound were made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the part principally affected; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if all the other things were accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly done diaſtatically, and the matter that iſſues out were alſo uſed as Art commandeth. By this meanes it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and found by experience, that the Gout in the hands, and feet, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts, may moſt happily and eaſily be cured. But returning again to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements &amp; blood, &amp;c. we ſay that this art uſeth theſe rather, and with better ſucceſs then the whole body that is hurt; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the vital ſpirit being free and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, eaſily receiveth and taketh impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, eſpecially from things agreeing with it. Therefore the Inventors of this Art mingled ſuch things, though taken from other bodies with their medicines, (as in the common weapon-ſalve is to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170252:38"/>be ſeen, where they mingle with the ointment the fleſh, blood, and fat of men, for no other cauſe then that being imbrued with theſe medicines and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of medicaments, they may the more eaſily help the hurt ſpirits: [This fleſh, blood, and fat, is comprehended in the word <hi>Mummy</hi>] for by their likeneſſe they doe eaſily draw the ſpirit;
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ccording <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Crollius.</hi>
                  </note> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing drawn, doe change it according to the quality acquired: But it is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes neceſſary that the Medicine be mingled with thoſe things that are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the body; for we ſee that the ſympathetical water alone, and ſimple without any mixtion, will cure all wounds by the meanes of the blood of the wounds. But eſpecial care muſt be taken, that you make choice of thoſe things which do cure, not by qualities, but by their whole ſubſtances (as they uſe to ſpeak) that is, by the ſignatures of their Celeſtial influences, or elſe ordained to ſuch effects by the ſemina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry reaſons of the ſoule; otherwiſe you may eaſily miſſe the mark; for that fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude diſpenſed from their influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, becauſe it paſſeth the like ſpirit, doth much advance the effects; and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170252:38"/>without this, hardly any good is to be expected.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII. CONCLUS. XII. <hi>The mixture of the ſpirits cauſeth love and compaſſion; from that compaſſion love takes its origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Concluſion little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing availes to the curing of diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, being rather directed to induce diſeaſes, and procure love: It is alſo the foundation of all implantations; for where commixtion and compaſſion is, if that which is ſound, draw unto it ſelfe that which hurteth another, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out queſtion that from which the hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful thing was drawn, will be helped and cured with the loſſe and prejudice of that thing that ſo attracteth and draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it. And this Concluſion needs no long proof, neither will I make many
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170252:39"/>words about it, becauſe of the dangers that may probably ariſe from hence; for from this fountain floweth the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plantation of diſeaſes from one man to another, and from the dead to the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving: It may alſo doe harm, it giving cauſe to too much exorbitant luſt, and the means to fulfill it. Now if this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion were fully and publickly known, (which God forbid) fathers could not be ſafe from their daughters, nor any man from any woman, nor woman from any man, nor brothers from ſiſters, nor ſiſters from brothers; for the world would be turned upſide downe with philtre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s; and therefore I will ſay no more in this place; for to them that are curious and diligent ſearchers of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that which hath been, and ſhall be ſaid hereafter, is enough. But before we come to handle the precepts of this Art, let us for an Epilogue to theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions, and for the better underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of what follows, advance one more Propoſition, and that is this: The vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſpirit is more powerfully drawn out of the whole body by thoſe things that have the ſignature of the whole body, or have a ſulphur like the ſulphur of mans
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170252:39"/>body: But from a part for a particular operation, thoſe things doe more vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently draw: And when it is drawne, ſooner communicates the ſpirit to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which hath the evident ſignature of the part. This I ſay, to the end that by thine own induſtry thou mayſt finde Magnets for every particular operation, by meanes of this general rule. This therefore I think good to tell thee; of all things proceeding from the body, the blood and the ſweat are moſt ſtuffed with vital ſpirits: Of the ſeed, I will ſay nothing, becauſe without great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civility it cannot be had: But of one thing take eſpecial heed, that as ſoon as they proceed from their bodies, they be committed to their proper Magnet; for as the common Loadſtone is fortified, and, at it were, fed with iron, ſo are theſe Magnets, which apprehend and keep the vital ſpirits, until they commit the care of them to another thing; for if you will ſtrive to keep them without their proper and due Magnet, two in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences will follow: Firſt, they cannot endure any conſiderable time in their eſtate, becauſe every moment they loſe ſomewhat of the ſpirit. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170252:40"/>without a Magnet they do not work ſo mightily, becauſe for the moſt part the Magnets doe much conduce to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plantation and communication, as we know by perfect experience; for in philtres thou wilt doe little or no good without a Magnet, except perhaps ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what may be done by meanes of fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the blood and ſeed, and then either is to other in ſtead of a Magnet: But in other things, though happily thou mayſt finde a vertue; yet thou wilt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver finde ſo powerful operations, as if in thy work thou uſe Magnets: Chooſe them then convenient, and apply them the right way, and thou ſhalt performe wonders: But of this <hi>ſat ſapienti.</hi> And now of more ſublime things, having put an end to our Concluſions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:170252:40"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>Of the things neceſſary for a Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an before he undertake this part of Magnetick Cures.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere are many things neceſſary for him that intends to undertake upon him the practice of this Art, and to do good by it. Firſt, he muſt know diſeaſes; for how elſe can he cure them? It is true, the ignorance of the diſeaſe is not here ſo dangerous as in common Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, becauſe we here uſe external Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, and alwayes comforting; and there internal, and for the moſt part not void of poyſonous qualities; but though it be not dangerous to the Patient, yet it may be a ſhame to the Phyſitian. He then that is well ſeen in the knowledge of diſeaſes, let him next ſeek the part firſt and principally affected; for if this be unknown, he ſhall never doe any
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170252:41"/>thing to the purpoſe. He muſt alſo have abſolute knowledge of Simples, and know as well the internal as external ſignature of things, whereby th ſimples are ſigned, as well to the parts of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as to the diſeaſes; for we uſe none but ſigned things to this Art: But ſignature being double, to wit, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal and Internal, we will uſe thoſe Simples that are externally ſigned, as being beſt known to us, except Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which is alwayes to be obeyed, be to the contrary. He that knoweth the nature of Simples, cannot be ignorant of the time fit for the ſowing and gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of them: But this Science cannot be thought ſufficient without Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy; our Phyſician muſt therefore be skilled in the Planetary diſeaſes and Plants, that ſo he may oppoſe thoſe with theſe; yet ſo, that to diſeaſes (whether ſtrong or remiſſe) he be ſure to oppoſe a Plant of a ſuperior degree: In a word, he muſt well underſtand the ſecreteſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of men and ſimples. I deny not, but one day this Art may be manifeſted, and very eaſie; but as yet it is in its cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, and lies lurking in the ſecret deske of ſome men; and therefore he that will
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170252:41"/>attempt it, muſt of neceſſity, from the aforeſaid Concluſion draw ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars; yet I would adviſe all men by the way, that in the <hi>interim</hi> they would miniſter inwardly ſuch things as are comforting, proper for the diſeaſe, that ſo the cure may be ſafelier, ſooner, and more pleaſantly done; yea, if perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture ſometime in ſome diſeaſes there muſt more violent things be given (which we muſt ever avoid as much as we can) yet this comfort we have from this Art, that by it nature is ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and kept from being overthrown by violent things; which conſider how much it imports. Moreover, I would perſwade, that until ſafer purgations be found in this Art, thou wouldſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to uſe theſe following, or the like, as the diſeaſe requireth; for theſe doe not much travail the vital ſpirits, and work without nauſeouſneſſe and gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings: Hitherto I have kept them ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:170252:42"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIV. <hi>Of Purgers and Purging.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN as much as the vital ſpirit being fortified, can by its own power free the body from noxious humours, it may be doubted whether in cures done by this Art, Purgation be to be premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: But for the further and ſpeedier diſpatch, we will admit to begin with Purgation; for the oppreſſed ſpirit is relieved, and is made fitter, being hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped by our Medicine, to doe the other things; and when it is free, it is more eaſily changed and reduced into its for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer eſtate; for there are ſome of the Philoſophers, which before they give a <hi>Doſis</hi> of the great <hi>Elixar,</hi> firſt think fit that the cure may be more eaſie to free the body by purgation; how much rather then in this Art? Now whether it be beſt to doe it by the common and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170252:42"/>wayes, or by <hi>Diaſtatick,</hi> it may be doubted: Well, firſt it is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, that there are very few Simples violently purging, that doe not hurt the vital ſpirit by their great proportion of venenoſity. Secondly; there is not yet found any medicine purging magneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally (except ſome ointments common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known) which utterly wants all ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous qualities; and therefore I would have them quite forborne, becauſe they may be cauſe of more miſchief, then if they were given inwardly: But unguents or oyls may be commodiouſly uſed, if the diſeaſe lurk in the ſtomach, inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines, meſeraicks. I will give an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of one that doth gently looſe the belly: Take <hi>Aloes hepatick,</hi> lb. <hi>Myrrhe</hi> ℥ 5. pour halfe a pound of the gall of a Bull upon them, and draw off the oyle in a retort, which thou maiſt uſe <hi>per ſe,</hi> or in forme of an unguent, anointing the ſtomack, and all about the navel therewith; and afterwards, covering it with a ſpunge, wet in the oyle, or oyntment, and thou ſhalt have a benigne and harmleſſe purgation, that works without all nauſcouſneſſe or gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings. There is much ſpeech of an
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170252:43"/>herb in the Weſt-part of <hi>Ireland,</hi> called by the Natives <hi>Mackenbuy;</hi> and from men of credit I have heard it reported, that if any man carry this herb about him, it purgeth him ſtrongly enough, without any gripings: But that it doth not this by way of corroborating the ſpirit, it appeares in that, if one carry it too long about him, it breeds a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous flux. There are that aſcribe the ſame power to <hi>Petum,</hi> or <hi>Tobacco,</hi> if it be tied to the flank: So the milky juyce of <hi>Tythi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male,</hi> mixt with ſalt, and put into the new excrements of the belly, doth vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently looſen, but not without pain; yet theſe things muſt be warily uſed, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it ſafe to apply any medicine that purgeth vehemently, to the vital ſpirit nakedly, either by excrement, blood, or any other means.</p>
               <p>We will therefore preſcribe ſome things to be taken inwardly, which are benigne, and agreeable to nature, till better may be found out. The firſt ſhall be the Specifical Purger of <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> which is good almoſt for every diſeaſe, whether the operation be according to <hi>Crellius, Hartmannus,</hi> or <hi>Tenzelius:</hi> Alſo you may uſe <hi>Mercurius vitae;</hi> if for a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170252:43"/>precipitate the pouder by common water; if by ſiege onely, then precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate it by oyle of <hi>Tartar,</hi> and after pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitation, waſh it well: If afterwards it be ſprinkled with oyle of common ſalt, and ſo left in digeſtion three or four daies, and then once or twice wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, it purgeth gently and univerſally, which is an high ſecret in the Dropſie: Moreover, if common ☿ <hi>vitae</hi> be well ground with common decrepitated ſalt, and again waſhed, and this work be thrice repeated, it leaves much of his violence: Alſo our <hi>Specificum purgans</hi> of our own invention, is of no ſmall moment; for it drawes the humours ſweetly out of the whole body, and opens obſtructions. <hi>Angelus Sala</hi> his <hi>Chryſtallum lunae,</hi> freeth the body benignly from all wateriſh humors, &amp; wonderfully helpeth the Dropſie: Our ☿ <hi>coeleſtis</hi> of all Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals moſt benignly purgeth the belly, it is fit for every one; it opens obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and freeth the head from humours, it ſtrengthens the ſtomack; neither are there any ſymptomes to be feared, as there is in all other ☿ als. The prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is thus: Take of common ☿ pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitated white, dulcified with often
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170252:44"/>waſhing, and dried as much as you will, of oyle of vitriol as much as will make a paſte of it, and put them in a glaſſe, and ſet it in the Sun for 14. daies; then take it out, and dry it, and ſprinkle it with oyle of <hi>Tartar,</hi> as before; then take it and dry it again, doing as before the third time; then waſh it to a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant tartneſſe, dry it and keep it for thy uſe: The <hi>doſis</hi> is from 6. graines to 15. according to the age, diſeaſe, and habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the body. It purgeth onely by ſiege; neither is there fear of ſalivati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though neceſſity force thee to uſe it often.</p>
               <p>The glaſſe of <hi>Antimony,</hi> purging only by ſtoole, is a moſt noble remedy in all melancholy diſeaſes and affects of the head; neither is it far from a ſpeciall Purger, and therefore may be ſafely uſed in every diſeaſe that requireth evacuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: It is made of the pouder of <hi>vitrum Antinoonii,</hi> made by it ſelfe, by irrora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the oile of <hi>Vitriol,</hi> even almoſt as our ☿ <hi>Coeleſtis</hi> was made in this manner.</p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Vitrum Antimonium</hi> ℥ 1. of oyle of <hi>Vitriol</hi> as much, mingle them well in a glaſſe-morter, and dry them by the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170252:44"/>fire; this doe ſeven times, each time drying them well; at laſt, the pouder being dry, have in a readineſſe a ſpirit of wine made thus: ℞ <hi>Maſtick</hi> ℥ 1. ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good ſpirit of wine lb 1. digeſt them together four dayes; then decant the ſpirit of wine, and macerate the prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red pouder of <hi>Antimony</hi> in it for three days; then put altogether in an earthen pot; make it hot, and kindle the ſpirit of wine, ever ſtirring it with a <hi>ſpatula,</hi> till the flame ceaſe, and dry well the pouder that remaines. The doſe is from four graines to ſix. But now I will ſhew thee the beſt preparation of <hi>Stybium</hi> that ever was; it is an univerſal medicine, curing all diſeaſes; and if any thing can ſtand in ſtead of <hi>Aurum potabile,</hi> this may, though it be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what weaker: I have written it in dark words, leſt the unworthy ſhould meet with it: It is made of <hi>Hungarian Sty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium</hi> by the multiplied fire of nature, calcined into moſt white pouder. Take heed of the fume, which will be much; but if by this calcination thou doſt not finde the weight increaſed, thou haſt er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; therefore put it into the fire again, until it increaſe in weight; then is the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170252:45"/>calcynation done. Take of this pouder ℥ 1. of the ſpirit of the higheſt vegetable lb 1. mix them, and digeſt them twenty dayes, or a moneth; then decant the liquor: The doſe is from <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>II to <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>III, and ſo to ℥s: A profound ſecret in all diſeaſes. If thou haſt a mind to make uſe of the pouder remaining, then cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine it as before; the calcination is ſoon done, and the pouder will be encreaſed in power and weight; ſo haſt thou a perpetual <hi>mineral</hi> of health. I have ſaid much to thee, if thou underſtand me; neither dare I ſpeak more clearly; uſe it to the benefit of the poor: If thou underſtand the ſenſe rather then the words, I have ſhewn thee the way to greater matters. Further thou mayſt uſe our mineral <hi>Panchymagogon</hi> in all Obſtructions, Dropſies, and the like af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections: It is made of ☿ <hi>vitae, vitrum Antimonii</hi> prepared as before, <hi>ana</hi> ℈II: ☿ <hi>coeleſtis</hi> ℈III: Let them be well ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and then with the ſpirit of common ſalt ſaturate with gold, let there be made a paſte, which dry, and ſprinkle again with the ſpirit of ſalt; doe thus thrice: at laſt infuſe this pouder in the ſpirit of wine, digeſting it three or
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170252:45"/>four dayes; then heat it ſo that the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit may take fire, and ſtir it with a <hi>ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tula</hi> till the flame ceaſe; then dry the matter and poure on it ſpirit of wine, and doe as before three times; then dry the pouder, and keep it: The doſe is from ſix graines to ten, as ſeems good. In ſome diſeaſes this may be mixed with the <hi>reſina Scammonii,</hi> ſo will it neatly purge all the humours of the body: Theſe are taken out of the family of Minerals, then which there can be no better given; out of the vegetative fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily many things may be taken: The chiefeſt I uſe, follow. I cannot too much commend the <hi>Reſina Scammonii,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be taken by it ſelfe, or with <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar</hi> vitriolated, or <hi>Chryſtalline</hi> in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient doſe, or whether you adde unto it <hi>Antimony</hi> purging downwards; but then you muſt uſe leſſe <hi>Chryſtal</hi> of <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar;</hi> as for example: In an intermitting Tertian Feaver, the body being indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently diſpoſed to Purgation, give the <hi>reſina Scammonii</hi> 12. graines; of the glaſſe of <hi>Antimony</hi> purging downwards 2 or 3 graines; of <hi>Chriſtal</hi> of <hi>Tartar</hi> 6 grains, thou ſhalt certainly cure all Feavers: But this medicine muſt be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170252:46"/>before the Paroxyſm, that Nature and the Phyſick may work together: If need be, let it be repeated; beſides, thou mayſt varie the doſe according to thine own judgment: This doth like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe cure continual burning-feavers, if it be given the firſt and ſecond day while the Patient is yet ſtrong; thou mayſt, if thou wilt, afterwards uſe ſome Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aphoretical, eſpecially of thoſe that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure ſweat, not by colliquation, but confortation, as the aforeſaid prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Antimony.</hi> Out of what hath been ſaid, thou mayſt learn to make a <hi>Panchymagogon,</hi> if thou know how to vary the <hi>doſis</hi> of the ingredient accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the variety of the humours: Thou maiſt alſo uſe the extract of black <hi>Hellebore</hi> for all melancholick diſeaſes made by white wine, eſpecially in the ſuppreſſion of the <hi>Menſtrua's,</hi> and all diſeaſes ariſing from thence: And thou maiſt adde to theſe the <hi>roſen</hi> of <hi>Scammo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny:</hi> ſo ſhalt thou both haſten the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and take away the nauſeouſneſs which often proceeds from the <hi>Hellebore:</hi> That which is by <hi>Rulandus</hi> called the golden ſpirit of life, is good for many diſeaſes: It is made with a ſtrong ſpirit
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170252:46"/>of wine, drawn from the Trochiſques of <hi>Alhendale,</hi> or the tincture: The doſe of the tincted liquor is from ℥ ſem1. to ℥1: Thou mayſt alſo in all diſeaſes of the Liver or Meſeraicks uſe with good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs our extract of <hi>Rubarb:</hi> It is made with the water of <hi>Cichory,</hi> whereunto is added the oyle rectified from his ſalt, together with the ſalt thereof, all digeſted till they be united: It is given in water di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled from the extract, or in <hi>Cichory</hi>-water, from the quantity of ℈2 to <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>1: Steep ſome <hi>Rubarb</hi> in <hi>Cinnamon</hi>-water, which preſſe forth, and ſtill in a glaſſe limbeck <hi>inbalneo,</hi> till the flegm be drawn off; the ſubſtance remaining like honey, keep cloſe ſtopped, good for Cramp, Gout, or Melancholy, <hi>Park.</hi> 159.</p>
               <p>Alſo our ſpirit of health helpeth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſeaſes, eſpecially in diſeaſes of the Spleen, Hypochondriack paſſion, and all melancholy diſeaſes, windineſſe, as well of the ſtomach as inteſtines, and in the diſeaſes of the Mother, which I have uſed with great ſucceſſe; it is thus made: Take of the ſtrongeſt ſpirit of wine lb 1. <hi>Sennae Elect.</hi> ℥2. Black <hi>Helle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore</hi> prepared according to <hi>Hartman</hi> ℥6. <hi>Oleum aniſi &amp; faniculi ana</hi> a few drops.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170252:47"/>Bruiſe the <hi>Senna</hi> and the <hi>Hellebore,</hi> &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerate them in the ſpirit of wine, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting often upon them the ſaid oyles for 14. daies ſpace; then take them out and preſſe them, and put as much of the new ſpecies as thou didſt at firſt; digeſt them and preſſe them againe and againe; put new as at firſt, doing all things as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: After the laſt expreſſion keep the ſpirit for thy uſe: The doſe is from ℥ſs to ℥1. I have likewiſe uſed <hi>Caryoſtinum</hi> chymically prepared very happily: The chymical oyl of Anniſeed taken in broth or in wine three or four drops at a time, at the moſt, healeth the ſame diſeaſes: The Extract may alſo be uſed made thus; infuſe the ſeeds bruiſed 24 houres in the ſpirit of wine; let it ſtand as long in <hi>balneo,</hi> then preſſe it forth, and diſtil it in a glaſſe, the reſidence keep for uſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Epilepſie, Spaſm, yea Madneſs; <hi>Park, cap. de Aniſo.</hi> The chymical oyle of Roſemary is commended for many griefes, but one drop or two at once: Alſo an oyle made by inſolation thus; ℞ the flowers, and put them in a ſtrong glaſſe well ſtopped, and digeſt them in hot horſedung 14 dayes; which then take out, and unſtop it, and lay a fine
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170252:47"/>cloth over the mouth, which put in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother ſtrong glaſſe, and an oyle will diſtil, which is a moſt ſoveraign balme for benummed joynts, conſumption, tiſick, the whites, peſtilence, jaundice, dim eyes, obſtructions, wind, hypochon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driack paſſion, indigeſtion, &amp;c. <hi>Park.</hi> 77. Lavender alſo is commended for many griefs: Make therefore according to the former directions, either an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract or oyle: It is good for Apoplexy, Epilepſie, Sppor, Convulſions, Palſies, Syncopes, and ſtrengthens the ſtomach, opens the liver and ſpleen, provoketh the menſtrua's, good againſt the Collick; but the oyle muſt be ſparingly uſed, becauſe of its fierce piercing ſpirits.</p>
               <p>For Vomits, I uſe the common ones, neceſſity forcing; but I prefer that <hi>aqua benedicta Rulandi,</hi> deſcribed by <hi>Hartman</hi> in his <hi>Chymica Praxi:</hi> It is made of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony</hi> and <hi>Vitriol ana,</hi> and twice or thrice as much of <hi>Sal Niter</hi> into <hi>Crocus metallorum,</hi> which being exquiſitely ſweetned, is given by infuſion ℈1, or ſomewhat more, as the ſickneſs requires in ℥3 of whitewine. The <hi>Vomitorium Conradinum Crollii</hi> is not to be deſpiſed. The coagulated <hi>Aſari</hi> deſcribed by <hi>Hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:170252:48"/>in the diſeaſes of the ſtomach and meſeraicks, when there is need of vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting, is very good: The cold Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of <hi>Angelus Sala,</hi> in continual and burning Feavers, is an excellent reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: ☿ <hi>vitae</hi> both vomiting and purging in rebellious diſeaſes, is excellent alſo whileſt the party is ſtrong: Alſo the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract of white <hi>Hellebore</hi> given in a conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient doſe, cures all paines in the head that ariſe from the ſtomach or the lower parts. And ſo much for Purging.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XV. <hi>Of Phlebotomy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrſt underſtand, that whatſoever Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine may be uſed in other Phyſick, may alſo be uſed here. And as for <hi>Phle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>botomy,</hi> firſt to them that contemplate the depths of Nature, and behold the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt cauſes of things, it may ſeem too
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170252:48"/>frequent <hi>Phlebotomy</hi> came into uſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Phyſicians: Eſpecially if the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of them be true, that ſay blood doth not putrifie, which is true both in reaſon and experience: For blood cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, ceaſeth to be blood, and dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerateth into unnatural humors, which are to be purged, not by letting of blood, but by ſweat or purgation, as the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter requireth. But perhaps they will ſay they doe it to coole the body; yet it is ſcarcely agreeable to reaſon, that blood ſhould be a cauſe of a feaveriſh or preternatural heat; unleſſe peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the ſpirits that have their ſeat in the blood, be ſtirred up by fermentation, which is ſeldome done <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> neither laſteth it, except choler be joyned therewith; which being purged away, the motion and heat are preſently quieted and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed: or it may be, becauſe ſometimes too much blood grieveth the body, and ſo begeteth Feavers: But to that I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that ſuch are not to be cured by <hi>Phlebotomy,</hi> becauſe a Phyſician muſt ever follow nature, and never ſtray from her lawes: And Nature hath ſhewed another way, that doth not trouble the body like <hi>Phlebotomy,</hi> and that is, to want nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment;
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170252:49"/>for whiles the body is not nouriſhed, the blood is conſumed, if it be not repaired by Aliment; therefore take away Aliment for the time, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will conſume the blood, without either troubling the humours or the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; and therefore ſage <hi>Hippocrates</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed ſlender dyers. But if thou ſay the body cannot now be nouriſhed becauſe of the malignant humours that infect the blood, thou ſayeſt nothing; for why doſt not thou throw them out by purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? It may be thou wilt ſay, there appeares no concoction; yet <hi>Hippocrates</hi> purgeth the turgid and ſwelling hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours. But who ſeeth not how much adoe may be made about the concoction of humours in Feavers? What if I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, with <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>racelſus,</hi> that there can be no Feavers at all without fermentation of the humours, which is as it were the very top of concoction: Do I not ſpeak reaſon? For what elſe but fermentation could breed ſuch a heat, and ſtir up ſuch troubles in his body? Choler, if it be an humour, yet it cannot grow hot, but either by external fire, or fermentation. Some prattle that putrefaction can ſtir up heat, but this is a trifle: Let them
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170252:49"/>tell me how putrefaction, which is a certain corruption, can cauſe heat; and whether this effect agreeth to all putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction? They dare not ſay ſo, for ſenſe would convince them; for it agreeth onely to moiſt things when they putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, and yet not by reaſon of putrefacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; neither is that the adaequate cauſe, but <hi>Fermentation</hi> cauſeth heat: For look how much it putrefieth, ſo much the heat decreaſeth, as it is plainly ſeen in all moiſt things putrifying; and the reaſon is, becauſe look how much corruption prevaileth, by ſo much fermentation is extinguiſhed: But let us hear theſe mens definition of putrefaction; it is (ſay they) the corruption of proper and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural heat in every moiſt thing by a ſtrange heat, as of the ambient; or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Galen,</hi> it is change of the whole ſubſtance of the body, putrifying to corruption by external heat. The firſt ſuppoſeth that the proper heat of a thing can be diſſipated by an external heat: But then let them tell me how heat, as heat, can work upon heat; what if it doe not firſt diſſipate natural heat, but conſume radical moiſture? For the property of heat is not to work upon
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170252:50"/>heat, but upon moiſture its paſſive qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity: Now if it work upon moiſture, it dryeth; but drying hinders putrefaction. Again, if it firſt work upon moiſture, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionally with the moiſt it conſumeth that which is hot, or heat it ſelf; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is ſo much heat loſt, as the moiſture left requireth: And ſo it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that external heat is not the cauſe of putrefaction. Look upon other things that putrifie; doth not heat by drying hinder putrefaction? and doth not natural cold ſometimes advance it? yea, and ſurely it ought to cauſe it, if it conſiſt in the corruption of heat, and that in moiſture; for what can deſtroy beat in a moiſt body, where there is nothing but moiſture left, except but cold? More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over it ſeemes that putrefaction cannot proceed from the corruption of proper heat. For if this were ſo, then the more the proper heat ſhould decreaſe, the more the putrefaction prevaileth, and ſo would be perfected when the heat were driven clean away: But who ſeeth not the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that putrefaction ceaſeth when heat is clean gone? do not thoſe things that have the leaſt portion of this heat, laſt longeſt without putrefaction? But
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170252:50"/>that we may come to that heat that takes its original from putrefaction (as theſe men would have it) of which is now all the controverſie, let any man tell me how external heat can ſtir up a greater and more intenſe heat? How doe dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hils putrifie (I ſpeak after their manner) in the winter-time, and have more heat then either the proper heat declining, or the ambient can ſtir up? Nay, they putrifie ſooner in the Winter then in the Summer, if they be laid in great heaps: And whence is that great inflammation in Feavers? not from the internal hear, ſaith <hi>Galen,</hi> but from a ſtrange adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titious heat; but whence it comes, or what it brings into the putrid matter, neither he nor any elſe can tell. But from the definition it is cleare, that pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefaction cannot be the cauſe of heat, becauſe it deſtroyeth heat, and is intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced from an external heat: That which is putrid is onely then the ſubject of the heat, which preſently paſſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way according to the intention or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the matter: neither laſteth it longer then the cauſe is preſent; and how theſe things agree to Feavers, let them look. Now as to <hi>Galens</hi> definition, I
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170252:51"/>wonder why he ſo unadviſedly and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculouſly made the body putrifying to be the ſubject of putrefaction? whether in the bringing in of all putrefaction is there a putrifying body neceſſarily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>required? And therefore that which is once ſound, is for ever free from putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction. But external heat is by him called the cauſe of putrefaction; and therefore it ſhall be the cauſe of heat in that that putrifieth: But putrefaction it ſelf cannot be called the cauſe of heat; yet I would fain have ſome of them tell me how moiſt things can putrifie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fermentation going before? &amp; where ſhall the putrefaction of humours at length ſtay but in corruption? And therefore that which is truly putrified, is not the ſame that it was before putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction finiſhed, but is changed into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother thing of an inferiour order, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the heat that is gone: And ſo choler putrefied is not now choler, but another thing colder then choler; and therefore cannot cauſe a Tertian, which depends of choler, as appeares by the excrements. Beſides, putrefaction is alwaies accompanied with ſtinkings (by which I doe not underſtand that odour
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170252:51"/>which is to us unpleaſant; but that which agreeth not with things in their proper ſtate) but who ever ſaw ſtinking choler avoyded in Feavers, except it were mixed with ſome things that did truly putrifie? whereas the <hi>faeces</hi> of the belly, though they had an odious ſmell before, yet being putrified, they have a moſt pleaſant odour, as experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence teſtifieth; and therefore the putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of humours is not the cauſe of Feavers, but fermentation; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the heighth of concoction, doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way (other things requiſite being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent) invite to purgation. In ſumme, I would fain ask thoſe ſupercilious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters one thing, what concoction they expect in a putrid humour? Can Nature bring a thing back from corruption? Can it ever be in better ſtate then now it is, if it be putrified? Is it not natures work to perfect the work begun, unleſs her intention be led aſide, or be hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? The truth is, theſe men are too ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile to ſee the ſimplicity of nature. But now, how if all the ſtrife be about the name? and how if Fermentation be by them called putrefaction? I will not ſtand upon this, if ſo be they confeſſe
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170252:52"/>that concoction in Feavers need not be expected; and that by timely purgation they provide for the life of the Patient, which is often loſt by needleſſe letting of blood: But of Feavers more in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place.</p>
               <p>To returne to Phlebotomy, whence we have long digreſſed, againſt which ſome do further urge, that conſidering the whole latitude of nature, they find no medicine that drawes blood; whence they infer, that if blood-letting had been neceſſary, provident nature would have ordained ſomewhat to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, who labours rather to keep the chariot of life with the body: Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, they ask how any man dares be ſo bold to draw blood from a cacochy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mick body, ſeeing themſelves grant tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that blood is the bridle of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours; they will ſay that nature being disburthened, will the ſpeedier riſe up againſt the humours; but fooliſhly: as if one ſhould take away a ſouldiers wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, and then bid him to ſet upon the Enemy, promiſing him by this meanes the Victory, would you not think him mad? How much leſſe is he, that robbing nature of her Armes, bids her
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170252:52"/>make head againſt the enemy? yea, but many have amended upon letting blood. I deny it not; but that was not the cauſe of the recovery, but natural heat, or the vital ſpirit ſtirred up by motion, ſet upon, and conquered the diſeaſe; which heat by any other moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, might have been better ſtirred up, eſpecially by Purgation at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, when there was ſtrength; by which means there is not only induced a motion exciting the ſpirit, but alſo the cauſe of the diſeaſe being partly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, the part is much relieved. Thus you ſee the madneſſe of them that are ſo forward upon every occaſion, time, and age, to let blood; whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, how many dangers follow, I appeal to Experience. And this is the true cauſe why Feavers are ſo ſeldome cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
               <p>But is Phlebotomy wholly to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned? Is it not in ſome cauſes law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for a Phyſitian that follows nature, ſeeing that ſhe in ſome caſes (as by blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at the noſe, &amp;c.) expels blood that is troubleſome? Yes, it is at ſometimes, and upon ſome occaſions needful; but the conditions ought to be obſerved,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170252:53"/>that are fetcht out of the cabinet of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Firſt, that it be never done but in a ſanguine body not too much filled with preternatural humours. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that it be done whileſt the ſtrength is conſtant, under which condition is comprehended the age, ſex, time of the diſeaſe and year, which when they wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken forbid Phlebotomy: Thirdly, that it never be done ſucceſſively, that is, two dayes together, let <hi>Avicen</hi> ſay what he will; for a double motion is too great, and operates too violently, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in Feavers, and troubles na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture very much. Fourthly, in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar irruptions, either in their making or already made, you may doe it more freely. Fifthly, in diverſion, if the diſeaſe require it. Sixthly, In Feavers, when nature ſhewes the way by bleeding at the noſe, or at other paſſages, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded if ſhe doe not evacuate enough of her own accord. Seventhly, if the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural flux of women be ſtayed, it is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted (until nature can by fit medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines be brought to her courſe) for the avoyding of diſeaſes; but there muſt great care be taken to open the paſſages; for nature knows better how to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170252:53"/>her ſelfe then we doe. And in theſe caſes, and upon theſe conditions, it is permitted; but except in a caſe where a particular irruption urgeth, as ſometime in a Pleuriſie and a Squinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, I would alwayes prefer Faſting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Phlebotomy; yet before this, if the indication command, I would free the body from the humours; for ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture would naturally be eaſed: I would Phyſicians would follow nature, and leave off one to ſwear himſelfe a ſlave to <hi>Galen,</hi> another to <hi>Avicen,</hi> a third to <hi>Paracelſus:</hi> Theſe men were great, but when they ſtrove to defend their owne Opinions, they often erred. So much, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:170252:54"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVI. <hi>Of Cauteries.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>CAuteries are uſed of many, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther know not, or conſider not why they uſe them: And this manner of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacuation of all now in uſe is leaſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, eſpecially when it is uſed by way of preſervation; for it weakeneth the member, it opens a way for the vital ſpirit to goe out; it alters the whole body by waſting the natural heat; ſo that almoſt all that uſe it, are either of ſhort life, or elſe growing fat, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled for the duties of life, and fall ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner then they ſhould into old age: For whereas nature thought good at firſt to make ſo many Emunctuories for the body of man, theſe men by making more, ſtir her up too much: Hath not God given medicines to purge the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent humours by natural Emunctuories?
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170252:54"/>and we to make others for our ſelves, is this to follow nature, or to go quite contrary to her? They will ſay they do it to evacuate humors, which elſe would cauſe a diſeaſe: And have not we other meanes in imitation of nature to doe it? But if they be once evacuated, they will come againe, they will indeed, if thou know not how to fortifie nature: They are fooles, that intending to cure a diſeaſe, are conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to make it far worſe: For my part I never ſaw any one by this meanes ſoundly cured; I have ſeen many weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. But are theſe <hi>Fontenellae,</hi> as they call them, utterly to be condemned? Surely if the humour be impact in a member not extremely weakened, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure I would admit them; like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to intercept a humour comming to a weak part until the part be fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: Alſo in averſion thou maiſt uſe them for a time, but warily, but it is better altogether to forbeare them. If thou wilt follow the trivial wayes, then doe it not in a weak body, nor in a child, except for a ſhort time, nor in a weak member, nor in a body extremely cacoochymical: But if thou doe uſe
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170252:55"/>them, then handle the purulent matter that comes from them according to the precepts of this Art, and apply to the wound thoſe things that are eſpecially proper to the diſeaſe, and then thou mayſt doe wonders: The ſame is to be underſtood of blood drawn by Phlebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy, by which thou mayſt doe great matters, as ſhall be ſaid in the Chapter of Blood.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVII. <hi>Of Confortative Medicines.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is a goodly thing to proceed to a work with conſent of all nature; and to that end we have firſt and briefly ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the beſt and moſt famous evacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: now of Cordials the which are inwardly to be taken, it being impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but that the diſeaſe ſhould be cured if the vital ſpirit be duly fortified as well within as without: we will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170252:55"/>lay down ſome moſt ſecret and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal things: And firſt the true <hi>Bezoar</hi> is to be admired, which without any preparation yields a ſingular cordial, comforting the heart and principall members; yet experience ſhewes us that it is much better when it is reduced to a Magiſtery; the <hi>doſis</hi> is from 4. grains to a ℈. The ſame judgement is to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the natural white <hi>Balſome</hi> of <hi>Peru,</hi> of which <hi>Monardus</hi> hath diſcourſt at large, whom thom maiſt ſafely fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low: The not vulgar preparation of <hi>Coral</hi> and <hi>Pearl</hi> we will hereafter ſpeak of, in the <hi>interim</hi> take ſome compounds. And the firſt ſhall be a <hi>Diatherion,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called by the Inventors name (<hi>Gaſcoynes</hi> pouder) which ſecret he ſold to the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi> for 300 <hi>l.</hi> I will give it freely. ℞ the toes of Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crabs boyled; beat them to pouder, which muſt be done the ☉ and <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> being in <hi>Cancer:</hi> Of this pouder take ℥i. of the Magiſtery of <hi>Coral</hi> and <hi>Pearl ana</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ii. of the true <hi>Bezoar</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>i. make rolls with the jelly of vipers skins, or if thou wilt, of the fleſh of the whole vipers, which is as good; and being dried, let them be made up again, and dryed with the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170252:56"/>ſame jelly, the oftner you doe it, the better: The uſe of it is to beat it into pouder, and to give from ℈i. to ℈ii. almoſt in any diſeaſe repeating it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: In poyſon thou maiſt give from <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>i to <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ii. But if thou knoweſt how to calcyne the Crabs clawes, Coral, Pearl, and Bezoar with the fire of nature, it would be an admirable <hi>Alexiterium</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and far more precious then any gold: The ſecond Cordial ſhall be our precious <hi>Diarrhodon.</hi> ℞ of pile roſe-leave as much as thou wilt, bruiſe them well in a morter until they be in an even maſs; and to every ounce thereof put of the extract of Cinnamon made by Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, and of the extract of Cloves and. Mace made by the ſame water <hi>ana</hi> ℥i of the extract of Musk and Amber made together, ſo that the Amber be three times as much as the Musk ℈ii. (This extract is made by meanes of a very ſtrong ſpirit of wine drawne off in a gentle <hi>balneo</hi> to the conſiſtence of oyle) Of the ſalt of Coral and Pearl <hi>ana</hi> ℈iiii. of <hi>Aqua magnanimitatis</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ſs: of the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſpirit of Roſes <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>iſs: let them all be well mingled and inſolated in a glaſſe veſſel, and ſtopped all the reſt of
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170252:56"/>the Summer; about the end of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> put them in <hi>balneo</hi> for a moneth; then ſeparate the <hi>faeces,</hi> and thou haſt a Kingly Medicine: The <hi>doſis</hi> is from ℈ſ. to ℈i. It doth miraculouſly ſtrengthen all the bowels, defends the health, ſtrengthens the ſeminal powers, and brings them to a fruitful diſpoſition. But to proceed from the flowers of <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha loortenſis</hi> (marigolds and the darkiſh red clove-gilly-flowers, there is made a ſpecial Cordial, eſpecially if you add the third part of the Extract of Saffron; let them be all drawn by a ſpirit of wine Cariophilate, according to Art. <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celſus</hi> his great Confortative good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt moſt diſeaſes of the body, is ſo and deſcribed by <hi>Crollius,</hi> with a long relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the vertues. The preparation of Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> rectified Amber is this, <hi>viz.</hi> ℞ of the beſt Ambergreeſe ℥i. elected Musk not ſophiſticated <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>i. of the whiteſt Sugar ℥s. pulverize them according to Art, imbibe them with the burning ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Roſes, and grinde them together till they be in a reaſonable ſoft paſt. Put them in a cloſe veſſel to digeſt in the ſun till it be dry, then imbibe them as before and dry it, the oftner the better and
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170252:57"/>ſtronger will the Medicine be; the <hi>doſis</hi> the quantity of a great Peaſe in diſtilled water of <hi>Satyrion</hi> impregnated with his own ſalt; it comforts all the inward parts, it moiſtens the body by encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the radical moiſture; it encreaſeth the power of generation, and cureth them that are barren of either Sex: The ſpirit of Soot is of great force alſo right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prepared; the manner how is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant in <hi>Hartman,</hi> where he ſpeakes of Confortatives in his <hi>Chymica Iatrica,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the beginning: And though the power of theſe be not ſo great as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the name of univerſal Medicines, yet experience ſhewes their power to be very great, and that they are alwayes uſed with good ſucceſſe But to enrich this new Art with an unvaluable Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, we will teach the calcination or diſſolution of Herbs, Stones, Minerals, and Mettals, wherein every thing may according to his own nature become an univerſal Medicine, and being exalted, work according to its ſubject; ſo that they ſhall equal the true <hi>Aurum Potabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le,</hi> which appears ſprings from the ſame root. And here Reader know, that our words are not otherwiſe to be interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170252:57"/>then out of the Books of genuine Philoſophers; but not like <hi>Quercitan,</hi> who though otherwiſe a great Schollar, ſpeaking of <hi>Theriaca</hi> in his <hi>Pharmaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paeia dogmaticorum reſtituta,</hi> calls the ſpirit of wine the fire of nature, and the ſalt of the Earth, the ſalt and ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur of nature; as if nature did uſe the ſpirit of wine to the generation of all things, and plaid the Chymick in the ſalt of the Earth. I doe not deny but the whole Earth, and principally the ſalt, is the receiver of the ſulphure and Mercury of nature, yet hath it no more then is ſufficient for it ſelfe; and as ſoon as it hath it, it immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly giveth it to another: We have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to doe then with the ſalt of the Earth, the ſpirit of Wine, or any vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly known ſalts and ſpirits whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. It is far another matter, which the blind, that are hindered with many operations, cannot ſee: Now how this calcination worketh miracles, I will tell thee: When here at <hi>London</hi> I did la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hour about the calcination of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral in a naked fire, in a ſtrong reverbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration foure dayes and nights, and could by no meanes get them to be red, I
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170252:58"/>gave it to the Glaſſe-makers to keep it a time in their fire; and when they had tryed it foure dayes in their fire, found it onely a little yellow on the outſide, having in taſte a little ſaltiſh ſweetneſſe: Whiles I was troubled at this, comes to <hi>London</hi> the moſt learned and ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sir <hi>Hen. Mer.</hi> and complaining to him of my Coral, he told me that in 8. houres ſpace he had calcined 8 ℥s of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral into a reddiſh colour, which put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſpirit of wine to, yeilded a yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowiſh tincture, whereas mine yeilded no tincture at all; which when I heard, I told him the ſecret was better then <hi>Aurum Potabile:</hi> And thence forward I gave my ſelfe to natural calcination, trying the ſeveral Families of things and learned to multiply the fire by art; whereas before I had only known (and that not long) the calcination of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral gold; ſo by trying many things, Experience taught one thing after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. If therefore thou know nature, I will ſhew thee her naked, as I have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, to my great content and happineſſe, ſeen her; yet I dare not be ſo irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous towards her, as to proſtitute her to the view of the ignorant and unworthy,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170252:58"/>an offence never to be expiated: But to the ſtudious and lovers of truth, I will ſhew a ſpectacle, that ſhall not like <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana</hi> transforme men into Harts, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Angels: Two things onely muſt be ſuppoſed, as foreknown, <hi>viz.</hi> the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers fire of nature, and water of life, which though to many unknown, yet to the punctual followers of nature, will demonſtrate themſelves out of the context. Then to underſtand this natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and abbreviated calcination, two in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments are neceſſary for us, if we mean to gain time. The firſt is a great pair of bellowes; if thou know the fire, thou canſt not, except thou be very ſtupid, but underſtand the bellows by which thou maieſt extremely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the fire: The ſecond is a collato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry veſſel, artificially compoſed of <hi>Asbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinum, alias</hi> called <hi>Pili Salamandrae, vel Pili Diaboli,</hi> which is eaſie to be procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: But though this be alſo unknown; yet in many things thou mayeſt operate without it; but in that ſecond prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſalts of Herbs, by which the Species doth manifeſt it ſelfe in a glaſſe after calcination of the Plant, it cannot be wanted, as alſo in the whole
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170252:59"/>preparation and calcination of gold it muſt be uſed, if any good end be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. And now we will deſcend to the practice, beginning with Plants; and becauſe they are prepared all after one manner, one Example will be ſufficient. Thus then may be compoſed a truly no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; moſt excellent Cordial of Roſes, <hi>viz.</hi> Take Roſes gathered in their Balſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mick time, either bruiſed or unbruiſed it matters not; put them in the colatory veſſel, the orifice well cloſed as with <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes</hi> ſeale; then hang them three months in a digeſting fire, take heed thou ſpoil not the materials with too much fire: After the third moneth bury it in the belly of a great horſe for ſix moneths ſpace; after digeſt it againe till the groſs and impure ſubſtance be ſeparated from the pure; ſo haſt thou a royal cordial indeed, whoſe vertue yet if thou pleaſe, thou mayſt augment thus: Take a good quantity of Roſes, dry them at our fire, at length increaſe the fire till they be calcined to pure white aſhes; then with water extract the ſalt, evaporate the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then put the ſalt in a colatory veſſel, whoſe mouth muſt be ſurely ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led up; let it remain three moneths, as
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170252:59"/>thou didſt the above mentioned Roſes themſelves (then bury it in dung, which muſt be new every fortnight or 3 weeks at the furtheſt) for the ſpace of ſix moneths; then take it out, and put it again to the fire of digeſtion, till the ſpecies begin to appeare; which will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly follow, if thou know how in the calcination and evaporation to keep both the volatil and fixed ſpirit; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which, nothing can be expected con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Idaea;</hi> and mix a ſufficient quantity of this with the other <hi>clyſſis</hi> of Roſes; ſo ſhalt thou have a more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Cordial, exceeding good for all hot diſeaſes, and to reſtore the radical moiſture. And thus mayſt thou make the true <hi>clyſſis</hi> of all Herbs, every Extract working according to the nature and true intention of that herb from which it was taken; yea, their vertues be by the above ſpecified fire of nature and freedome from their <hi>Faeces</hi> wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully multiplyed and enabled; neither can they be purged from their impuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but by our fire.</p>
               <p>Next we will come to middle Minerals and ſtones, which all yield their extracts
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170252:60"/>after one and the ſame manner; let Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral be the example: Then ℞ as much Coral as thou pleaſeſt, ſprinkle it on a calcinatory veſſel to the thickneſſe of a ſtraw, put it to our fire, and ſtir it up with our bellows as much as thou canſt, and ſo multiply the fire till thou ſee the colour changed; but look that the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face be equal, the calcination will be the ſooner effected, and ſo ſuddenly beyond expectation; thus doe 3 or 4 times, for ſo it will ſooner let fall his tincture into the wine; which when it hath done, and that it doth give no more, repeat the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cination as above, and with a new ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit draw off the tincture, or with the ſame till it be extremely red; then mix all the ſpirit of wine wherewith thou haſt drawn the tincture together, and draw them to the conſiſtence of oyle: And thus mayeſt thou draw the tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures from ſtones, middle minerals, and ſalts, infinitely increaſing their ſtrengths: And Pearls thus calcined will truly cure an Hectick Feaver. Now we will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to Mettals, and propound for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample the true <hi>Aurum Potabile,</hi> ſo much magnified amongſt the Philoſphers; to effectuate which, we muſt begin alſo
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170252:60"/>with calcination by our fire, as before expreſſed; then briefly thus: ℞ of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury</hi> made menſtrual by calcination, and ſubtilly prepared by ſublimation, that it may become ſharp &amp; piercing, 12 ℥s. of <hi>Solis</hi> refined by frequent fulmination, and drawn into thin plates one ℥. upon which in a glaſſe veſſel pour ſome of the <hi>Mercury,</hi> about the fourth or fifth part; ſet this glaſſe ſhut up cloſe that nothing fall in or out of it when it is ſtirred or inclined in a lukewarm heat in the firſt degree of heat, and let it ſtand for 15. or 20 dayes; during which time, a part of the <hi>Sol</hi> will be diſſolved into the <hi>Mercury,</hi> by reaſon of the internal fire and corroding acrimony thereof; then pour off that menſtrual, and keep it, and pour on again another part of the ſame, doing as is ſaid before, and let that ſtand 8 or 10 dayes, and thus doe till the <hi>Sol</hi> be all diſſolved into the Mercurial wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; which after the commixtion and reſolution of the <hi>Sol</hi> into it, the Mercury (which before) was menſtrual, now is of another temper, and is called <hi>lac vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gineum, Aqua vitae,</hi> &amp;c. and by many more names amongſt the Philoſophers: Now put all this <hi>lac virgineum</hi> in the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170252:61"/>glaſſe with the aforeſaid degree of heat, for 8 or 10 dayes, and then will appear a black ſuperficial ſubſtance, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly emergent above, and partly ſubſident: The which (the water, or <hi>lac virgineum</hi> being firſt poured off) muſt be collected ſo oft as it appeareth, and is to be kept for the next work, which is Coagula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And this black ſubſtance is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Caput Corvi, ſulphur Auri, ſed crudum &amp; nondum fixum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now to proceed to this Coagulation: Put this <hi>ſulphur Solis</hi> into a vial glaſſe cloſe ſtopped, and ſet in the firſt degree of heat for 8 dayes, till it be almoſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficcated with the humidity of <hi>lac virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis</hi> that was left inherent in it; and then open the glaſſe, and pour thereon as much of the <hi>lac</hi> as is the weight of the <hi>Caput Corvi,</hi> and mix it well, and let it ſtand one or two dayes, till they both be coagulated in one, and become almoſt dry: And do thus till all the <hi>lac</hi> be drunk up, which will be about the ſpace of 90 daes more or leſs, as the matter is of activity. Now then the matter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus coagulated, it muſt goe on with the ſecond degree of heat for one moneths ſpace, and then there will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170252:61"/>
                  <hi>Gauda pavonis,</hi> that is, a variety of colours, and at length it will turne to a white colour, called <hi>corpus album, ſulphur album, terra Philoſophorum,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Now from this coagulation you muſt proceed to fermentation thus. Take as much of purified and laminated <hi>Sol</hi> as anſwers to the third part of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <hi>coagulatum album, alias corpus album,</hi> and of Menſtrual Mercury foure parts of the weight of the <hi>Sol;</hi> Amalgamize them, and put them in the viol on a lukewarm heat for 15 dayes, till the <hi>Sol</hi> by the <hi>Mercury</hi> be reduced into a ſubtile <hi>calx;</hi> then amalgame in a marble mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all the aforeſaid <hi>corpus album</hi> with the <hi>calx Solis,</hi> and menſtrual <hi>Mercury,</hi> and then put altogether in the viol, and ſet it for a moneth in an heat of the 3d. degree, and let it ſo continue a good ſpace, till it become an hard white hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy maſſe, and from thence to an yellow colour, and from thence to an orange, and after incline to a reddiſh colour; from which maſſe, if by the ſpirit of wine thou extract the tincture accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Art, thou mayeſt perform ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable cures in all deſperate diſeaſes: I will yet ſhew another more brief way
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170252:62"/>to the lovers of Art, which take thus: Put foliated gold into a veſſel well ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with <hi>Hermes</hi> ſeale; put it into our fire till it be calcined to aſhes; then ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime it into flores, having his <hi>caput mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum,</hi> or black <hi>terra damnata</hi> in the bottome; then let that which is ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med be with the ſame degree of fire uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the ſame <hi>caput mortuum,</hi> that it may be revived by it; ſo that all may be reduced into an oyle which is called <hi>Oleum Solis;</hi> The doſe hereof is 2, or 3 grains: And out of this Mercury of <hi>Sol</hi> thou maieſt alſo by the ſpirit of wine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract an high redneſs, which will contain the cure of all diſeaſes curable in nature, which is a true <hi>Aurum potabile,</hi> and much to be eſtimated: And by the ſame way thou mayeſt make any other mettal po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. I ingeniouſly confeſſe I have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken more plainly of this ſubject then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any hitherto; and if thou underſtand not what hath been ſaid, then thou art utterly ignorant of nature and her ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations; and therefore I adviſe thee to ſtudy and contemplate her better before thou meddle with theſe ſecrets: <hi>Oſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus Crollius</hi> in his <hi>Baſilica chymica,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the title of his <hi>Cordialia,</hi> deſcribes a
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170252:62"/>way, but yet imperfect, as he confeſſeth, of extracting this quinteſſence, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of an <hi>Aurum potabile;</hi> which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny not but may give an Artiſt ſome light in the aforementioned way: And firſt he diſſolves refined <hi>Sol</hi> in <hi>Aqua Regis,</hi> and then precipitates the <hi>Sol</hi> by a wary and ſoft inſtillation of good oyle of <hi>Tartar,</hi> made by reſolution from a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in a cold cellar; or for want thereof, he takes the ſalt of <hi>Tartar</hi> diſſolved in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua nubis,</hi> by which he makes his precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; then he dulcifies the pouder pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitated 4 or 5 times, and dries in <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neo Maria,</hi> or in a ſtone very carefully, in reſpect of the danger thereof: Then he takes ſome 20 <hi>Menſura's</hi> or therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts of urine of a ſound man that u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to drink wine altogether, or for the moſt part, and puts it into a glaſſe Alembick, and evaporates 19 of theſe meaſures in <hi>Balneo:</hi> The one meaſure that remaines, he diſtils in ſand; at laſt increaſing the fire ſtrongly, then it ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limes a little; the ſalt that remains in the bottome, he takes away, and recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the ſpirit in <hi>Balneo,</hi> and ſo proceeds to a tedious diſtillation, and coagulates this ſpirit of urine with the ſpirit of
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170252:63"/>wine, and then uſeth the ſpirit of ſalt, and pours it on the <hi>calx ſolis,</hi> and goes on to a laborious work, as in his ſaid Book more may at large be ſeen: A true Philoſopher out of theſe things compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and well contemplated, cannot chuſe but find a ready path to ſublime and arcane Secrets: Concerning the <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danum's,</hi> it is not much material here to be ſpoken of; many deſcriptions are extant everywhere. In <hi>Tenzelius</hi> there is an expreſſe form of <hi>Laudenum opia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> and in <hi>Crollius:</hi> And in <hi>Hartman,</hi> of that which is is not opiate. A true Phyſician knowes how to vary the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of things to his own intent and the nature of the diſeaſe. And doubtleſſe he that knows how to effectuate the work of calcination by the fire of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, may performe excellent matters. And thus far for Cordials and Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative Medicines.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:170252:63"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVIII. <hi>Of thoſe Medicines that ought to be choſen in this Art.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw we have declared our mindes ſufficiently of thoſe things that are helps unto this Art; we will proceed further, and demonſtrate what Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines are to be choſen therein, that we may the better underſtand the matter of our Phyſick: And here take dilgent no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that thoſe things are principally to be choſen that beare the ſignature of the diſeaſe, and of the part principally affected: For the knowledge whereof, I would advertiſe thee to be converſant with <hi>Crollius,</hi> and diligently to peruſe his Book <hi>de ſignaturis internis rerum, vel de ſignaturis plantarum humanamembra ſimilitudine repraeſentantium:</hi> In the mean time ſurely, if thou knoweſt the Specifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cals (though the ſignatures doe not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear)
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170252:64"/>yet there needs no doubting of them, for they have either ſuch an exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſignature, as we do not perceive ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hid perhaps in their motion, num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, &amp;c. or an external one unknown un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee becauſe thou art ignorant of the <hi>Anatomy</hi> of them.</p>
               <p>If thou therefore know any ſpecifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calls, contrary to any diſeaſes, apply them diligently, according to this Art to thoſe diſeaſes whereto they are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; in the manner as ſhall be taught.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that help by any known quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, are not ſo much worth as to be taken into this Art, for the matter of our Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, unleſſe it be when they have aſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacity (Mark well what I ſay) for theſe things ought to be precious to thee; for then if any externall quality hurt the body or the ſpirit moſt violently, thou muſt uſe theſe ſagacious plants endued with a contrary quality, which have more ſpirits. And thoſe herbs and plants we call ſagacious, which know how to avoid their enemies and embrace their friends; as for example, the Olive tree is a friend to the <hi>Vine,</hi> and the oake is an enemie to the Olive; likewiſe the Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort is the Vines Enemy: of which ſee
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170252:64"/>
                  <hi>Levinus Lemnius de occultis naturae mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis,</hi> Lib. 40. Cap. 10. and alſo <hi>Bapt. Porta in his Magia naturae,</hi> lib. 10. Cap. 90. <hi>de Sympathia &amp; Antipathia.</hi> Now theſe ſagacious herbs and plants have a ſignature againſt diſeaſes which have ſome property contrary to them; ſo the <hi>Salix</hi> or <hi>Willow</hi> is ſigned to a dry He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctick, for it hath the power to grow a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pace, and though torn or cut from the trunke; if yet it be pricked into the ground, it dyes not, but growes preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into a tree and gets roots of his own: Likewiſe the Oak dyes not of a long time, and therefore that is to be uſed when and where diuturnitie of time is required: and ſo of all other: now you ſee that ſuch herbs are to be choſen, as have in them the ſignature both of the member and the diſeaſe; but becauſe it is ſomewhat difficult to find one that hath both the ſignatures, thou mayſt take two of a divers ſpecies and ſo it will operate the ſame effects, if thou be cunning in the application. This one alſo more I ſhall advertiſe thee of, as the greateſt ſecret in this Art, namely that the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines taken from mens bodies, if they be rightly uſed will perform the greateſt
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170252:65"/>matters. Therefore ſearch with the moſt diligence what parts or excrements of the body, conduce to the diſeaſe; for thou muſt have a due compoſition there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, if thou mean to effect any good therewith: Take Example by the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon ſalve, by meanes whereof wonders are performed in Chirurgery. If thou canſt imitate the compoſition thereof, and canſt mix together ſuch, or the like ingredients, fitting other affects, thou wilt admire the wonderful operations thereof! And becauſe I would not have thee ignorant thereof, I will give it thee here even in <hi>Oſwaldus Crollius,</hi> own words in his <hi>Baſilica Chymica</hi> under the name of his <hi>unguentum Sympatheticum ſeu ſtellatum Paracelſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and under the Title of <hi>vulneraria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Adipis verris a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prugni, Vrſini, ana lotones</hi> oct. i.e. 4 ℥s.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quo ſeniora animalia, eo melior adeps; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men non ultra ſeptennium:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vtrieſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> animalis adeps prius in vino ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bro per dimidiam horam lento igneibulliat; poſtea effundatur ſuper aquam frigidam &amp; cochleari colligatur pinguedo innatuns; quicquid fundum petit, abjiciatur; poſtea</hi> ℞ <hi>Lumbricorum ex vino vel aqua lotorum ſex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarios
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:170252:65"/>duos; nam in affectibus nervorum magnum uſum habent; torrefiant in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ollae tecta in fornace piſtoris; cavendum tamen ne adurantur; poſtea terantur in pulverem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>℞ <hi>hujus pulveris Cerebri aprugni ſiccati, Citrini, Sandali odoriferi, Mummiae Communis E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptiorum, Haematitis ana</hi> 1 ℥.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Demum accipe uſneae è Cranio hominis vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olenta morte perempti abraſae, Luna cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcente &amp; in bona domo exiſtente, Veneris ſi fieri poſſit, non Martis aut Saturni, ad pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus avellanarum duarum circiter, hoc eſt</hi> 1 ℥. <hi>Ex omnibus tritis &amp; invicem mintis cum adipe aprugni &amp; urſi ſecundum artem fiat unguentum in vitro clauſo vel pyxide diligenter adſuos uſus reſervandum: Paretur unguentum ſole in Libra exiſtente, hoc eſt in Autumno.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The uſe of this famous Sympathetical unguent followeth, with the effects and virtues.</p>
               <p>By this ſalve are cured all wounds, by whatſoever weapon they are made; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by blowes, thruſts, falls, if the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon may be but had that made the thruſt, or ſtruck the blow, though the partie wounded be many thouſand
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170252:66"/>miles diſtant, ſo it be a curable wound in nature, and tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> none of the three prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall members be hurt, nor the nerves nor Arteries, neither being duely appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed will ſuffer or permit any noxious ſymptomes to abound, becauſe it is conglutinative, ſuppurative and renova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive; then take the uſe of it thus.</p>
               <p>Annoynt the weapon with the which the partie was wounded, once a day, if the wound be great, or neceſſity compel; otherwiſe but once in 2 dayes, and lap it up with a clean cloth, and in a warm clean place, but not too hot; keep it ſo lapped, take heed no duſt fall on it or cold winds blowe on it, for it will much offend the party though never ſo far diſtant. And this is ſufficient to ſtop the mouthes of thoſe Calumniators that contemn and deſpiſe this famous dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaticall unguent, injuriouſly ſaying it muſt be but a ſmall wound or hurt; and then nature it ſelfe by but only wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping it from the aire will in a ſhort time effect the cure. But to ſuch I make an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that whatſoever wound is in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture curable by the hands of any expert Chirurgeon, the ſame may be done by this famous ſalve (except before except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed)
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170252:66"/>But better to clear theſe ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſpeeches; and to ſtop the mouthes of theſe ignorant, but malicious detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, Let them in the ſmalleſt wound, make this experiment. <hi>viz.</hi> after they have artificially dreſſed the knife, ſword, rapier or inſtrument whatſoever, that made the ſaid wound, let them a little after wipe clean away the ſaid anguent, and inſtead thereof applye ſome <hi>Corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive</hi> to the weapon, as <hi>aqua fortis,</hi> Arſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall powder, ſpirit of Vitrioll, or the like, and then let them tell me how the Patient fares, though never ſo far from them, and let them mark then what pain is procured to the patient thereby, and what ſymptomes follow if ſpeedily carefull remedy be not ſuddenly u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; &amp; and this I hope is ſufficient to ſtop the defamatory tongues of illite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate inveterate <hi>Zoillans</hi> who carp at all things that are out of the reach of their ſhallow capacities. But to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to our unguent. Now before you annoynt the weapon &amp; wrap it up, you are to conſider whether the wound was made by the point only; for then you need to annoint no more then the point, or ſo far as it entered into the fleſh, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:170252:67"/>need you here to ſtich up the lips of the wound, but only to bind it up with a fair linnen cloth firſt either dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in the Patients Vrine or in warm wine: and that day that one annoints the ſaid weapon, let him abſtain from Venery. Alſo obſerve that aſſoone as the weapon is annointed, the bleeding will ceaſe of its own accord, bleed it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo faſt before. In the fractures and ruptures of the bones you muſt adde ſomewhat of the powder of Comphry the great or of the herb Oſteocolla, or of the roots of black Hellebore. Next if thou having the weapon thus anointed, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to know whether the Patient be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to dye or to recover of the ſaid wound, then hold the weapon ſo anointed, over hot coales ſo long till thou canſt but only ſuffer thy hand to touch it, and then ſprinkle the fine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of red <hi>Sanders</hi> and the <hi>bloodſtone</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, and if it ſweat or ſhew drops of blood, then the patient is in great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; otherwiſe not.</p>
               <p>Alſo if thou canſt not come to the weapon that hurt the party, then take a Willow-ſtick and open the wound gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and put the ſtick into it till it bleed a
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170252:67"/>little, and after the blood is dried, not either by the ſun or fire, for thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hale the ſpirits, but of its owne accord, then dreſſe this ſtick as the weapon, or put into the box where the unguent is, leaving it there till it be fully cured.</p>
               <p>If the wound be deep or great, then eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day in the morning you muſt cleanſe and lap it up with a freſh fair linnen cloth, uſing no other extraneous oyle or <hi>unguent:</hi> But to every new wound you muſt obſerve to uſe a new willow ſtick: To cure the tooth-ach herewith, Take a penknife or other inſtrument and ſcarifie the gums till they bleed, and then dreſſe the knife with the <hi>unguent</hi> and preſently the pain ſhall be gone. Alſo if a nayle be run into the foot of man or horſe, firſt pull it out, and then anoint it as above, and it ſhall inſtantly heale it without <hi>ſuppuration.</hi> And thus we may cure all living creatures that have fleſh and bones. For further ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to all the oppoſers of this our <hi>Hepliotrick</hi> or <hi>Traumatick unguent</hi> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre them to the learned notes of <hi>Hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> upon <hi>Baſilica Chymica Crollij</hi> under the title of his <hi>vulneraria</hi> afore ſaid. But it is now time to return to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe;
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:170252:68"/>onely this digreſſion I thought good to inſert here that the true and diligent enquirers after natures ſecrets may be encouraged to goe on chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, till they have attained their deſired ends.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIX. <hi>Of the time as well of gathering as the application of theſe medicines in generall.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ANd for this purpoſe we ſhall ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the influential elections of the heavens not to be here <hi>impertinent;</hi> for indeed herbs and plants do not at all times poſſeſſe the ſame virtues; but ſometimes more, ſometimes leſſe. But the moſt profitable, and beſt for our uſe are thoſe having ſignatures; and which are then gathered, when the ſignature is moſt apparent, and the moone in the ſigne that governs the member ſigned, eſpecially the planet that is lord of the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170252:68"/>plant, being in his eſſential dignities, and beholding the moone favourably And let the moone and the Lord of the plant be both free, the Moone having then dominion of the plant, or <hi>Jupiter</hi> in the ſixth houſe, and take heed the Moone be not joyned to any ill planets that are retrograde. And here note that thoſe things that have their ſignatures in their roots muſt be gathered in <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumne.</hi> But if they have the ſignature of the diſeaſe they muſt be gathered when the planet lord of the diſeaſe is weak, &amp; in a cadent houſe, &amp; the lord of the planet fortified. The medicines taken from men, receive as ſoone as they come from the body, and keep them in veſſells well ſhut till the time you mean to uſe them; but yet if thou canſt fit the Moone and the planet that is lord of the part, if thou intend it for a particular operation, do. But for a general, make <hi>Libra</hi> fortunately aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and <hi>Jupiter</hi> in the ſixth houſe if thou canſt, or at leaſt let him have a friendly aſpect to the ſixth; but eſpeciall heed muſt be taken whether they be excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or blood or ought elſe, that they be not corrupted before thou uſe them;
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170252:69"/>yet miſtake me not as though I ſhould diſlike fermentation, which in this Art is moſt neceſſary, the which ſome call corruption though falſly. But if at any time thou wilt uſe <hi>Mumny</hi> in this Art, take it if poſſible from a body living, or next to life, or elſe it will not do ſo much good as the warme blood, and how ever annoint the <hi>Mumny</hi> with the warm blood, and ſet it to dry in the ſhade, but be ſure it doth not corrupt before the drying; to avoid which, cut it in little ſquare pieces like dice, for ſo it will ſooner dry: If thou canſt not have it from a living or warm body, then it muſt be often annoynted with warm blood, or ſteeped in it, and left there for a time and curiouſly dried, &amp; ſo it will be fortifyed with the ſpirits drawne from the blood. And if at any time thouintend to work by fermentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, aſſoone as the blood, excrements or the like are out of the body, put them up in a cloſe veſſel well ſhut, and mix with them ſuch things as are to be mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if any addition be required, as in ſome experiments there are, and then ſet them todigeſt in a gentle heat, not paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the heat of the body from whence
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:170252:69"/>they came; note alſo you muſt not uſe the ſame veſſels always, but ſometimes glaſſes, ſometimes things taken from living crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. As for example ſake. If thou wouldſt digeſt ones excrements for to ſtay the flux, the ſtreight gut, or gut of the fundament of an hog is the moſt convenient veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel. If thou wouldſt ſtay vomiting, then the ſtomack of a ſwine is beſt to digeſt in, &amp;c. But where thou intendeſt Implantation, then in all putrefactions to this purpoſe, glaſſe veſſels are the beſt, though I would uſe an eggſhell in ſome caſes; as in digeſting blood by it ſelfe, or mixt with ſweat. Now if thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the time of application, generally take it thus: All Application of theſe remedies, be it in Implantation, or a ſimple appoſition of things convenient, ought to be done the Moon in a ſigne convenient and fortunate, and <hi>Jupiter</hi> in the ſixth houſe, as aforeſaid, and the Lord of the Plant or Herb exalted above the Lord of the diſeaſe; yet if all theſe things concur not exactly, neither for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake or procraſtinate the cure; but ſo fit things, that when the reſidue agree, thou mayeſt begin anew; for if there be a due application of things, though
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:170252:70"/>the Stars doe not exactly accord, the cure though prolonged, yet the effect wil lnot be altogether fruſtrate; for note this well, that if thou obſerve the time and the progreſſe of the work in the cure, and ſo ſet upon the diſeaſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh, applying new inſtruments of health, thou canſt not but effect thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires: for in this lies the wiſedome of a Phyſician. But becauſe we have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken concerning the gathering of theſe plants in their moſt vertuals time <hi>(viz.)</hi> when the Plannet that is Lord of the Plant is in his eſſential dignities. It is meet briefly to run over the 7 Planets, and demonſtrate ſome particular Herbs that each Planet doth govern, or is Lord over; and what diſeaſes they alſo have dominion over. And firſt for <hi>Saturn,</hi> he is Lord over Angelica, Box, Byth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wind, Bearefoot, Clotbur, Ceterach, Cummin, Dragon, Fumitory, Ferne, Horſtaile, Hemlock, Hellebor, Moſſe, Mandrake, Nightſhade, Poppy, Spin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nach, Shepherds purſe, Sage, Tutſan, Wolfbane, Parſnip, and many more the like. The Plants and Trees are Cypreſs, Hemp, Savine, Yew, Willow or Sallow, Polipody, Sene, Rue, Pinetree, Tama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risk.
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170252:70"/>The diſeaſes peculiar to his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are Quartane Agues, Teeth, Lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, all melancholy diſtempers, Conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions, Palſies, black Jaundice, Dropſies, Gouts, Apoplexies, <hi>Appetitus Caninus, &amp;c</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Jupiter</hi> he is Lord over theſe Herbs, Plants, Trees, and Drugs follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; namely, Strawberry, Bettony, Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, Organy, wild Marjoram, Rhubarb, Borrage, Bugloſs, Selfeheal, Piony, Daſie, Saffron, Clove-gillyflower, Cloves, Mace, Nutmeg, Sugar, Balſome herb, Maſtix, Wheat, and Violets. Cherry-tree, Birch, Mulberry, Oake, Olive, Almond, Aſh tree, Pear-tree, Hazel, Beech, Barberry, Coral, Mulberry Gooſeberry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The diſeaſes that he reignes over, are infirmities of the Liver, inflammation of the Lungs, palpitation of the Heart, Cramps, pain and ach in the Back-bone, diſeaſes in the Arteries, Veines and Ribs, Pluriſies, Squinancies, Windineſſe, Blood putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied, and all Feavers proceeding from the abundance thereof, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Mars</hi> lordeth over all cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, corroſive, and penetrating herbs and plants; ſuch as the Nettle, all Thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, Reſtharrow, Brambles, Pettyſpurge, Onyons, Scammony, Garlick, Muſtard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:170252:71"/>Pepper, Ginger, Leeks, Red San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Radiſh, Arſeſmart, Tamarinds, Caſtoreum, Aſſarum, Carduus Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus, Cantharides: All pricking trees, as Thorn, Cheſnut, and many more, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Diſeaſes Tertian and peſtilential burning Feavers, Plague, Megrims, Ringwormes, burning Bliſters, Phren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, yellow Jaundies, bloody Flux, Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtula's, all wounds and diſeaſes in the Genitories, the ſtone in the Reins and Bladder, ſmall Pox, all hurts by Iron, Shingles, all cholerick diſeaſes, with many other, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as Tetters, Wounds, Carbuncles.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>Sol</hi> rules the following Plants and Trees: The Lawrel, Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citron, the Vine, Marigold, Roſa Solis, Roſemary, Hypericon, Amber, Musk, Cinnamon, Spikenard, Cellandine, Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bright, Aloes lignum, Balme, and all flowers of good odour inclining to a yellow colour, Enula Campana, Barly, Flos Solis. Of Trees, the Orange, Lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Myrrhe, Frankincenſe, the Cedar, Palm, Lawrel, and many other, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Diſeaſes are rotten Feavers, Cramps, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities of the Eyes, pimples and heat in the face, diſeaſes of the brain, mouth,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:170252:71"/>ſtinking breaths, Catarrhes and Rheums, Syncopa's, Tympanies, with many other the like, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Fifthly <hi>Venus,</hi> and ſhe predominates over thoſe herbs that have white flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and of a ſweet ſavour; as the Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, white and yellow, Satyrion, Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denhaire, or Capill. Veneris, the white and yellow Daffodil, the Myrtle, Ladies Mantle, Sanicle, Vervin, Thime, Cori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander. Trees: The ſweet Apple, the white Roſe, the Fig, the Sycamore, Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine, Walnut, Almonds, Apricocks, Plums, Raiſins, &amp;c. The Diſeaſes are all ſuch as belong to the Matrix; and to the members of Generation; and to the Reins, Belly, Back, French Pox; or any that ſprings from luſt, as Priapiſm, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency, Hernia's, Diabetes, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, <hi>Mercury;</hi> and he triumphs over all ſuch that bear their ſeed in the Husk or Cods; as Beans, the Nut, El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Adders tongue, Dragonwort, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſeeds, Cubebs, twopenny graſs, Lung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, Marjoram: Of Drugs, as Theri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aca, Hiera, Diambra, &amp;c. The Diſeaſes are Vertigoes, Lethargies, Madneſs, Pti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, imperfection by ſtammering in the tongue, phantaſtick imaginations,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:170252:72"/>all the defects of Memory, dry Coughs, Hoarſneſſe, Dumbneſſe, all diſeaſes of the Tongue, ſnuffling in the noſe, &amp;c. with an infinite of the like.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Lady <hi>Luna</hi> her Domination is over Belly-akes, Collicks, Menſtrua's, Dropſies, Sciatica, Worms in children, Convulſion-fits, Falling-ſickneſſe, Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſles, Kings Evil, Apoſtumes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And for her Plants and Herbs, they are Cab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bage, Colworts, Melons, Gourds, Pum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions, Lettuice, Rape, Endine, Muſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rooms, and all herbs which have ſhading and ſpreading leaves; and ſuch as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in watry places. And this will ſuffice to a reaſonable Artiſt by the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of theſe Plants, &amp;c. and diſeaſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpecified, to find out many more of the ſame kind by conſidering the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures thereof; and ſo by the ſimilitude to uſe, and apply them to his own uſe and benefit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:170252:72"/>
               <head>CHAP. XX. <hi>Of the meanes whereby this Art ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyeth the Medicine to procure health.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere are many wayes and meanes whereby this Art applyeth Medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the naked ſpirit; but for Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods ſake we will contract them into two in general: The one we will no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate, and call <hi>Tranſplantation;</hi> the other naked Application. Now Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plantation is when by meanes of the diſeaſed Mummy, we put the diſeaſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Plant, or into another living crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſo procure the Patients reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very; for when the plant or creature hath drawn to it ſelfe the evil complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that troubled the ſpirit vital; then the ſpirit is thereby freed, and made ſit, and enabled to exerciſe his due functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: But the creature or herb into which
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:170252:73"/>the diſeaſe is planted, languiſheth, and at the length, unleſſe it be cured, dyeth: And now here this caution is to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently obſerved, that we ſtrive not in vaine for to tranſplant the diſeaſe into another creature which hath too ſtrong a ſpirit; for the vitat ſpirit being ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times very ſtrong, reſiſts vehemently, and then all the preparation doth no good. But into Plants never ſtrive to tranſplant the diſeaſe, unleſſe it be in ſome property contrary to the diſeaſe; eſpecially take heed leſt it have any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult quality contrary to the nature of man, or might by its too much violence (after it hath attracted the diſeaſe and as it were digeſted it) attract more then it ſhould: For by tranſplan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, not only the evil, but the good is ſometimes attracted, and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to another: And from hence it is manifeſt, that they that tranſplant hair into a Willow to make it grow, and leave it there longer then they ſhould, doe weaken the head, and dim the ſight; for the Willow drawes the ſpirit out of the head too violently: And from hence it appears that a true Artiſt may obtain to himſelfe a ſurpaſſing ſtrength
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:170252:73"/>out of an horſe, or bull, or the like ſtrong creatures, if he know the right and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious uſe of this Tranſplantation. To proceed, this Tranſplantation is two-fold, Immediate, or Mediate: The Immediate is that which is done to any living creature by Mummial things; for ſo the thing whereunto it is applyed, appropriates unto it ſelf, and converts into his own nature the good or evil quality of the Mummy; and either freeth the ſpirit from ſuch a quality, if it be evil; or appropriates to it ſelfe the ſpirit, if it be hurt by no evil quality, and ſortifies it ſelfe by this ſpirit, by meanes whereof it can bring in the qualities and temper of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy into the thing whereunto it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed: And that thing, by meanes of theſe qualities, unites the ſpirit into it; and by that, and in the vertue of it, can work many admirable things: And leſt you ſhould here be deceived by the word <hi>Mummy,</hi> underſtand that it is whatſoever is impregnated with the vital ſpirit, and can exhibit it naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: Others have called the vital ſpirit it ſelfe Mummy; but I conceive it not ſo diſtinct. Next, Mediate tranſplan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:170252:74"/>is that which is done by imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate tranſplantation; as if any qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity be tranſplanted into an herb con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, and that herb given to an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimal; then the quality, or the ſpirit tranſplanted into that herb, will be tranſplanted into the Animal to whom it is given: And by theſe meanes won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders may be performed: But take heed of abuſing this profound knowledge by acting evilly: And here alſo note, that due putrefaction doth excellently pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the aforeſaid Mummy; ſo that any quality may be introduced into A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimals; and experience finds, that blood doth beſt admit of ſuch putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
               <p>Now the other part of this Art, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Naked Application, is nothing elſe but the applying thoſe things to the Mummy which can either correct the evil quality, or can draw the vital ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit off it; by which laſt meanes alſo immediate tranſplantation may be done as in ſome amatories it is manifeſt: And in this Application eſpecial re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard muſt be had; Firſt, that nothing endued with any venemous quality
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:170252:74"/>be applyed to the Mummy; for then the ſpirit being and living in the Mummy, and being prejudiced by that meanes, doth eaſily communicate its hurt to the whole: But if thou fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the former method concerning Signatures, thou canſt not eaſily erre.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Take heed leſt by evil dyet in the time of Application, thou deſtroy not the whole work.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:170252:75"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXI. <hi>Of Tranſplantation, and of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers manner by which it is effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere are ſix manners of Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plantations; viz.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Inſemination.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Implantation.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Impoſition.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Irroration.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>Ineſcation.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. <hi>Approximation.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Inſemination</hi> is when a Magnet im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnated with Mummy, is mingled with fat Earth, wherein the ſeeds of Herbs agreeing to the diſeaſe are ſowed; for the earth being ſifted and mixed with the <hi>Mummy,</hi> and put in an earthen pot, and the ſeeds ſowed therein, and watered with the waſhings of the diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed member, or of the whole body, if it be all affected; ſo in time conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:170252:75"/>all the diſeaſe ſhall be tranſplanted into thoſe ſeeds, provided, as is ſaid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, the ſaid ſeeds be agreeable and proper to the diſeaſe: If time and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion require it, they are to be watered every day with the ſaid waſhings of the part, or the whole, as above is directed. This being done, watch when the ſeeds begin to ſprout; and when it is time, tranſplant them into the like earth, and ſo thou ſhalt perceive, as the herb in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth, the diſeaſe will decreaſe. Some uſe when the herbs are at their maturi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to pull them up, and either hang them to dry in the ſmoke, or throw them into a running River: Now if it ſhall happen that the <hi>Mummy</hi> wherewith the Magnet is impregnated be not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed and infected, then the Plant will be impregnated with the vital ſpirit of him whoſe <hi>Mummy</hi> it was, wherewith ſtrange ſecrets may be accompliſhed: But be thou ſure to elect herbs fit for thy purpoſe; for every one is not fit for all occaſions, each having his peculiar gift; for otherwiſe worketh the ſpirit joyned to <hi>Vervain,</hi> then to <hi>Carduus</hi> or <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelica,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Implantation</hi> is in a manner almoſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:170252:76"/>as Inſemination, but that here the herbs are to be taken with their Rootes, or the root alone and implan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the like earth and ſo prepared and watred, now here it is beſt if the rootes have no other water but the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhings aforeſpoken of; ſo they will be as it were conſtrained to attract and appropriate the Mummie with the greater violence, which alſo you may obſerve in inſemination provided the condition of the herbs require not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, but in all let experience be thy guide, for <hi>experientia Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra Artium.</hi> Yet one thing in both theſe waies is to be noted that if the herbs, plants, or Rootes dye, having at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted ſome ill quality before the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe be fully cured, then another of the ſame kind muſt be implanted in the ſame or rather the like earth.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Impoſition is thus. Take the <hi>Mummic</hi> of the diſeaſed member, or the excrements, or both, and be ſure to take as many as thou canſt get, and put them in a tree or an herbe, betwixt the barke and the wood, or elſe put them into an hole made with a piercer, and ſtop it with a pin of the ſame wood, and put
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:170252:76"/>upon it clammie earth: or if thou put it betwixt the bark and the wood, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the place with the bark and with earth as is done in inoccultation, and leave the <hi>Mummie</hi> there, and thou ſhalt quickly perceive the effect. But yet underſtand that ſome diſeaſes are ſooner cured by inſemination, as the fixed by one, the vollatill by the other. And theſe waies are not burthenſome to nature. Alſo this impoſition may effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually be uſed in preſervation againſt ſome diſeaſes &amp; in every impoſition this is to be noted, that where thou deſireſt a durable effect thou make uſe of long lived trees, and where a ſpeedy effect, uſe them that grow a pace, but remember the caution before mentioned in thoſe that are of celerous growth <hi>(i.)</hi> that as ſoon thou haſt thy deſire, to take out all thou puteſt in, leſt two much attracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſpirits hurt the patient.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Irroration this is done, that by it tranſplantation may be perfected: ſo that every day thou ſhalt water fit and convenient herbs, or a tree, untill the diſeaſe be cured with the urine, ſweat, order, or the waſhings of the member, or whole body as occaſion requires, either ſeverally or all mixed together, which is
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:170252:77"/>beſt; and this I would rather uſe as an help to the other, then alone. And here obſerve aſſoone as irrigation is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, that thou cover all the earth ſo irrigated with new earth, leſt the Aire doe diſſipate the Mummial vertue before the plant attract and receive it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. In eſcation is, when we give the <hi>Mummie</hi> to creatures for food; for then the vitall heat of the creature unites the <hi>Mummie</hi> to it ſelf, and corrects it; appropriating to it ſelf the evill quality by which the ſpirit was diſeaſed, and ſo reſtores health to the body from whence the <hi>Mummie</hi> was extracted. But if the patient be not fully cured when the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is infected and killed; then you muſt give another beaſt a portion of the like <hi>Mummie,</hi> and reiterate the operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on till the party be whole. And in this caſe blood rightly putrified, or to ſpeak more properly, fermented, is eſpecially to beuſed: and yet there is no doubt but the ſame cures may be done with the <hi>Mummie,</hi> extracted by the Magnet. Some have uſed to give the blood, being warme from the vein, with good ſucceſſe to a dog or a ſwine, which though it happen they be not infected with the
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:170252:77"/>diſeaſe (becauſe the ſpirit is therein too faſt locked up and fettered) yet it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by experience that it hath much adjuvated and furthered the cure. And by this operation naturall Philtres are performed, and yet I know that love may be procured by meere applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But I dare deliver no more of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Philtres; for though to men of up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right converſations they may work ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and lawfull effects, yet evill diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed perſons may convert them to abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>five uſes.</p>
               <p n="6">6. But by Approximation, tranſplan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is effected, which is performed, if to the ſick perſon ſuch things be appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed which can attract the vitall ſpirits and active beames, &amp; having ſo attracted them, can unite them to themſelves, and correct them; and this is done either by application of plants, and their parts, or of beaſts, birds or the like. As if you ſhould lay a Cowcumber by an Infant that hath a feaver when it is aſleep, the Cowcumber will wither and the child will be cured; ſo ſome uſe to applye young whelps to the feet of children, ſick in their Cradle; ſo doves cloven in the midſt, and applied hot to the ſoles of the
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:170252:78"/>feet, doe by attraction rectifie the preter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural heat diffuſed through all the body, and remove all pains, being after the ſame manner applyed to ſeveral parts. Soe the fundament of an hen plucked bare, and applyed to the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a viper, freeth the body from the venome, and the hen ſwells (and if not cured) dyeth ſooner then if ſhe had been bit by the Viper. All which things are done by no other means then <hi>Magnetiſme.</hi> Moreover experience tells that ſome diſeaſes infect by approxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; for the ſpirit inſinuating it ſelf into the body communicates an evill diſpoſition to its brother ſpirit. And we may eaſily perceive how love is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by approximation, eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them who by ſweat communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate their ſpirits, and lying in the ſame bed by a long Circulation as it were of ſpirits lead almoſt the ſame life. But that this doth not alwaies happen, is long of the reaſonable ſoule which commands the affections as ſuperiour to them: yet this hinder not our Art; but here I forget an objection of ſome validity; for it may be ſaid, If diſeaſes may be ſo cured by approximation, how then happens it
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:170252:78"/>that he that gives the infection to another is not cured himſelfe? for anſwer, firſtit is to be conſidered what, &amp; what manner of diſeaſes they be that are moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to men by infection; neither would I ſay that every diſeaſe may by tranſplantation be communicated to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very beaſt; I deſire here but to ſearch what diſeaſes of themſelves and their owne nature are fitted for it. And ſuch diſeaſes are of three kinds; the firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in a ſubtile preternaturall heat, not venemous, which when it can quickly and ſuddenly inſinnate it ſelf into bodies, in the leaſt moment of time it will alter the body, and adds unto it an evill complexion. And theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties are here aſcribed unto heate in reſpect of the ſubject in which it lies hid; yet this carrying the heat of the vitall ſpirit, becauſe of the ſudden alteration, is not ſtrongly freed.</p>
               <p>The ſecond kind conſiſts indeed in preternaturall heat; but ſuch an one that lies occult in ſubtile venemous breathes; and this kind worketh more ſoon and more vehemently, as in the Peſtilence.</p>
               <p>The third kind doth not conſiſt in a
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:170252:79"/>meer quality, nor in the meere fluctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting humours nor lurketh in any part peculiarly, but changeth all the habit of the body and ſubverteth all the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, or at leaſt diſpoſeth them other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then mans nature requires. And this kind doth infect by ſending forth an halitus, or vapour altogether infected, and in no part ſound, which though more groſſe then the two former, yet hath an inſinuating power upon a neer approximation; and doth in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of time (though not ſuddenly) o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow the temperature of the body; and of this kind is the <hi>Leproſie</hi> and <hi>French Pox.</hi> Now having layed this ground, I ſay that in the two firſt kinds why the body infecting another is not thereby releaſed it ſelf, this is the cauſe. The infection ſuddenly communicated doth in an inſtant change the body that receives it, and being wholly infected, it cannot correct another, but rather hurts it. And therefore wee ſee when many are ſick of the <hi>Plague</hi> in one houſe, hardly one eſcapes; for the diſeaſe is ſtrengthned by being circulated from one to another, whereas if there be but one infected, there is more hope of his
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:170252:79"/>recovery. And therefore that care and cuſtome is much to be commended, that allots a ſeveral houſe to every particular perſon infected. But it is contrary to in <hi>Feavers;</hi> for it hath been obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that if one be infected by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the infector is often and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently freed, and ſo it goes ſucceſſively through the houſe till it comes to the laſt, who ſeldome eſcapes and very hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And this confirmes our doctrine ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much. And it happens thus, when the weakeſt body falls ſick firſt. As to the third kind, the reaſon why the body in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting is not alwaies cured (beſides what hath been ſaid) is this, becauſe thoſe confirmed diſeaſes have ſo change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the whole habit of the body, that it is very difficult, nay almoſt impoſſible to reſtore it; but in the beginning, that ſome (though impiouſly) have been freed from theſe diſeaſes, as is known by experience and the confeſſion of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers that have tranſplanted them, as in the <hi>French Pox,</hi> by lying with many women. But theſe are deteſtable waies, yet they ſtrengthen and make good our Art:</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:170252:80"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXII. <hi>Next of the means by which naked application is performed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NAked application is two ways per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed; either by impoſition or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication. Impoſition is when ſome thing agreeing to thine owne intention either in quality or ſignature, is put in the Excrement, blood &amp;c. or contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when they themſelves are put into ſome agreeable Compoſition, and there left to remaine till thy deſire be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed. And ſuch compoſition ought to be made in a fit veſſel, of which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hath been formerly delivered. But if the Mummiall things bee to be kept in ſome convenient compoſition, then earthen veſſels will ſerve thy turn. If the matter be liquid, then let them be ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; if otherwiſe, it is ſufficient if but ſtruck in; now application ſtrictly taken, is when liquid things ſigned, are out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:170252:80"/>ward applyed to the body or to the part affected, or when the cure is intended to be done by phyſicall appenſions or by wearing things about one. And theſe are called <hi>Zenextons, Amulets,</hi> or <hi>Sigilla's,</hi> of which <hi>vide Baptiſt Porta in Magia na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turali,</hi> lib. 4. and <hi>Oſwaldus Crollius</hi> in his <hi>Baſilica Chymica</hi> under the title of <hi>Peſtilentiale;</hi> of theſe there is no want a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the common Authors and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of Phyſick, which are extant in a copious manner, though they being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together or for the moſt part ignorant of the cauſes, do aſcribe unto them I know not what, firſt and ſecond quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, never ſeeking further into the true reaſons thereof. Alſo the time of ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of herbs and plants for this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication is neceſſary to be obſerved; for if thou gather herbs, rootes or plants for Amulets, experience tels us that certaine rules can hardly bee ſet downe; only this I will adde that if thou gather herbs for the diſeaſes or paines of the head, thou muſt not ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them as thou doſt herbs for the lower parts, but contrary, as thou doſt <hi>Aſarum</hi> for a purgative; but much of this muſt bee learned by experience. Note
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:170252:81"/>alſo if any one would cure wounds by magnetiſme and that by appoſition, it will be in vaine, unleſſe he firſt ſuffer the Magnetick herbs to putrifie in the ground; for that means frees the virtue, &amp; makes the operation powerfull. And looke that in no operations thou uſe dry herbs, if thou canſt procure green ones; but if neceſſity doe conſtrain thee to uſe dry; then remember to macerate them in their own water before thou uſe them. And alſo obſerve further that it is not alwaies neceſſary to make appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to the part affected; but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times neer it, eſpecially if the part bee pained by conſent, or by contagion of another part; for example if the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack be the cauve of the pain in the head or ſend any noiſome fumes or vapours up unto it, then let the medicine called the Amulet be hung about the neck; but if the ſtomack be of it ſelf diſeaſed, then its beſt to make naked application, next now we will proceed to the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net that is to be uſed in this Art.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:170252:81"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXIII. <hi>Of the Magnet in this Art; the diſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of four, whereof two have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto been unknown to the world.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis is the profoundeſt ſecret in this Art, and of greateſt uſe; for many things that ſeeme impoſſible in nature are eaſily by this accompliſhed. I need not a praeambular recommendation thereof; for he that knowes any thing in this Art, muſt needs acknowledge that not onely we, but nature her ſelfe works magnetically in the greateſt part of her ſublime operations: though we be ſo coecutiated that we perceive her not. But to our purpoſe, know then that I am not ignorant, that there may be divers magnets; all tending to one and the ſame end. I will ſet down firſt two prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall ones, then adde a third moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to reaſon: and laſtly a 4th found out by my owne experience. <hi>Tentzelus</hi>
                  <pb n="154" facs="tcp:170252:82"/>out of ſome of <hi>Paracelſus</hi> words hath made one not to be contemned. He took the ordure of a ſound man, and dryed it in a ſhady place; for ſo it loſt the ſtench and excrementitions moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture; a portion of the ſpirit aforeſaid he kept, which he by a word apt &amp; ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant enough calls ſulphur; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dried he kept for his uſe. And this matter or the preparation thereof can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denied; for a magnet ſo prepared doth copiouſly attract the ſpirits; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will we enviouſly deterre any one from the practice thereof becauſe it is not of our invention. For the ſecond, It is nothing elſe but dryed mans fleſh; the which was a long time preſerved &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed cloſely by Doctor Flood, which as he ſaid, being applied to the region of the heart, would ſo violently attract that it could not long be endured; but it muſt be taken from the body of a man that dyes a violent death; and if it be poſſible, whiles he is warm. But this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſomething difficult to obtain, I will for the third ſhew you a better, and to be had with no ſuch cruelty. Take then the blood of a ſound man or men, as much as thou canſt get. It is not material
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:170252:82"/>whether you take it all at one time or at many; permit this blood to congeal, then pour off the water ſwimming aloſt, and keep it; and when it is coagulated, dry it in the ſhade, and then irrigate and moiſten it with the ſame water poured off it, and ſo dry it, doing ſo till the dry blood hath drunk up all the water, and then being dry, keep it for thy uſe. For the Fourth, which in a manner doth comprehend the whole body of man, Take therefore a great quantity of mans Ordure, but of a ſound man, and with the urine of the ſame man bring it to the conſiſtence of a Pultice; add to it as much ſweat as thou canſt get, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from ſound bodies with linnen cloths or a ſpunge; put them altogether in a clean place in the ſhade till they be dry; then adde as much freſh blood to them, and incorporate them altogether, and ſet them to dry again; and if any water ſwim on the top, decant it, and keep it in a veſſel very well ſhut; and when the aforeſaid materials are dry, imbibe them again with this decanted water, and ſo dry it; and repeat this ſo often, till the maſs have drunk up all the water. This Magnet thus prepared,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:170252:83"/>keep in a veſſel very well cloſed up for thy uſe: And thus haſt thou a Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net of great effect, being the Epitome or <hi>Compendium</hi> of mans body.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXIV. <hi>The uſe of the Magnet in this Art.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEfore we come to the uſe of the Magnet, you muſt underſtand that though the beames before ſpoken of doe alwayes flow from the body, yet there are ſome parts out of which they flow more copiouſly: And, in a word, they are the Emunctories, by which the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is as it were cleanſed, and the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit accompanying thoſe ſuperfluities (becauſe thoſe parts are naturally more porous and ſpungy) wandreth out more freely, finding a larger egreſſe: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for the uſe of the Magnet, apply it to the Emunctory of the place grieved, and procuring the Patient to ſweat,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:170252:83"/>which is beſt done by ſome diaphore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Cordial fitting the diſeaſe) leave there the Magnet till it be impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the vital ſpirit; then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move it and immediately uſe it, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the precepts given in the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Tranſplantation; but be ſure to doe it ſpeedily, for feare the ſpirit be diſſipated by ſome external and more powerful cauſe; for then Tranſplanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will be in vain attempted.</p>
               <p>And if the Patient be not cured at the firſt, doe it againe, and ſo thou ſhalt have thy deſired effect; and mark well that Chapter of Tranſplantation; for very ſtrange and incredible ſecrets may thereby be brought to paſſe. Let not then ignorance reproach this Art; for if what hath been before delivered, be well and rightly underſtood, many rare experiments will eaſily be attained. And this ſhall be ſufficient for the uſe of the Magnet.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:170252:84"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXV. <hi>Of the meanes whereby cures may be done in this Art without a Magnet.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>INdeed ſometimes ſtrange and admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble matters are in this Art performed, not onely with the Magnet, but many times they are with better ſucceſs accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed without it then with it; and that is when the thing it ſelfe that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries the ſpirit nakedly is applyed to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother thing diſpoſed to receive it; but this muſt be ſtrictly regulated according to the precepts aforegiven; and for the moſt part here is required fermentation, that by meanes thereof the ſpirit being freed and looſed from its bonds, may more eaſily inſinuate it ſelfe: And by theſe meanes, for the moſt part, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:170252:84"/>diſeaſes are more happily cured, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the active beames doe more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the part whence they proceed. And experience confirmes it, that the blood, becauſe it is the ſeat and chariot of the vital ſpirit, if it be rightly, and according to Art uſed and applyed, cures the greateſt, and almoſt all diſeaſes of the body; and ſo by the excrements of the belly are all the diſeaſes of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtines cured: And ſo by the urine thoſe of the bladder and reines, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times other diſeaſes, becauſe of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity it hath with the veines, liver, and ſtomach; ſo by the ſpittle that is cough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up may the diſeaſes of the Lungs be cured, and by ſweat the parts from whence it is taken may be helped: And ſo by the nails the diſeaſes of the hands and feet; by the hair the diſeaſes of the parts from whence it is taken; and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally by the blood all the diſeaſes of the body as aforeſaid. Note, that if all the things which belong to any part, be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken together, they will be the ſooner and eaſier performed: We will therefore run over them all ſeverally, but briefly, yet ſo that we ſhall not condemn the joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of two or more of them together;
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:170252:85"/>but rather perſwading ſo to doe, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moſt beneficial, if the rules of Art be kept, followed, and obſerved.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXVI. <hi>And firſt of the Ordure or the Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the backdoor.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BY theſe Excrements, we ſaid a little before, are cured all the diſeaſes of the Inteſtines; the body alſo may be purged, or brought into a flux; diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the fundament are both cured and procured, and many other things, which Experience will manifeſt. And when they are applyed, they cure old Ulcers, Carcinomata, Fiſtula's, &amp;c. yea, which is concealed as a great ſecret, they may ſupply the place of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguentum Sympathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticum</hi> without any great preparation; but you muſt underſtand they muſt be choſen from a ſound man, and a ſtrong body, leſt the preparation hurt them that are
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:170252:85"/>weaker: And by theſe <hi>faeces</hi> mixt with wholſome herbs, much good may be done by Tranſplantation; and truly this may be ſome cauſe (together with the freſh Airs ſalubrity) why Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try people are of a ſounder conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and live longer then Citizens; for the Citizens permit and ſuffer their Excrements to putrefie in leiſtals, or caſt them into unwholſome places; but the other Countrymen committing them to the earth, moſt commonly amongſt wholſome herbs, and ſo by meanes of an occult Tranſplantation, lead their lives more free from diſeaſes: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we have given a caveat to take heed of the excrements of diſeaſed perſons; but now we doe here more particularly adviſe, that you be very careful not to vent your Excrements in places where diſeaſed people doe theirs; for much miſchiefe may proeeed thereby; and likewiſe to avoid the ſmell alſo; nay I have known one get the flux by going to the ſame ſtoole where a party had newly been that had that diſeaſe: Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo take heed that you doe not your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements upon herbs that are malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:170252:86"/>exulcerating, or violently pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging; for hence many times, the cauſe being unknown, proceeds a dangerous dyſſentery, which, until thoſe herbs be quite putrefied, will hardly yield to any Medicine: Finally, it is not ſaſe to leave theſe Excrements in any place where thine enemies can come to them; for if he know but very common things (the which I dare not name for feare of inſtructing evil people) he may much prejudice thee, much more if he be an Artiſt; therefore be cautious, and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prevent theſe things, if thou reſpect thy health and ſafety. Thus much ſhall ſerve for the Excrements of the back door</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:170252:86"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXVI. <hi>Of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>URine is an Excrement of the ſecond Concoction, done in the Liver, or rather in the Veines, from whence by the emulgent veins it is ſent to the reins, yet mixt with blood, out of which by the Uriters it is as it were percolated and ſtrained, and ſo ſent to the bladder, where alſo it abideth a while, and then is by its paſſage caſt out: Hence it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares that the urine hath a great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with moſt part of the body; for it hath great affinity with the Liver, Reines, and Bladder; for by theſe parts it paſſeth, and thereupon Phyſitians judge by the urine of the diſeaſes of theſe parts; and moreover it hath no obſcure conſent with the whole body, having been once joyned with the blood; therefore the Hectick Feaver, a grievous diſeaſe of the whole body, is no way
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:170252:87"/>better cured then by the urine.</p>
               <p>So whatſoever diſeaſes are uſual in this Art, may all be cured by the urine, though the better if there be other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations particular.</p>
               <p>Now as in the Chapter of the Ordure, ſo here it ſhall not be impertinent to adde ſome Cautions: And firſt take heed you uſe not to let your children piſſe in the fire; for it is a conſtant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived opinion amongſt Nurſes, that by ſuch meanes they get the Nephre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick diſeaſe, or the ſtone and gravel. Secondly, that they doe not piſſe upon ſharp and venemous herbs, or ſuch as by their occult quality doe violently provoke urine; for from hence proceeds the exulceration of the Reines and Bladder; neither would I willingly make water in a chamberpot where any man infected with any loathſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe of thoſe parts had made his water in before, or ſuffer my urine to ferment with his; for to a weak body much hurt may come thereby, and to the ſick as much good, nay health, if there be any ſpecifical added againſt the diſeaſe; therefore more ſafer by the urine of ſome beaſt fitting the diſeaſe may the
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:170252:87"/>cure be effected, with the addition o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fermentation, which ought to be done in the bladder of a beaſt of that kinde, adding thoſe things that have both the ſignature of the diſeaſe and the member And ſo much for Urine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXVIII. <hi>Of Sweat and inſenſible Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piration.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SWeat is not onely an Excrement of the third Concoction, but it may alſo be as it were taken for the melting away of the whole body; for no otherwiſe doth the body tend to deſtuction then by reſolution, cauſed either by natural or adventitious heat; for except every part ſhould loſe ſomething of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and greatneſſe, the bodies of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving creatures would grow infinitely; for by continual nouriſhment there is alwayes ſome thing added unto them; nay if this reſolution were not, crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures would not deſire nouriſhment at
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:170252:88"/>all: Sweat therefore, and that which Phyſicians call inſenſible Tranſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is not onely excrementitious, but carries with it the reſolved particles of the body: Hence it comes, that in Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick or Diaſtatiak Phyſick, the ſweat becomes of very great uſe; for by it marveilous wonders are performed, while diſeaſes are as well cauſed as cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, paſſions both of the mind and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy are changed and procured: By theſe a wiſe Phyſician may doe much good, and a poyſoning witch may act much evil, and cauſe madneſſe, anger, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow all the goods of the mind, nay even cauſe death it ſelfe to enſue. This is that Devil, or familiar ſpirit, by which they are thought to have done wonders: Hence it is, as appeares by their own confeſſions, that without this and the like excrements they could never hurt the bodies of any, nay the devil himſelfe cannot conſtraine nature, who, if he doth wonders, he doth them onely by the application of actives to paſſives, and no otherwiſe; for though theſe poor ſilly deluded wretches (de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed with ſuperſtition, feigne many things, and mix much folly and lyes
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:170252:88"/>with the truth, through the devils de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtions, which was alſo done by the Ancients, from whom they took their traditions, holding this opinion, that a Deity being preſent, their imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions would operate more violently, and ſo all nature conſpiring, the effect might be produced) yet whatſoever they did, they did it naturally. For, as aboveſaid, the Devil could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine nature; ſo I here ſay he cannot operate <hi>ſupra naturam, ſed in natura;</hi> and no mervail if his works appear ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable to us, that in reſpect of him know nothing, who hath had the full knowledge and contemplation of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and her operations for this 5000. yeares and odde; beſides his Angelical knowledge, the which he ſtill retaines, ſo that by this natural knowledge it is eaſie for him, or his ſchollars that he inſtructs, to move the paſſions of the mind, to alter the habit of the body, and to infer diſeaſes, ſeeing we in this Art with that ſmall ſpark of knowledge can ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate beyond expectation, even to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration it ſelfe: But it is time to returne to our purpoſe. Well then, I ſay that by this inſenſible Tranſpiration, fixed
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:170252:89"/>in a body, or a ſubject ſitting, all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes of the body may be cured, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be radically fixed, as the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie, Gout, French Pox; or meerly volatil, as Scabs, Morphew, and Scurf, and the like ſuperficial and curaneal diſeaſes of the outmoſt parrs; and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without this ſweat we can doe but little good in this Art: By this the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctick may be cured, the body may be long preſerved ſtrong and able; the paſſions of the mind may be ſtirred up, and as much good may hereby be done: So to prevent miſchief, take theſe Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: It is not unknown that almoſt all infection flowes from this inſenſible Tranſpiration; for it being impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with much ſpirit, and holding it faſt (according to the diſpoſition there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) it works violently; and therefore beware that we partake not of the ſweat or exhalations of an unſound body, nor that we lie not in the ſheets ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnated, nor put on the clothes, ſtock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, gloves or the like, of ſuch unſound perſons, but eſpecially that we be not bed-fellowes with them: And here we may conjecture, nay be fully aſſured, that it is very wholſome in the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:170252:89"/>time to ſleep, and lie upon ſweet and wholſome herbs, as Roſemary, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed Sage, Thyme, Betony, Balme, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to make beds for ſick folks of ſuch herbs that are good for them, according to their ſeveral infirmities; for from thence may by the body be exhaled excellent Confortatives: It is alſo good for weak bodies to uſe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany and garments of ſtrong and able perſons; for from thence flow ſuch ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits as will fortifie weak nature: But in no caſe let us permit our garments to be worne by diſeaſed perſons; and that we caſt not our cloaths impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with our ſweat, into ſtinking and unwholſome places, nor let them come into the hands of evil diſpoſed people; for there is much (though inviſible) matter occultly hid in them, of which <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> though obſcurely, makes fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent mention of. And this ſhall ſerve our turn for inſenſible Tranſpiration.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:170252:90"/>
               <head>GHAP. XXIX. <hi>Of the Haires.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OUt of almoſt moſt parts of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy haires proceed and grow; and they are made, not onely of that dry and viſcous excrements of the third Concoction, growing in the pores, which by addition of new matter grow in length, as ſome falſly imagine; but they take not the leaſt part of their mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from the reſolved parts, as appeares by this experiment in this Diaſtatick Art. If thou wouldſt encreaſe hair by meanes of a Willow tree, if thou ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the medicine to continue longer then it ought, thou wilt bring a weakneſſe upon the part from whence the hair was taken, which can be by no other means but becauſe of the violence of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, the parts being reſolved further then Nature can permit, are injured<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> adde to confirm this truth, that haires are known to grow long after death,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170252:90"/>when as there is no Concoction; and therefore they muſt needs proceed from the body reſolved, which reſolutions are added to the haires by the vital ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which is ſtill there remaining; for by any other meanes this addition can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be; whence alſo our Aſſertion of the remaining ſpirit is confirmed; and hence appeares how great agreement haires have with the body; and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon we uſe them as inſtruments in this Art: It is well known to many what ſtrange things were effected by the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Magi</hi> by the meanes of hair; why may not the like now be done? Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port hath told us how Love hath been procured by meanes of hair burned in a candle Aſtrologically made; which though I queſtion not but it was mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a deale of ſuperfluous and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious fopperies, yet I that ever was accuſtomed to reduce ſuch operations within the confines and poſſibility of natural cauſes, do abſolutely conclude that thoſe ſuperſtitions were nothing but diabolical deluſions, and nothing pertinent nor prevalent to the produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the effects: Likewiſe we have known many diſeaſes (otherwiſe incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable)
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:170252:91"/>cured by haires, eſpecially being taken from the parts affected, being duly putrefied, and mixed with things ſigned, and ſo implanted into Plants; ſo if the haires be taken from the principal E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munctories, no doubt, being well pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, they will cure all, or moſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes: Then for advice, I would have you to be more careful, and not ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly to ſcatter your haire up and downe, which may doe much wrong, nor yet to burne them; for Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence will ſhew you that burning of them doth much impedite the growth; but bury them in ſome wholſome ground if they be any quantity, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to them things good to ſtrengthen the head, which will much conduce to your health.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <pb n="172" facs="tcp:170252:91"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXX. <hi>Of the paring of the Nails and Teeth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Nailes as well as the Hairs have their matter from the Excrements of the third Concoction, ſeparated from the nouriſhment proper to the bones and the more ſolid parts, and therefore they obtain the hardneſſe we ſee, and they grow not but in their uttermoſt extremities; for the body doth not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry plenteouſly exhale ſuch matter as proceeds not but from the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacteſt parts thereof: The Ancients have uſed the paring of the nails againſt ſome moſt rebellious diſeaſes, becauſe it is undeniable but that fixed diſeaſes lie and lurk in the moſt ſixed parts of the body; and therefore wiſe Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty uſed theſe, as we may alſo preſcribe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Quartane Agues, Leproſies, Gout in the feet and hands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the like
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170252:92"/>diſeaſes; but we have altered the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of their proceeding; for they han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged about Beaſts or Fiſhes, and ſo let them goe alive, which ſeemes too raw to have any Tranſplantation effected; therefore we adviſe, that ſome Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficks may be added, and that Fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation may be uſed, the ſooner and more effectually to make good our ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations: And for the Teeth, you may alſo uſe as you doe the parings; but they rather ſeem to have in them a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of cure; for they are produced and made of a moſt ſolid ſtrong ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, as we may ſee by them that have been long buried, whoſe teeth are ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then any other bones; and therefore they iſſue out but few ſpirits, and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly multiplyable by Art; yet becauſe they laſt long ſound, and alwayes ſend out ſome, though ſome ſmall portion of the ſpirit, they are fit for durable ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, which require no great quantity of ſpirits. And here we will leave off concerning the nails and teeth, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the Spittle and Excrements of the Noſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:170252:92"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXXI. <hi>Of the Spittle and the Excrements of the Noſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SOme there are that make a threefold Spittle; for either it falls, ſay they by diſtillation, from the head to the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat, or elſe is brought by coughing up from the Lungs; or laſtly, by nauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe from the ſtomach, and ſo ſpit out at the mouth; but indeed that which is vomited up, deſerves not the name of ſpittle; and that which comes from the Lungs, hath even the ſame original as that of the head; for by diſtillation it ſlides from thence upon the lungs; and being digeſted there a while, is at laſt ſpit out. I am not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant alſo, that ſometimes from the lungs proceed blood and purulent mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and theſe muſt be referred to the Chapter of Blood and Matter: But here we ſpeak of Spittle, which is the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:170252:93"/>part of the meat and drink which Nature cannot concoct into good and convenient nouriſhment, ſent firſt from the ſtomach to the head by vapors, and then diſtilling again from the head to the inferiour parts, and ſo ſent out by the mouth, and called ſpittle: Alſo ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times comes a wateriſh and undigeſted matter, which is ſowriſh, and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately proceeds from the ſtomach to the mouth, which containeth ſome parts of corrupted nutriment, which ſome will have to be a ſpecies, and of the kinds of ſpittle. All theſe, becauſe they have made ſome ſtay in the body, doe according to the former doctrine, carry ſome of the vital ſpirit with them; and therefore we may uſe them in ſome light diſeaſes, according to the portion of the ſpirit they hold: And ſo of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements of the Noſe the ſame may be ſaid: But alwayes be mindful that thou uſe them to the diſeaſes of the part whence they come: And of this I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſe thee, that there is nothing that proceeds from the body more weake then theſe, or that holds leſſe ſpirit; which partly proceedeth from the little ſtay that they have made in the body
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:170252:93"/>partly from the few places they have gone through, and partly from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digeſtion; yet take ſome heed of them, if they be newly avoided, and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes be in thoſe places (as of the other Excrements you were adviſed:) But more eſpecially take heed of the ſome comming from Epilepticks, and of the froth of a mad dog, or of one bitten by a mad dog; for here by violence of the diſeaſe the humours are thruſt out infected: But by a due uſe thereof, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Art thou mayeſt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come that contumacious and deplorable diſeaſe. And this may ſuffice for the Spittle and Excrements of the Noſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXII. <hi>Of Blood and putrefied matter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OVitting theſe many diſputes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Blood, which makes not to our purpoſe; as of the original Circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, &amp;c. and the like, ſo far forth as
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:170252:94"/>doth concerne this Art, I ſay that blood is the principal chariot of the Spirit: And if the ſpirit, as is ſaid, be the bond by which the ſoul is tyed to the body, then where the ſpirit moſt reſideth, there ſhall the ſoule moſt powerfully work: The blood then, if it ſo plentifully poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth the ſpirits, and communicates them to the body, is certainly the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt inſtrument to cure diſeaſes, and to effectuate all the other operations that appertain to this Art; for in the blood the ſpirit is free, and not bound up, as elſewhere; therefore in the blood the ſpirit is ſooneſt affected, becauſe there it is naked; yet we muſt not immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately conclude that it may be taken and uſed ſtrait as it comes from the body, without any fermentation or putrefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; for they are uſeful, and of great concernment: But this take heed of, that thou corrupt not the blood with too much fermentation; for ſo the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit will be driven away, and nothing will be effectual that is therewith at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted: And that you may not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in Fermentation, meditate well this ſecret: Let the blood, with the moſt excellent parcels of the body, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:170252:94"/>ſpoken of, be joyned in a due pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, &amp; put into a natural veſſel, well cloſed, and left or put under an hen to hatch in her broody time, and thou ſhalt have a Magnet, performing by a true Artiſt many miraculous ſecrets, nay even the coagulated maſſe will not dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer much from the beſt of <hi>Paracelſus Homunculo's;</hi> yea, the oyle or liquor ſwimming about it, being mixed with the proper ſweat, changeth and meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphoſeth the mind of man, even, as I may ſay, by the very touch.</p>
               <p>Many more moſt rare and profound operations may be by blood performed, which are better concealed, then to the ignorant, wilful, and malicious world divulged. Follow Nature, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently mark her operations, and be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with her footſteps, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime things will be facile unto thee. In the <hi>interim</hi> take theſe enſuing Cautions. After the blood is drawn, thou muſt be very carefull how thou uſeſt it; for ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly there may both good or hurt be done thereby: Some have thought it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to put it in the ground, which I alſo allow, ſo it be done in a clean place and mixt with wholſome herbs; for if
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:170252:95"/>it ſhould be buried in an unwholſome and infectious place, it may prejudice the body from whence it came: Some will give it to dogs or whelps which I diſlike not; for it may perhaps tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant the diſeaſe, and cure it wholly, or at leaſt help the Phyſician: But it would be far better it were given warme, but beſt of all being putrefied in a cloſe veſſel with a temperate heat: And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed here I can hardly paſſe by the vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany of ſome Empyricks, who with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecrable boldneſſe dare preſume to give blood, yea the menſtrual blood for a Philtre, not conſidering the enſuing miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs iſſuing from thence; for blood, though never ſo pure, is an enemy to the ſtomach, and before it will be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted, is corrupted and turned into pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefactive matter; and then it muſt needs be extremely offenſive and dangerous: Beſides, here lieth not that loving force and vertue which they ſeek after; for there muſt be another manner of prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration before thou canſt come to that; for it muſt be looſed, that the ſpirit may work more freely to incline the mind, and that becauſe of the will ruling; ſo that there is a great force requiſite, and
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:170252:95"/>the conſpiring together of many cauſes, which they that are ignorant of can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver attain the truth; and ſo for want of true natural knowledge, and ſound judgement, calumniate and vituperates the Art. And albeit the blood, of all other things in the body, containes the looſeſt and freeſt ſpirits; yet being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted (experience hath taught us) it is more available, and operates more mightily in every reſpect: But here I doe foreſee an Objection. It may be ſaid, if the power of love lie in the blood; then how happens it that rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous beaſts that doe ſo greedily drink blood, and ſo well digeſt it, are not brought to be in love with thoſe things that they eat, the ſame reaſon being of the individual and the ſpecies? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: Firſt, in particular operations of the whole <hi>ſpecies</hi> to the <hi>individuum,</hi> or of one <hi>individuum</hi> to another, there is not the ſame reaſon. Secondly, they eat unprepared blood, which is not ſo powerful to change nature; but it is moſt certain, that by blood duely fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented and prepared, any <hi>individuum</hi> may be reconciled to another; as this dog to that hare; this cat to that mouſe;
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:170252:96"/>this lyon to that lamb, &amp;c. Thirdly, the beaſt being filled with the commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an angry ſpirit, and retaining alwayes the nature thereof, doth rather incite revenous beaſts into rage, and whet them on to the deſtruction of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. And hence take this general ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, that it is altogether impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and repugnant to the law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, by any preparation whatſoever, to procure love by meanes of blood that is violently ſhed: It is more likely by far to cauſe hatred; and therefore the Ancients in their Reconciliations never drank the blood of one anothers fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head-vein before perfect and undoubted amity appeared: And here note, that the ſalt of blood, if it be diſſolved in the <hi>Menſtruum</hi> of the world, and Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophically handled, it is the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent medicine in the world. And as for matter, or putrefaction, which is nothing elſe but blood corrupted without the veines, of fleſh looſed with rottenneſſe, you may diſpoſe on, as of blood aforeſaid, ſaving that it hath loſt much of his ſpirits (which are in the ſound blood) by its putrefaction; yet by meanes of it, ulcers and old ſores
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:170252:96"/>may be cured with the Sympathetical unguent or water. Some will anoint the inſide of a nutſhell with Balſome, and then put the purulent or ſanious matter into it, and ſo hang it up in the dry aire, and ſo cure ulcers. And here is to be noted, that this matter may be diverſly conſidered, according as it is found in the body; for either it ſimply ariſeth from blood by means of putrefaction, corrupting without the veines, as aforeſaid; or elſe it ariſeth from ſome venemous quality of ſome foule diſeaſe, as in the French Pox; or elſe it is infected with ſome ſimple diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed quality, as in the <hi>Phthiſis;</hi> and from theſe <hi>(experientia teſte)</hi> much prejudice may ariſe. But if thou intend by the Sympathetical water or unguent to cure any ſuch ulcers, the extraneous qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities ſhew that there muſt be ſome <hi>Alexipharm acum,</hi> or Specificks added a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing to the diſeaſe; for you muſt remember the qualities muſt be taken away before the ulcers can be cured: Of ſuch things that are caſt up by vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit we need not ſpeak much; for we may think of them, as of other Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements,
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:170252:97"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="183" facs="tcp:170252:97"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="184" facs="tcp:170252:98"/>uſing alſo the ſame Cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but if the Vomit proceed from Nature, and not procured by Phyſick, it will be more convenient for our purpoſe; yet if it be by Phyſick, it is not altogethe unprofitable: But re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard muſt be had to the quality of the vomitory Medicine; which if it be not contrary to the diſeaſe, muſt be corrected, and things ſigned added to it. And thus we have briefly, yet ſufficiently handled the Theorical and Practical Principles of this Art.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <pb n="185" facs="tcp:170252:98"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXXIII. <hi>Now becauſe we have heretofore ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the neceſſary uſe of Signa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in this Art; I hold it here ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry convenient briefly to adde ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of ſigned Herbs and Plants, the more to illuſtrate the ſame: And we will begin then firſt with the Head.</hi>
               </head>
               <note place="margin">Head.</note>
               <p>FOr the diſeaſes of the which, we finde that Poppy doth ſomething re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the head; and thereupon we uſe the decoction thereof for many infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the ſame.</p>
               <p>Alſo Walnuts have the whole figna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture thereof.</p>
               <p>Alſo the Sea-onyon called <hi>Scilla,</hi> the which is much commended in all Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lepſies.</p>
               <note place="margin">Haires.</note>
               <p>The Moſſe of Trees repreſent the
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:170252:99"/>haire, whoſe decoction is effectual in the falling of the hair.</p>
               <p>Maidenhaire likewiſe is much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for making thick, fair, and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led locks.</p>
               <p>So the Herb <hi>Thapſia</hi> is applauded much by <hi>Avicenna</hi> in the diſeaſe <hi>Alo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecia.</hi>
               </p>
               <note place="margin">Ears.</note>
               <p>Next for the Eares; who is ſo ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid that doth not perceive the ſhels of Oyſters to be their ſignature, and much by <hi>Crollius</hi> uſed againſt deafneſſe?</p>
               <p>Likewiſe <hi>Aſsara baccha,</hi> or Folefoot, the flowers whereof conſerved, and ſo eaten, much availe the hearing and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory.</p>
               <note place="margin">Eyes.</note>
               <p>To the eyes is ſigned the Marigold, which helps the dimneſs.</p>
               <p>So <hi>Agrimony,</hi> or wild Tanſy, whoſe name is ſo called from helping the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe of the Eye called <hi>Argema;</hi> the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of which diſeaſe is ſuch, that if it be in the black of the eye it appeareth white, but being in the white of the eye ſheweth red. Alſo <hi>Anemone</hi> or <hi>Celan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine,</hi> alſo <hi>Scabious,</hi> both good, and ſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the eyes.</p>
               <note place="margin">Noſe.</note>
               <p>So <hi>Mentaſtrum Aquaticum,</hi> whoſe leaf ſomewhat ſhapes out the forme of the
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:170252:99"/>noſe, the extract whereof is exceeding good for the ſmelling loſt or decayed.</p>
               <note place="margin">Gums.</note>
               <p>Likewiſe <hi>Sedum minus,</hi> or Prick-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, being ſigned to the Gums, is very effectual in the Scurvy.</p>
               <note place="margin">Teeth.</note>
               <p>The receptacle of the ſeed of Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane, being the ſignature of the Teeth; therefore the oyle, or the juice expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or the decoction of the root with Arſmart boiled in vinegar, and being hot, to waſh the teeth and gums, doth help the tooth-ach.</p>
               <p>The Pine nut doth very well counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit the repreſentation of the teeth cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>inciſores;</hi> and thereupon we uſe the decoction of Pine-leaves or branches in vinegar, to aſſwage the paine of the Teeth.</p>
               <note place="margin">Throat.</note>
               <p>The herb <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>vularia,</hi> or Horſtong; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the herb <hi>Cervicaria,</hi> both good for Gargariſms.</p>
               <note place="margin">Liver.</note>
               <p>Who is ignorant of the herb Liver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, how nature hath ſigned it for the Liver-infirmities?</p>
               <p>Alſo the Muſhrome of the Oak or Beech-tree, the powder whereof ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kled upon blood violently iſſuing at the noſe or wounds, doth even after a miraculous manner ſtanch it.</p>
               <pb n="188" facs="tcp:170252:100"/>
               <note place="margin">Heart.</note>
               <p>The Quince, Myrabblane, Pomeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, Limmons, Orenges, all good and cordial, and ſigned to the heart.</p>
               <note place="margin">Lungs.</note>
               <p>To whom is Lungwort, called <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monaria,</hi> unknown for his ſignature? the decoction whereof is much availa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in all the impediments that doe in any wiſe appertain to the Lungs.</p>
               <note place="margin">Paps.</note>
               <p>Alſo for the evil affects of the breaſts of women, the <hi>Specula</hi> (or eyes as I may term them) in the taile of a Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cock, as they give an exact ſignature and reſemblance thereof; ſo phyſically uſed, prepared, and adminiſtred in drink, hath great vertue to heal the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments thereof.</p>
               <note place="margin">Spleen.</note>
               <p>So the herb <hi>Scolopendrium,</hi> which the Apothecaries call <hi>Ceterach:</hi> And Hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tongue, and Lupines, all very good for the diſeaſes of the Spleen.</p>
               <note place="margin">Stomach.</note>
               <p>Gallingale, Ginger, and the leaves of Cyclamen, effectual.</p>
               <note place="margin">Inteſtines</note>
               <p>
                  <hi>Callamus aromaticus,</hi> and <hi>Caſſia fiſtula,</hi> of profitable uſe.</p>
               <note place="margin">Bladder.</note>
               <p>The herb <hi>Alkekengi,</hi> called Winter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherries, ſigned to the Bladder, and of excellent vertue againſt the ſtone in the Bladder.</p>
               <p>Alſo the buſhy Tree called <hi>Staphylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendros,</hi>
                  <pb n="189" facs="tcp:170252:100"/>which beareth cods like round bladders: So <hi>Solanum</hi> and <hi>Collutea,</hi> all effectual againſt the diſeaſes of the blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               <note place="margin">The Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitals.</note>
               <p>Likewiſe Aron, or Cuccowpintle, which ſome doe conceive to be the true <hi>Satirion</hi> of <hi>Paracelſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo all the kinds of Dragon-wort, as <hi>Dracunculus major,</hi> the great Dragon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort or Serpentine: So <hi>Drancunculus minor,</hi> leſſe Dragon-wort, or ſpeckled Aron; <hi>Dracunculus paluſtris</hi> water, or Marſh-dragon; <hi>Dracunculus hortenſis,</hi> Tarragon, or biting Dragon-wort. Moreover Beanes, which by their flatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous quality are very provocative, and inciting luſt, and therefore condemned and the uſe forbidden by <hi>Pythagoras</hi> to his followers: Alſo the meal of Beans being made a Pultice, and applyed, is good for the inflation of the Genitals.</p>
               <p>So the Acorne hath the ſignature of the <hi>Preputium.</hi>
               </p>
               <note place="margin">Teſticles.</note>
               <p>All Bulbous Roots, but eſpecially Gandergooſe or Dogſtones: So <hi>Satiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and that kind thereof called <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorchis:</hi> So <hi>Satirion Erythronium:</hi> So the Leek, all inciting and provoking luſt.</p>
               <pb n="190" facs="tcp:170252:101"/>
               <note place="margin">Matrix.</note>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ariſtolochia rotunda:</hi> So Mace inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Nutmeg, as the womb inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Embryon.</p>
               <p>Savine hath the ſignature of the veins of the Matrix, and therefore diſſolves the tartarous humour thereof.</p>
               <note place="margin">Reins.</note>
               <p>Purſlane is properly ſigned to the Reins, and their peculiar diſeaſes.</p>
               <note place="margin">Backbone</note>
               <p>
                  <hi>Filix foemina,</hi> or the female Fern, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth with the ſignature of <hi>Spina dorſi,</hi> which manifeſtly repreſenteth the effigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es thereof.</p>
               <note place="margin">Bones.</note>
               <p>That gravelly ſtone called <hi>Oſſiſana, ſeu lapis ſabuloſus,</hi> found about <hi>Spira</hi> and <hi>Darmſtad,</hi> doth wonderfully operate in the conglutination of broken bones by his magnetick ſignature.</p>
               <note place="margin">Nerves &amp; Veins.</note>
               <p>Plantane hath the whole ſignature of the veins and nerves of the hands and feet: Alſo Savine is ſigned to the Veines.</p>
               <note place="margin">Pores of the skin.</note>
               <p>Hypericon, or St. <hi>Johns</hi> wort, with its perforated leafes, is good for ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions and evil ſweats of the Pores.</p>
               <note place="margin">Hands.</note>
               <p>
                  <hi>Palma Chriſti,</hi> and the Fig-leafes are ſigned thereto, and are available againſt the articular impediments. And this ſhall ſuffice for a taſte of the ſignatures and ſigned herbs to the aforenamed par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular parts of the body.</p>
               <pb n="191" facs="tcp:170252:101"/>
               <p>We will yet for ſome further ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction adde the ſignatures of the diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and demonſtrate what herbs are ſigned to ſome peculiar diſeaſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXIV. <hi>And firſt of the Apolexy.</hi>
               </head>
               <note place="margin">Apoplexy</note>
               <p>THE Lilly of the Valley, whoſe Flowers doe hang like drops, is of great uſe in this diſeaſe: So the Carp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, being of a halfe-moon forme, is herein commended.</p>
               <note place="margin">Sto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <p>As the Chryſtal, Flint, <hi>lapis Citrinus</hi> and <hi>Judaicus, Lincis,</hi> and all which drive out the ſtone, are Magically ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
               <p>So Saxifrage Roots, and <hi>Calculus Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crocoſmi, Lithoſpermon: Lachryma Jobbea: fructus Alkekengi &amp; Ononidis;</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more things that have their magne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick ſignatures.</p>
               <note place="margin">Cancers.</note>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lunaria,</hi> which <hi>Carrichter</hi> affirmed that he cured all the Cancers of the
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:170252:102"/>Breaſts thereby. And <hi>Ros Solis, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <note place="margin">Collick.</note>
               <p>
                  <hi>Convolvulus,</hi> or withwind and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guilla, &amp;c.</p>
               <note place="margin">Dyſentery</note>
               <p>
                  <hi>Acorus Aquaticus,</hi> having a yellow root, and digged up in <hi>May,</hi> is a moſt ſingular Amulet, being appenſed on the region of the belly; for it hath both the colour and ſignature of the Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <note place="margin">Eriſipila's</note>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oxylapathum,</hi> the ſeed whereof is moſt efficacious, being decocted and drunk.</p>
               <p>Alſo the Cholchotar of Vitriol ſtrongly calcined and diſſolved in Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane water, and outwardly applyed.</p>
               <note place="margin">Epilepſie.</note>
               <p>
                  <hi>Viſcus Quercinus:</hi> and Piony ſeeds. <hi>Paracelſus</hi> commends a ſparrow in the Falling Sickneſſe, &amp;c.</p>
               <note place="margin">Excreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſences.</note>
               <p>Agarick, and ſuch Excreſſences of trees, which grow upon the boughs and leafs above the natural order, doe heale theſe turbercula's.</p>
               <note place="margin">Exanthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mato.</note>
               <p>Rapeſeed and Lentils are very effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall, and ſigned both for the ſmall Pox.</p>
               <note place="margin">Ficus ani.</note>
               <p>The herb <hi>Scrofularia,</hi> either the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction uſed, or hanged for an Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let about the orifice of the ſtomach, is excellent in this diſeaſe,</p>
               <pb n="191" facs="tcp:170252:102"/>
               <note place="margin">Fiſtula's.</note>
               <p>
                  <hi>Juncus Aquaticus</hi> hath its ſignature; and therefore the ſalt thereof artificially extracted, and given inwardly and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed outwardly, is a ſure remedy.</p>
               <note place="margin">Hernia's and Rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note>
               <p>In Ruptures and Hernia's you will finde very prevalent the Root of Aron, and Oak-apples gathered in <hi>May,</hi> and hanged in glaſſes in the Sun till they convert to a liquor, and ſo anoint the Hernia's. And it is obſervable, that all creatures that extend &amp; contract them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, are Magically ſigned for theſe impediments: as the Tortoiſe, whoſe calcined powder doth much prevaile; alſo the <hi>Proboſcis,</hi> or mout of an Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant.</p>
               <note place="margin">Flux of Blood.</note>
               <p>Red Sanders boiled in Tent, or ſtiptick red wine, doth ſtay them mightily: So the root of Tormentil: Alſo the Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matite Cornelian Coral, if any of them be held in the hand.</p>
               <p>Eſpecially calcined Vitriol of a blood colour, wonderfully ſtayeth blood out of the breaſt or head, &amp;c.</p>
               <note place="margin">Hemorro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ids.</note>
               <p>The downy ſubſtance of woolly herbs and plants doe by an occult ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſtay Hemorroids, or Pyles ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</p>
               <pb n="192" facs="tcp:170252:103"/>
               <note place="margin">Dropſie.</note>
               <p>The Bryony root hath the ſignature of this: The Extract whereof doth draw forth the water; ſo doth <hi>Radix Miohoacae.</hi>
               </p>
               <note place="margin">Yellow Jaundice.</note>
               <p>Saffron, and Celandine, and <hi>radix Cucurmae,</hi> many other the like, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The fleſh of Vipers prepared, doth much conduce to this diſeaſe.
<note place="margin">Leproſie.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Strawberry hath the ſignature of this infirmity; and therefore the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled water thereof doth make pale a red, pimpled and leprous face; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Raymund Lully in libro de quinta eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentia,</hi> doth highly commend the uſe of Strawberries ſteeped in ſpirit of Wine.
<note place="margin">Pluriſie.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Carduus Benedictus by his pricking leaves ſheweth his ſignature to this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſe; ſo doth <hi>Hippogloſſum</hi> or Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tongue; and ſo doth <hi>Conſolida Regalis,</hi> wilde Cummin, conduce properly here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</p>
               <note place="margin">Phantaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma's.</note>
               <p>Hypericon, or St. <hi>Johns</hi> Wort, is mighty prevalent in obtunding Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſms, the name denoting the vertue <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>(i. e.) ſuper imagines &amp; ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctra dominium habens.</hi> Likewiſe the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines</hi> call it <hi>fuga daemonum.</hi> Alſo <hi>Amir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rbinum</hi> hath potency, &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="193" facs="tcp:170252:103"/>
               <note place="margin">Panatitia.</note>
               <p>Archangel, which bruiſed and put upon the diſeaſe of the looſe skin at the root of the nails, preſently cures.</p>
               <note place="margin">Plague.</note>
               <p>A Toad is ſigned hereto, and a Liz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard extracts the Eſchar of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buncle: And ſo is the Tubers, or Muſhroomes of an Oak, either new, or poudred, and put upon, doth operate effectually, &amp;c.</p>
               <note place="margin">Kings evil</note>
               <p>The herb <hi>Scorfularia,</hi> or dead nettle, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> properly hereto ſigned: and the Fig, which ſwelleth like it.</p>
               <note place="margin">Squinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</note>
               <p>The Mulberry, whoſe juyce, and alſo the leaves, and the juyce of them, is very efficacious for gargarization in this impediment, &amp;c.</p>
               <note place="margin">Cramp.</note>
               <p>The Snail is ſigned hereto, and effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious herein, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The Herb Arſmart is hereto ſinged.
<note place="margin">Stripes black and blue. Urine. retained.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Medulla</hi> in the concavity of a gooſe-quill, dryed and pounded, and given in wine, extremely driveth forth the urine retained.</p>
               <p>Alſo the ſoule of an herring, as the vulgar call it, powdred and given, hath the ſame effect.</p>
               <pb n="194" facs="tcp:170252:104"/>
               <note place="margin">Poyſon &amp; venom.</note>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dracunculus minor,</hi> or ſpeckled A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, which by an occult and ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetical quality in nature doth appear out of the Earth as ſoon as any ſerpent begins to creep abroad; for till that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth above the ground, no Adder, Snake venemous, or Serpent will be ſeen, premoniſhing us as it were to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of them. <hi>Biſtorta</hi> is alſo effectual for the biting of vipes or ſerpents. And all ſuch Plants that have the ſpeckles or marks like to the skin of adders, &amp;c. are found to be ſigned by nature againſt their poyſons and venoms.</p>
               <note place="margin">Wounds.</note>
               <p>Hydropiper being ſigned naturally, as by the bloody ſpots is demonſtrated that appear upon the leaves, which cures new wounds, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And alſo Hypericon being perfora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as it were with a needle, is profitable to all the external and internal imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of the skin.</p>
               <p>And ſo <hi>Millefolium,</hi> and Betony, and all perforated Plants, have their ſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and prevailing potencies in wounds.</p>
               <p>He that deſireth further inſtruction in theſe ſignatures, and more ample uſe
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:170252:104"/>thereof, muſt acquaint himſelfe with <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> or at leaſtwiſe with <hi>Oſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus Crollius</hi> in the latter end of his <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilica Chymica,</hi> as afore, is adviſed where he may receive more ample ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and judicious inſtruction. And this ſhall ſuffice for the preſent concerning this Art.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Ne nimium Boltone precor, precor, Artis amice;</l>
                  <l>Quod prius eſt dictum ſit dictum ſat ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pienti.</l>
                  <l>Nam jam ſumma procul villarum fulmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na fumant,</l>
                  <l>Majoreſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> cadunt altis de montibus um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brae.</l>
                  <l>Vive, valo Lector; ſiquid ſcis vectius Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis</l>
                  <l>Candidus imperti: ſi non, his utere me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:170252:105"/>
            <head>Reader, <hi>Theſe Books follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing are printed for</hi> Nat. Brook, <hi>and are to he ſold at his ſhop at the</hi> Angel <hi>in</hi> Cornhill.</head>
            <p n="1">1. TImes Treaſury, or Academy for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, for their accomoliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in arguments of diſcourſe, habit, faſhion; ſummed up all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Character of Honour: By <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Eſq;</p>
            <p n="2">2. B. <hi>Morton</hi> on the Sacrament:</p>
            <p n="3">3. That excellent piece of Phyſiog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy and Chiromancy, Metopoſcopy, the Symmetrical Proportions and ſignal Moles of the Body, the ſubject of Dreams: to which is added the Art of Memory: By <hi>R.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Theatrum Chemicum Britanicum,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining ſeveral Poetical pieces of our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Engliſh Philoſophers, which have written the Hermetick Myſteries in their ancient language: By the truly noble <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias Aſhmole</hi> Eſq;</p>
            <p n="5">5. Chiromancy: or the Art of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vining by the Lines ingraven in the hand of Man by Dame Nature, in 19. Geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; with a learned Diſcourſe of the ſoul of the World: By <hi>Geo. Wharton,</hi> Eſq;
<pb facs="tcp:170252:105"/>and gathered out of Scripture, Councils; &amp; ancient Fathers, in anſwer to D. <hi>Vanes loſt ſheep returned home:</hi> By <hi>Edward Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenhale,</hi> Eſq;</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Tactometrica,</hi> or the Geometrie of Regulars, after a new manner, in Solids: with uſeful Experiments, with new Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments, never before extant, for Gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging; a work uſeful for all that are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in the Art Metrical: By <hi>John Weyberd,</hi> Dr. in Phyſick.</p>
            <p n="8">8. An <hi>Aſtrological</hi> Diſcourſe, with <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematical</hi> Demonſtrations, proving the influence of the Planets and fixed Stars upon Elementary bodies: By Sir <hi>Chr. Heydon,</hi> Knight.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>Magick Aſtrologie</hi> vindicated by <hi>H. Warren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Cataſtrophe Magnatum:</hi> By <hi>N. Culpeper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. Ephemerides for the year 1652. by <hi>N. Culpeper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. Judicial <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> vindicated, and Demonologie confuted: By <hi>W. Ramſey,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p n="13">13. The Hiſtory of the Golden Aſſe.</p>
            <p n="14">14. The painting of the Ancients, the beginning, progreſſe, and conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of that noble <hi>Art.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170252:106"/>
            <p n="15">15. <hi>Wilsfords</hi> Arithmetick, made plain to the eaſieſt capacity, in two books, <hi>viz.</hi> Natural and Decimal; being moſt uſeful for all Gentlemen. Merchants, Shopkeepers, all others; by <hi>Tho. Wilsford,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p n="13">13. <hi>Adam</hi> in <hi>Eden,</hi> the Paradiſeof Plants, Deſcription of all our Engliſh Plants, wilde or otherwiſe, with their ſignatures applied to the parts of the body of Man, with their Phyſical uſe, that a man may be his own Phyſitian, the Ingredients being to be had in every field and garden; made publique by <hi>W. Coles,</hi> M.D. for the benefit of all Engliſh men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe Books will he publiſhed ſpeedily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15. The Perfect Cook, A right method of the Art of Cookery, reſtoring the whole pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice to a more refined way then was ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore extant.</p>
            <p n="16">16. Caſtellus <hi>Lexicon medicum,</hi> being a Dicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onary explaining all the terms, both in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, and Chyrurgery, Tranſlated by <hi>J.D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. <hi>Timothies vade mecum,</hi> or a pocket com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion for the ſons of the Prophets, wherein are Treated of matters appertaining to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and ſuch as intend for the Miniſtry; by <hi>T. Crave.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18. The Treaſury of the ſoul.</p>
            <p n="19">19. <hi>Frambeſorius,</hi> His ſcholia Medica; alſo the Treatiſe of ſeavers made Engliſh, by <hi>J.D.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
